So, let's talk about Quality Assurance:
Automated Testing.
DEV: Wait, you mean I'm going to have
to write code to test my code
to make sure that the
code I wrote is doing what it's
supposed to be doing?
Man, that's going to take double the
time it takes me to execute on
the project!
Why are you going to make me
do this, mang?!
NARRATION: Yes, but you're going to want to
include testing, unit and functional
within your project because
it can document what your code does
so that others coming into the project
can look at
the tests and see how specific functions
were implemented if you're providing APIs.
How specific functions are to perform
certain tasks if you are writing some
kind of a pipeline.
It can help people better understand
what your code is all about if
they have some tests
that they can go through and look
at and see what some mock inputs
may look like and what
some expected outputs could be.
You ever fall into a situation where
you got that one developer, that one
server, that
one process, that one thing that everybody
uses, that everybody does, and when
it goes
down, it's a big fire, it's a
big deal, it's a big blocker to
people getting stuff done?
Well, if you have proper testing in
place, then it coerces you to have
modular designs
such that you'll be able to test
a specific pipeline, a specific function,
or a specific
operation, do one thing and do it
well inside your code, your project,
whatever it is you're
building.
And 3rd: oh, you are going to
love this one! You ever get those
business requirements
that don't quite make sense and somebody's
like, yeah, can you just get that done?
Well, if you have test cases in
place, then it kind of sort of
coerces people to make
sure that they more clearly define
their required outcomes or specific
details that they need
to be handled during the course of
the project, not after it, while it
needs to be reviewed.
And fourth, it just kind of sort
of ties into the third one, which
ties into the second
one, and that is, it makes sure
that the test cases that you create,
CYA, we want to cover
and make sure you're good, okay?
So that way, when somebody comes back
and says, well, why didn't it work
this way?
Well, I didn't test it this way,
meaning it wasn't intended to be used
this way.
The test cases that I wrote were
exhaustive as per the business requirements
that you
gave to me at the time, and
therefore, it is not my fault that
your program doesn't
work to specification because it wasn't
in the specifications.
So yes, testing will slow down the project.
That is by design, that is for
intention, that is so you slow down
to speed up.
If you're in an environment where
it seems like it's fast paced and
it shouldn't be fast
paced, because it's, you know, something
that doesn't involve life and death,
you know,
it's a project or some kind of
code that you're working on that can
take the time to sit back
and strategically think through a
product that is actually going to
survive in the market
and sustain itself for the long term,
or if we're just standing up something
really quick
because somebody thought it'd be a
great idea.
It's good to know when you have
metrics that are built into the application,
when you
actually get feedback that suggests
that this is a good thing and
you're able to bake that
into the solution as you bring all
that data and analytics back.
So yes, testing is going to slow
your project down just a little bit,
not by that much,
because while at first it may seem
like a lot, over the longer term,
it'll start to taper
down and the benefits you'll be reaping
from it will be less and less
because you'll be
more consistent and methodical about
how you're going to implement your solution.
Software does have a taper off limit.
It's not like you're going to be
building on a project forever.
At some point, it gets to a
place where it can be just simply maintained.
And so testing can help you get
there by making sure that you're just
a little more rigid
and disciplined and deliberate in
your software designs rather than
creating hodgepodge trees
that only one person can support.
Makes them more modular so other people
can jump on board and provide support
as well.