All right, I was gonna wait until
this was finished before I told the
story about it
But cat's out of the bag, you
already know it's here
So I can go ahead and tell
you what this means now
And I can always remake this video
once I finally get the coloring finished
in. This is incomplete
I will go back in December so
that I can have this finished off.
But what is it? And what does
it mean to me?
My name is Markizano Draconus and
that's the alias I go by on
the internet
Everybody should know me by this name
by now because this is the story
that I need to tell
This is called an Altrish
It is a symbol and a sigil
that I have created to represent me
and everything it is I stand for.
The gold bars represents the foundations
upon which we stand the light that
is contained within us all and
That upon which we may use as
a platform to ascend
It starts off in the darkness where
we are all shrouded in mystery, unknowing,
as we enter into this world and
cross into that veil
whatever that is and
Oftentimes just like a seed placed
into the ground
Sometimes you just need to continue
moving and continue trudging forward
and keep ascending until you reach
the light
Which is the enlightenment. The colors
represents the purple and the blue
to represent
The crown and the third eye respectively
of the chakras that are oftentimes
Suppressed in order to keep us in
this survival state
the arrow pointing up represents the
ascendance that is available to us
all and also
it
It just asserts that belief that I
have within me that
Every single human being has value
and that this is applicable to all
of us
This is
It's a
culmination of a unique hand sign
that I had created
Way back when I was like 7-8
years old as I was trying
to piece together what unique symbol
sigil something
Whatever can I use that represents
me and this is what I came
up with and this is what came back
And I've been using this for years
So even though it looks like a
crypto whatever... Welcome. You must
be new here
This has been around since I was
like 7-8 years old
I have paper documents that I've been
writing since school that I've got
this sigil on it
so this is basically a representation
of that the ascendance that is available
to us all to reach whatever level of
Enlightenment that is possible
And I also believe a belief system
is something that is extremely unique
to every single one of us
there is no single belief system that
is exactly the same and
Religion was just a tool a means
by which we use to describe
something so that we can try and
make some sense of it because this
ethereal states this
Theta this idea of what is life
that isn't the measurable physical
things we can put our hands on
and measure here
There's more to it that we don't
understand and we're just trying to
use the tools available available
to us to describe it
And so this is this is that
this is the representation of
The possibilities that are that are
contained within a soul. We all start
in the shadows. We all try to
ascend to the light
We all try to find our level
of enlightenment and I encourage that
of the third eye and the crown
Because I value intelligence. I value
minds that think beyond just the social
programmings that we experience in
a day-to-day
I am erudite, but I am also
candor. I also try to be abnegant
and I'd like to think I'm dauntless
But most of all I try to
keep amnity in my heart as well. I
draw from so many elements and
This just existed long before that
so I just wanted to share that
with you so that you knew
Who's this Markizano guy? Why is he
here? And what is he doing all
this stuff for?
It's a projection of the self
You have value too.