So, I just asked ChatGPT to help
me out with some real estate questions
that I've got here
and I just wanted to highlight some
things for you here.
I asked ChatGPT first if it could
tell me what the average rate is
for tax properties
in Dallas and it turns out
2.18% is about the average in
North Dallas County.
Okay, cool.
So let's assume we got a $285,000
house with a $20,000 payment.
And the interest is going to be
a 7.54% fixed for 30 years.
What will the payments look like?
Well, I was kind of shocked it
actually gave me the equations and
talked it through.
The monthly payments for
just the house by itself is going
to be $1854.76.
So with that in mind, let's say
we had a 2.2% property
tax in PMI until the loan has
20% equity.
What would the payments be then?
Because I know I'm not (dumb) -- I know
it ain't as simple as just paying
on the house.
You also got taxes, insurance and
insurance on top of the insurance
and well, I was grateful
that we went through, you know, all
of that as well and came to
$2,487.
Holy cow!
I'm currently doing $1,572 for my
apartment and this is a level of
lifestyle inflation
that I have just not seen before.
How in the world?
So, just to entertain the idea, let's
say we drop the rates back down
to 3.25%.
What could that do to the monthly payments?
Well, with PMI, insurance, taxes and
all that fun stuff, it would drop
the monthly
payments down to $1,786, which is
actually what I'm targeting.
So I'm not wrong for looking for
houses that are less than $285 because
with a $20,000
down payment and let's say I get
to refinance with interest rates at
a more reasonable amount,
you know, 5 or 7 years from
now, well, that's going to save me
a ton of money later.
So here's a breakdown, I just asked
you to put together a table of
what would happen
for various house prices, what it
would take for the $20,000 down
payment that would be
put in for it and then what
would the monthly payments just look like.
I understand these are just estimates,
I know there's all kinds of other
stuff to consider
but just a ballpark figure to say,
yeah, you buy a 3.25% house,
you're going to be paying
$2,100 a month.
After tax tags and title, that's going
to be $2,900 a month.
That's almost $3,000, like that's
twice the rent that I pay right
now for a 3.25% house
and a $20,000 down payment, that's
just... WoW.
So these values would be greatly affected
if interest rates were lower.
I noticed the one thing that really
triggered a lower monthly payment
is if the interest
rates were lower.
So everybody's talking about Wall
Street's buying up houses and the
housing market crash
or whatever, blah blah blah, no, it's
interest rates.
They're really high right now and
it's causing the monthly payments
on houses to be really
high, which is what's causing people
to not want to move around as
far as real estate
is concerned.
Now, I'm not saying that that's every
house deal ever, but like I'm just
a guy who works
in IT, who's been living in an
apartment for the last five years
and is ready to move
into a house.
I've, you know, been in the same
place and it just makes sense.
It's like, why not?
I'm going to be here a while,
so why not?
And as I really try to step
into it, holy cow, wow, ummmm...