Wait a minute... if you have a
variable set to True, if a condition,
else false, why not
just coerce the condition to a boolean???
like.... isn't that easier?
Wait a minute, instead of assigning
a variable to a value like this,
iterating over an array
so that you can access the key...
Why not just use enumerate()?
It will give you
the array with the index as part
of something you can use in a
compound for loop.
(This is Python, by the way.)
Wait a minute...
instead of opening a file descriptor
and holding the variable in memory
and writing some data to disk,
especially if your intention is just
to touch the file or write just
a simple byte or two to it
as well, why not just open the file
and write to it directly? If Python
doesn't have a variable to store the
file descriptor,
it'll close the file descriptor. You
can test this out inside of the interpreter.
And you knew that there were different
ways in which you could format the
same string, right?
I mean, you can use the plus
operator to combine variables and strings,
provided the data types match. You
could do integers, which you might
get an error.
You could also use the percent notation.
This is, Python2 friendly.
Python3 does
introduce the f"" thing, which
creates a format. Strings by default
have this "".format()
embedded with them. And this
f"" basically makes it so that
that function is
automatically applied to the string.
This is what I would call "Syntax
Sugar" for that "".format()
that would replace what those do.
You knew that, right? :P
And then number five is just
going to be an explainer because I --
it'd be a lot of code to
write and I don't have an active
screenshot that I could take and overlay
here. But the idea is if you
find yourself taking a
block of code and copying and pasting
that everywhere, you should probably
paste it
into a function, call the function
instead. And whatever variables that
function needs
provide them as arguments to the function.
And you'll be surprised how much less
you have to
copy and paste code and can instead
just call the function. But you're
a professional, you're an
expert, you already knew that, right?
If not, can I have one of
these in return? Thank you! =D