oh man this is too cool!
no it's not me... I know I'm
awesome, but if you if you...
if you just...
check out the gisty thingies and you
go to find
one of my gisty thingies it talks
about voice2text: Yeah this here
github
gisty thingy talks about some fun
stuff that you can do. You can
take this Dockerfile,
stash it in a file. Take
this requirements.txt stash it in a file
take the
voice2text.py stash it in
a file put the three of those
in a directory run
docker-build and you got yourself
a docker image run docker run you
got
yourself a docker tool that'll let
you do voice to text I also
happen to have
blogged about it all right so this
is a quick once over of the
output that you
can expect from it once you run
the docker command what it's gonna
do is
it'll extract the audio from the video
file that you gave it or the
audio file
that you gave it and it'll attempt
to translate all of that voice into
text
you can optionally output the results
to an SRT file or you can
output it so that
it encodes it directly into the video
as a subtitle stream. I personally
like to
extract them out to an SRT file
I'll do a once over just to
make sure everything
translated over correctly and then
I'll inscribe them onto the video
itself
through another filter using subtitles
in FFmpeg. Credits to Guillaume for
putting together Faster Whisper this
project is awesome I just am standing
on
the shoulders of giants in this case
all I did was wrap this code
up inside of a
docker container so that I could have
this application itself in its own
self-contained space what this lets
me do is automatically translate and
add
subtitles to my videos in a streamlined
fashion that does not require me to
send
them up to some cloud to pay
for open AI and pay for CapCode
possibly pay for
CapCut if they ever turn that into
a paid service only thing or something
else you know I can control and
manage and do all of that locally
also not to
mention it is a lot more accurate
than CapCut and that's one of the
first
principles maintain your own data.