The history of the tablets translated
in the following pages is strange
and beyond the
belief of modern scientists.
Their antiquity is stupendous, dating
back some 36,000 years BC.
The writer is Thoth, an Atlantean
priest-king who founded a colony in
ancient Egypt after
the sinking of the mother country.
He was the builder of the Great
Pyramid of Giza, erroneously attributed
to Cheops.
In it he incorporated his knowledge
of the ancient wisdom and also securely secreted
records and instruments of ancient Atlantis.
For some 16,000 years he ruled
the ancient race of Egypt, from approximately
52,000 BC
to 36,000 BC.
At that time, the ancient barbarous
race among which he and his followers
had settled had
been raised to a high degree of civilization.
Thoth was an immortal, that is, he
had conquered death, passing only
when he willed and even
then not through death.
His vast wisdom made him ruler over
the various Atlantean colonies, including
the ones in
South and Central America.
When the time came for him to
leave Egypt, he erected the Great
Pyramid over the entrance
to the Great Halls of Amenti, placed
in it his records and appointed guards
for his
secrets from among the highest of
his people.
In later times, the descendants of
these guards became the Pyramid Priest,
by which Thoth
was deified as the God of Wisdom,
the Recorder, by those in the Age
of Darkness which followed
his passing.
In legend, the Halls of Amenti became
the Underworld, the Halls of the Gods,
where the
soul passed after death for judgment.
During later ages, the ego of Thoth
passed into the bodies of men in
the manner described
in the tablets.
As such, he incarnated three times,
in his last being known as Hermes
the Thrice-Born.
In this incarnation, he left the writings
known to modern occultists as the Emerald
Tablets, a later and far lesser exposition
of the ancient mysteries.
The tablets translated in this work
are ten which were left in the
Great Pyramid in the
custody of the Pyramid Priest.
The ten are divided into thirteen
parts for the sake of convenience.
The last two are so great and
far-reaching in their import that
at present it is forbidden
to release them to the world at large.
However, in those contained herein
are secrets which will prove of inestimable
value to the
serious student.
They should be read not once, but
a hundred times for only thus can
the true meaning be
revealed.
A casual reading will give glimpses
of beauty, but more intensive study
will open avenues
of wisdom to the seeker.
But now, a word as to how
these mighty secrets came to be revealed
to modern man after being
hidden so long.
Some thirteen hundred years B.C.,
Egypt, the ancient Khem, was in turmoil
and many delegations
of priests were sent to other parts
of the world.
Among these were some of the Pyramid
Priests who carried with them the
Emerald Tablets
as a talisman by which they could
exercise authority over the less advanced priestcraft
of races descended from other Atlantean colonies.
The tablets were understood from legend
to give the bearer authority from Thoth.
The particular group of priests bearing
the tablets immigrated to South America where
they found a flourishing race, the
Maya, who remembered much of the ancient wisdom.
Among these, the priests settled and remained.
In the tenth century, the Maya had
thoroughly settled the Yucatan, and
the tablets were
placed beneath the altar of one of
the great temples of the sun god.
After the conquest of the Maya by
the Spaniards, the cities were abandoned
and the treasures
of the temples forgotten.
It should be understood that the Great
Pyramid of Egypt has been, and still
is a temple of
initiation into the mysteries.
Jesus, Solomon, Apollonius, and others
were initiated there.
The writer, who has a connection with
the Great White Lodge, which also
works through
the Pyramid Priesthood, was instructed
to recover and return to the Great
Pyramid the
ancient tablets.
This, after adventures which need
not be detailed here, was accomplished.
Before returning them, he was given
permission to translate and retain
a copy of the wisdom
engraved on the tablets.
This was done in 1925, and only
now has permission been given for
part to be published.
It is expected that many will scoff,
yet the true student will read between
the lines and
gain wisdom.
If the light is in you, the
light which is engraved in these tablets
will respond.
Now, a word as to the material
aspect of the tablets.
They consist of twelve tablets of
emerald green formed from a substance
created through
an alchemical transmutation.
They are imperishable, resistant to
all elements and substances.
In effect, the atomic and cellular
structure is fixed, no change ever
taking place.
In this respect, they violate the
material law of ionization.
Upon them are engraved characters
in the ancient Atlantean language.
Characters which respond to attuned
thought waves, releasing the associated
mental vibration
in the mind of the reader.
The tablets are fastened together
with hoops of golden-colored alloy
suspended from a rod
of the same material.
So much for the material appearance.
The wisdom contained therein is the
foundation of the ancient mysteries,
and for the one
who reads with open eyes and mind,
his wisdom shall be increased a hundredfold.
Read, believe or not, but read, and
the vibration found therein will awaken
a response in your
soul.
In cosmic harmony, Duriel, Supreme
Voice of the Brotherhood.
In the following pages, I will reveal
some of the mysteries which as yet
have only been
touched upon lightly either by myself,
or other teachers or students of truth.
Man's search for understanding of
the laws which regulate his life have
been unending.
Yet, always, just beyond the veil
which shields the higher planes from
material man's vision,
the truth has existed, ready to be
assimilated by those who enlarge their
vision by turning
inward, not outward, in their search.
In the silence of material senses
lies the key to the unveiling of wisdom.
He who talks does not know.
He who knows does not talk.
The highest knowledge is unutterable,
for it exists as an entity in
lanes which transcend
all material words or symbols.
All symbols are but keys to doors
leading to truths, and many times
the door is not
opened because the key seems so great
that the things which are beyond it
are not visible.
If we can understand that all keys,
all material symbols or manifestations
are but extensions
of a great law and truth, we
will begin to develop the vision which
will enable us to
penetrate beyond the veil.
All things in all universes move according
to law, and the law which regulates
the movement
of the planets is no more immutable
than the law which regulates the material expressions
of man.
One of the greatest of all cosmic
laws is that which is responsible
for the formation
of man as a material being.
The great aim of the mystery schools
of all ages has been to reveal
the workings of the
law which connect man the material
and man the spiritual.
The connecting link between the material
man and the spiritual man is the intellectual
man, for the mind partakes of both
the material and immaterial qualities.
The aspirant for higher knowledge
must develop the intellectual side
of his nature and so
strengthen his will that it is able
to concentrate all powers of his being
on and in the plane
he desires.
The great search for light, life and
love only begins on the material plane.
Carried to its ultimate, its final
goal is complete oneness with the
universal consciousness.
The foundation in the material is
the first step.
Then comes the higher goal of spiritual attainment.
In the following pages I will give
an interpretation of the Emerald Tablets
and their secret, hidden
and esoteric meanings.
Concealed in the words of Thoth are
many meanings that do not appear on
the surface.
Light of knowledge brought to bear
upon the tablets will open many new
fields for thought.
Read and be wise, but only if
the light of your own consciousness
awakens the deep-seated
understanding which is an inherent
quality of the soul.
In the threefold light, Duryodhana.
I, Thoth the Atlantean, Master of
Mysteries, Keeper of Records, Mighty
King, Magician
living from generation to generation,
being about to pass into the halls
of Amenti, set
down for the guidance of those that
are to come after, these records of
the mighty wisdom
of Great Atlantis.
In the great city of Kiur on
the island of Undal, in a time
far past, I began this incarnation.
Not as the little men of the
present age did the mighty ones of
Atlantis live and die,
but rather from eon to eon did
they renew their life in the halls
of Amenti where the
river of life flows eternally onward.
A hundred times ten have I descended
the dark way that led into light,
and as many times
have I ascended from the darkness
into the light, my strength and power renewed.
Now for a time I descend, and
the men of Khem shall know me
no more.
But in a time yet unborn will
I rise again, mighty and potent, requiring
an accounting
of those left behind me.
Then beware, O men of Khem, if
ye have falsely betrayed my teaching,
for I shall cast ye
down from your estate into the darkness
of the caves from whence ye came.
Betray not my secrets to the men
of the north, or the men of
the south, lest my curse fall
upon ye.
Remember and heed my words, for surely
I will return again and require of
thee that which
ye guard.
Ay, even from beyond time and from
beyond death will I return, rewarding
or punishing
as ye have requitted your trust.
Great were my people in the ancient
days, great beyond the conception
of the little
people now around me, knowing the
wisdom of old, seeking far within
the heart of infinity
knowledge that belonged to earth's youth.
Wise were we with the wisdom of
the children of light who dwelt among
us, strong were we
with the power drawn from the eternal
fire, and all of these, greatest among
the children
of men was my father, Thothme, keeper
of the great temple, link between
the children
of light who dwelt within the temple,
and the races of men who inhabited
the ten islands,
mouthpiece, after the three, of the
dweller of Unal, speaking to the kings
with the voice
that must be obeyed.
Grew I there from a child into
manhood, being taught by my father
the elder mysteries, until
in time there grew within the fire
of wisdom, until it burst into a
consuming flame.
Nought desired I but the attainment
of wisdom, until on a great day
the command came from
the dweller of the temple that I
be brought before him, few there were
among the children
of men who had looked upon that
mighty face and lived, for not as
the sons of men are the
children of light when they are not
incarnate in a physical body.
Chosen was I from the sons of
men, taught by the dweller so that
his purposes might
be fulfilled, purposes yet unborn
in the womb of time.
Long ages I dwelt in the temple,
learning ever and yet ever more wisdom,
until I too
approached the light emitted from
the great fire.
Taught me he the path to Amenti,
the underworld where the great king
sits upon his throne
of might.
Deep I bowed in homage before the
lords of life and the lords of
death, receiving as
my gift the key of life.
Free was I of the halls of
Amenti, bound not by death to the
circle of life.
Far to the stars I journeyed until
space and time became as naught.
Then having drunk deep of the cup
of wisdom, I looked into the hearts
of men, and there
I found greater mysteries and was
glad, for only in the search for
truth could my soul
be stilled and the flame within be quenched.
Down through the ages I lived, seeing
those around me taste of the cup
of death and return
again in the light of life.
Gradually from the kingdoms of Atlantis
passed ways of consciousness that
had been one with
me, only to be replaced by spawn
of a lower star.
In obedience to the law, the word
of the master grew into flower.
Downward into the darkness turned
the thoughts of the Atlanteans, until
at last in this wrath
arose from his aguanti the dweller.
Speaking the word, calling the power,
deep in earth's heart the sons of
Amenti heard,
and hearing, directing the changing
of the flower of fire that burns
eternally, changing
and shifting, using the logos, until
the great fire changed its direction.
Over the world then broke the great
waters, drowning and sinking, changing
earth's balance
until only the temple of light was
left standing on the great mountain
on Undal, still rising
out of the water.
Some there were who were living, saved
from the rush of the fountains.
Called to me then the master, saying,
Gather ye together my people.
Take them by the arch ye have
learned of far across the waters,
until ye reach the land
of the hairy barbarians, dwelling
in caves of the desert.
Follow there the plan that ye know of.
Gathered I then my people, and entered
the great ship of the master.
Upward we rose into the morning.
Dark beneath us lay the temple, suddenly
over it rose the waters, vanished
from earth, until
the time appointed was the great temple.
Fast we fled toward the sun of
the morning, until beneath us lay
the land of the children
of Khem.
Raging, they came with cudgels and
spears, lifted in anger, seeking to
slay and utterly
destroy the sons of Atlantis.
Then raised I my staff, and directed
a ray of vibration, striking them
still in their
tracks as fragments of stone of the mountain.
Then spoke I to them in words
calm and peaceful, telling them of
the might of Atlantis, saying
we were children of the sun and
its messengers.
Cowled I them by my display of
magic science, until at my feet they
grovelled, when I released
them.
Long dwelt we in the land of
Khem, long and yet long again, until
obeying the commands
of the master, who while sleeping
yet lives eternally, I sent from me
the sons of Atlantis,
sent them in many directions, that
from the womb of time wisdom might
rise again in her
children.
Long time dwelt I in the land
of Khem, doing great works by the
wisdom within me.
Upward grew into the light of knowledge
the children of Khem, watered by the
rains of
my wisdom.
Blasted I then a path to Amenti,
so that I might retain my powers,
living from age to
age a son of Atlantis, keeping the
wisdom, preserving the records.
Great grew the sons of Khem, conquering
the people around them, growing slowly upwards
in soul force.
Now for a time I go from
among them into the dark halls of
Amenti, deep in the halls of
the earth, before the lords of the
powers, face to face once again with
the dweller.
Raised I high over the entrance a
doorway, a gateway leading down to Amenti.
Few there would be with courage to
dare it, few pass the portal to
dark Amenti.
Raised over the passage I a mighty
pyramid, using the power that overcomes
earth force.
Deep and yet deeper place I a
force house or chamber, from it carved
I a circular passage
reaching almost to the great summit.
There in the apex set I the
crystal, sending the ray into the
time space, drawing the force
from out of the ether, concentrating
upon the gateway to Amenti.
Other chambers I built and left vacant
to all seeming yet hidden within them
are the
keys to Amenti.
He who in courage would dare the
dark realms, let him be purified first
by long fasting.
Lie in the sarcophagus of stone in
my chamber, then reveal I to him
the great mysteries.
Soon shall he follow to where I
shall meet him, even in the darkness
of earth shall I
meet him, I, Thoth, lord of wisdom,
meet him and hold him and dwell
with him always.
Built I the great pyramid, patterned
after the pyramid of earth force,
burning eternally
so that it too might remain through
the ages.
In it I built my knowledge of
magic science so that I might be
here when again I return
from Amenti, I, while I sleep in
the halls of Amenti my soul roaming
free will incarnate,
dwell among men in this form or another.
Emissary on earth am I of the
dweller, fulfilling his commands so
many might be lifted.
Now return I to the halls of
Amenti, leaving behind me some of
my wisdom.
Preserve ye and keep ye the command
of the dweller.
Lift ever upwards your eyes toward
the light.
Surely in time ye are one with
the master, surely by right ye are
one with the master,
surely by right ye are one with
the all.
Now I depart from ye, know my
commandments, keep them and be them,
and I will be with
you, helping and guiding you into
the light.
Now before me opens the portal.
Go I down in the darkness of
the night.
Deep in earth's heart lie the halls
of Amenti, far neath the islands of
sunken Atlantis,
halls of the dead and halls of
the living, bathed in fire of the
infinite all.
Far in a past time, lost in
the space-time, the children of light
looked down on the world,
seeing the children of men in their
bondage, bound by the force that came
from beyond.
Knew they that only by freedom from
bondage could man ever rise from earth
to the sun.
Down they descended and created bodies,
taking the semblances of men as their own.
The masters of everything said after
their forming,
We are they who were formed from
the space-dust, partaking of life
from the infinite all,
living in the world as children of
men, like and yet unlike the children
of men.
Then for a dwelling-place far neath
the earth-crust blasted great spaces
they by their power,
spaces apart from the children of
men, surrounded them by forces and power,
shielded from harm they the halls
of the dead.
Side by side then placed they other
spaces, filled them with life and
with light from above.
Builded they then the halls of Amenti,
that they might dwell eternally there,
living with life to eternity's end.
Thirty and two were there of the
children, sons of lights who had come
among men,
seeking to free from the bondage of
darkness those who were bound by the
force from beyond.
Deep in the halls of life grew
a flower, flaming, expanding, driving
backward the night.
Placed in the center a ray of
great potence, life-giving, light-giving,
filling with power all who came near it.
Placed they around it thrones two
and thirty, places for each of the
children of light,
placed so that they were bathed in
the radiance filled with the life
from the eternal light.
There time after time placed they
their first created bodies so that
they might be filled
with the spirit of life.
One hundred years out of each thousand
must the life-giving light flame forth
on their bodies,
quickening, awakening the spirit of life.
There in the circle from aeon to
aeon sit the great masters,
living a life not known among men.
There in the halls of life they
lie sleeping, free flows their soul
through the bodies of men.
Time after time, while their bodies
lie sleeping, incarnate they in the
bodies of men,
teaching and guiding onward and upward,
out of the darkness into the light.
There in the hall of life, filled
with their wisdom, known not to the
races of man,
living forever neath the cold fire
of life, sit the children of light.
Times there are when they awaken,
come from the depths to be lights
among men,
infinite they among finite.
He who by progress has grown from
the darkness, lifted himself from
the night into light,
free is he made of the halls
of Amenti, free of the flower of
light and of life.
Guided he then by wisdom and knowledge
passes from men to the master of life.
There he may dwell as one with
the masters, free from the bonds of
the darkness of night.
Seated within the flower of radiance
sit seven lords from the space-times
above us,
helping and guiding through infinite
wisdom the pathway through the time
of the children of men.
Mighty and strange they, veiled with
their power, silent, all-knowing,
drawing the life-force, different,
yet one with the children of men.
Ay, different, and yet one with the
children of light.
Custodians and watchers of the force
of man's bondage, ready to loose when
the light has been
reached, first and most mighty sits
the veiled presence, lord of lords,
the infinite nine,
over the other from each cosmic cycle,
weighing and watching the progress
of men.
Under he sits the lord of the
cycles, three, four, five, and six,
seven, eight,
each with his mission, each with his
power, guiding, directing the destiny
of man.
There sit they, mighty and potent,
free of all time and space, not
of this world they,
yet akin to it, elder brothers they
of the children of men, judging and weighing,
they with their wisdom, watching the
progress of light among men.
There before them was I led by
the dweller, watched him blend with
one from above,
then from he came forth a voice
saying, Great art thou thought among
children of men,
free henceforth of the halls of Amenti,
master of life among children of men.
Taste not of death except as thou
will it, drink thou of life to
eternity's end,
henceforth forever is life, thine
for the taking, henceforth is death
at the call of thy hand.
Dwell here or leave here when thou
desirest, free is Amenti to the son
of man.
Take thou up life in what form
thou desirest, child of the light
that has grown among men.
Choose thou thy work, for all should,
must labor, never be free from the
pathway of light.
One step thou hast gained on the
long pathway upward, infinite now
is the mountain of light.
Each step thou taketh, but heightens
the mountain, all of thy progress
but lengthens the goal.
Approach ye ever the infinite wisdom,
ever before thee recedes the goal,
free are ye made
now of the halls of Amenti to
walk hand in hand with the lords
of the world, one in one purpose
working together, bringers of light
to the children of men. Then from
his throne came
one of his masters, taking my hand
and leading me onward through all
the halls of the deep hidden
land. Led he me through the halls
of Amenti, showing the mysteries that
are known not to man.
Through the dark passage downward
he led me, into the hall where
sits the dark death,
vast as space lay the great hall
before me, walled by darkness but
yet filled with light.
Before me arose a great throne of
darkness, veiled on it set a figure
of night,
darker than darkness set the great
figure, dark with a darkness not of
the night.
Before it then paused the master,
speaking the word that brings about
life, saying,
O master of darkness, guide of the
way from life unto life, before thee
I bring a sun of the
morning, touch him not ever with the
power of night, call not his flame
to the darkness of
night, know him and see him, one
of our brothers lifted from darkness
into the light, release
thou his flame from its bondage, free
let it flame through the darkness
of night.
Raised then the hand of the figure
forth came a flame that grew clear
and bright,
rolled back swiftly the curtain of
darkness, unveiled the hall from the
darkness of night,
then grew in the great space before
me flame after flame from the veil
of the night.
Uncounted millions leaped they before
me, some flaming forth as flowers
of fire,
others there were that shed a dim
radiance, flowing but faintly from
out of the night,
some there were that faded swiftly,
others that grew from a small spark
of light,
each surrounded by its dim veil of
darkness, yet flaming with light that
could never be quenched,
coming and going like fireflies in
springtime, filled they with space,
with light and with life.
I, death, come, and yet I remain
not, for life eternal exists in the all,
only an obstacle I in the pathway,
quick to be conquered by the infinite light.
Awaken, O flame that burns ever inward,
flame forth and conquer the veil of
the night.
Then in the midst of the flames
in the darkness grew there one that
drove forth the night,
flaming, expanding, ever brighter,
until at last was nothing but light.
Then spoke my guide, the voice of
the Master,
See your own soul as it grows
in the light, free now forever from
the Lord of the night.
Forward he led me through many great
spaces filled with the mysteries of
the children of light,
mysteries that man may never yet know
of until he, too, is a son
of the light.
Backward then he led me into the
light of the hall of the light,
knelt I then before the great Masters,
Lords of all from the cycles above,
spoke he then with words of great
power, saying,
Thou hast been made free of the
halls of Amenti, choose thou thy work
among the children of men.
Then spoke I, O great Master, let
me be a teacher of men,
leading them onward and upward until
they, too, are lights among men,
freed from the veil of the night
that surrounds them,
flaming with light that shall shine
among men.
Spoke to me then the voice,
Go as ye will, so be it
decreed. Master are ye of your destiny,
free to take or reject at will.
Take ye the power, take ye the wisdom.
Shine as a light among the children
of men.
Upward then led me the dweller, dwelt
I again among children of men,
teaching and showing some of my wisdom,
son of the light, a fire among men.
Now again I tread the path downward,
seeking the light in the darkness
of night.
Hold ye and keep ye, preserve my
record, guide shall it be to the
children of men.
I, Thoth, the Atlantean, give of my
wisdom, give of my knowledge, give
of my power,
freely I give to the children of
men. Give that they, too, might have
wisdom to shine
through the world from the veil of
the night. Wisdom is power, and power
is wisdom,
one with each other, perfecting the
whole. Be thou not proud, O man,
in thy wisdom.
Discourse with the ignorant as well
as the wise.
If one comes to thee full of
knowledge, listen and heed, for wisdom
is all.
Keep thou not silent when evil is
spoken, for truth like the sunlight
shines above all.
He who oversteppeth the law shall
be punished, for only through law
comes the freedom of men.
Follow thine heart during thy lifetime.
Do thou more than is commanded of thee.
When thou hast gained riches, follow
thou thine heart, for all these are
of no avail
if thine heart be weary. Diminish
thou not the time of following thine heart.
It is abhorred of the soul.
They that are guided go not astray,
but they that are lost cannot find
a straight path.
If thou go among men, make for
thyself love the beginning and end
of the heart.
If one cometh unto thee for counsel,
let him speak freely,
that the thing for which he hath
come to thee may be done.
If he hesitates to open his heart
to thee, it is because thou, the
judge, doeth the wrong.
Repeat thou not extravagant speech,
neither listen thou to it,
for it is the utterance of one
not in equilibrium. Speak thou not
of it,
so that he before thee may know
wisdom. Silence is of great profit.
An abundance of speech profiteth nothing.
Exalt not thine heart above the children
of men,
lest it be brought lower than the dust.
If thou be great among men, be
honored for knowledge and gentleness.
If thou seekest to know the nature
of a friend, ask not his companion,
but pass a time alone with
him. Debate with him, testing his
heart by his words and his bearing.
That which goeth into the storehouse
must come forth,
and the things that are thine must
be shared with a friend.
Knowledge is regarded by the fool
as ignorance, and the things that
are profitable are to him
hurtful. He liveth in death, it is
therefore his food.
The wise man lets his heart overflow,
but keeps silent his mouth.
O man, list to the voice of
wisdom, list to the voice of light.
Mysteries there are in the cosmos
that unveiled filled the world with
their light.
Let he who would be free from
the bonds of darkness first divine
the material from the
immaterial, the fire from the earth.
For know ye that as earth descends
to earth,
so also fire ascends into fire and
becomes one with fire.
He who knows the fire that is
within himself shall ascend until
the eternal fire
and dwell in it eternally. Fire, the
inner fire,
is the most potent of all force
for it overcometh all things and penetrates
to all things of the
earth. Man supports himself only on
that which
resists, so earth must resist man
else he existeth not.
All eyes do not see with the
same vision. For to one an object
appears of one form
and color, and to a different eye
of another. So also the infinite fire,
changing from color
to color, is never the same from
day to day. Thus speak I, Thoth,
of my wisdom.
For man is a fire burning bright
through the night, never is quenched
in the veil of the
darkness, never is quenched by the
veil of the night.
Hark ye, O man, and list to
this wisdom. Where do name and form cease?
Only in consciousness, invisible,
an infinite force of radiance bright.
The forms that ye create by brightening
thy vision are truly effects that
follow thy cause.
Man is a star bound to a
body, until in the end he is
freed through his strife.
Only struggle and toiling thy utmost
shall the star within thee bloom out
in new life.
He who knows the commencement of all
things, free, is his star from the
realms of night.
Remember, O man, that all which exist
is only another form of that which
exists not.
Everything that has being is passing
into yet other being, and thou thyself
are not an
exception. Consider the law, for all
is law.
Seek not that which is not of
the law, for such exist only in
the illusions of the senses.
Wisdom cometh to all her children,
even as they cometh unto wisdom.
All through the ages the light has
been hidden. Awake, O man, and be wise.
Far neath the earth crust, in the
halls of Amenti, mysteries I saw that
are hidden from men.
Oft have I journeyed the deep hidden
passage, looked on the light that
is life among men.
There, neath the flowers of life ever
living, searched I the hearts and
the secrets of men.
Found I that man is but living
in darkness, light of the great fire
is hidden within.
Before the lords of hidden Amenti,
learned I the wisdom I given to men.
Masters are they of the great secret
wisdom, brought from the future of
infinity's end.
Seven are they, the lords of Amenti,
overlords they of the children of
morning, sons of the
cycles, masters of wisdom. Formed
are not they as the children of men.
Three, four, five, and six, seven,
eight, nine are the titles of the
masters of men.
Far from the future, formless yet
forming, came they as teachers for
the children of men.
Live they forever, yet not of the
living, bound not to life, and yet
free from death.
Rule they forever with infinite wisdom,
bound yet not bound to the dark
halls of death.
Life they have in them, yet life
that is not life, free from all
are the lords of the all.
Fourth from them came forth the logos,
instruments they of the power over all.
Vast is their countenance, yet hidden
in smallness, formed by a forming,
known yet unknown.
Three holds the key of all hidden
magic, creator he of the halls of
the dead.
Sending forth power, shrouding with
darkness, binding the souls of the
children of men.
Sending the darkness, binding the
soul force, director of negative to
the children of men.
Four is he who looses the power,
lord he of life to the children
of men.
Light in his body, flame in his
countenance, freer of souls to the
children of men.
Five is the master, the lord of
all magic, key to the word that
resounds among men.
Six is the lord of light, the
hidden pathway, part of the souls
of the children of men.
Seven is he who is lord of
the vastness, master of space and
the key of the times.
Eight is he who orders the progress,
weighs and balances the journey of men.
Nine is the father, vast he of
countenance, forming and changing
from out of the formless.
Meditate on the symbols I give thee,
keys are they, though hidden from men.
Reach ever upward, O soul of the
morning, turn thy thoughts upward
to light and to life.
Find in the keys of the numbers
I bring thee, light on the pathway
from life until life.
Seek ye with wisdom, turn thy thoughts
inward, close not thy mind to the
flower of light.
Place in thy body a thought-formed
picture, think of the numbers that
lead thee to life.
Clear is the pathway to he who
has wisdom, open the door to the
kingdom of light.
Pour forth thy flame as a sun
of the morning, shut out the darkness
and live in the day.
Take thee, O man, as part of
thy being, the seven who are but
are not as they seem.
Open, O man, have I my wisdom,
follow the path in the way I
have led.
Masters of wisdom, sun of the morning,
light and life to the children of men.
Thoth
List ye, O man, to the voice
of wisdom, list to the voice of
Thoth the Atlantean.
Freely I give to thee of my
wisdom, gathered from the time and
space of this cycle,
master of mysteries, sun of the morning,
living forever, a child of the light,
shining with brightness, star of the
morning, Thoth the teacher of men
is of all.
Long time ago I in my childhood
lay neath the stars on long buried Atlantis,
dreaming of mysteries far above men.
Then in my heart grew there a
great longing to conquer the pathway
that led to the stars.
Year after year I sought after wisdom,
seeking new knowledge, following the way,
until at last my soul, in great
travail, broke from its bondage and
bounded away.
Free was I from the bondage of
earth men, free from the body I
flashed through the night.
Unlocked at last for me was the
star space, free was I from the
bondage of night.
Now to the end of space sought
I wisdom, far beyond knowledge of
finite man.
Far into space my soul travelled freely
into infinity's circle of light.
Strange beyond knowledge were some
of the planets, great and gigantic
beyond dreams of men,
yet found I Law in all of
its beauty, working through and among
them as here among men.
Flashed forth my soul through infinity's
beauty, far through space I flew with
my thoughts.
Rested I there on a planet of
beauty, strains of harmony filled
all the air.
Shapes there were moving, in order
great and majestic as stars in the night,
mounting in harmony, order equilibrium,
symbols of the cosmic, like unto Law.
Many the stars I passed in my
journey, many the races of men on
their worlds,
some reaching high as stars of the
morning, some falling low in the blackness
of night,
each and all of them struggling upward,
gaining the heights and plumbing the depths,
moving at times in realms of brightness,
living through darkness, gaining the light.
Know, O man, that light is thine
heritage, know that darkness is only
a veil,
sealed in thine heart is brightness
eternal, waiting the moment of freedom
to conquer,
waiting to rend the veil of the
night. Some I found who had conquered
the ether,
free of space were they while yet
they were men. Using the force that
is the foundation of all
things, far in space constructed they
a planet, drawn by the force that
flows through the all,
condensing, coalescing the ether into
forms that grew as they willed,
outstripping in science, they, all
of the races, mighty in wisdom, sons
of the stars.
Long time I paused watching their
wisdom, saw them create from out of
the ether cities,
gigantic of rose and gold, formed
forth from the primal element, base
of all matter,
the ether far flung. Far in the
past they had conquered the ether,
freed themselves from the
bondage of toil, formed in their mind
only a picture and swiftly created
it grew.
Forth then my soul sped throughout
the cosmos, seeing ever new things
and old,
learning that man is truly space born,
a son of the sun, a child
of the stars.
Know ye, O man, whatever from ye
inhabit, surely it is one with the stars.
Thy bodies are nothing but planets
revolving around their central suns.
When ye have gained the light of
all wisdom, free shall ye be to
shine in the ether.
One of the suns that light outer
darkness, one of the space born grown
into light.
Just as the stars in time lose
their brilliance, light passing from
them into the great source,
so, O man, the soul passes onward,
leaving behind the darkness of night.
Forth from ye, from the primal ether,
filled with the brilliance that flows
from the source,
bound by the ether, coalesced around,
yet ever it flames until at last
it is free.
Lift up your flame from out of
the darkness, fly from the night,
and ye shall be free.
Travelled I through the space time,
knowing my soul at last was set free,
knowing that now I might pursue wisdom.
Until at last I passed to a
plane hidden from knowledge,
known not to wisdom, extension beyond
all that we know.
Now, O man, when I had this
knowing, happy my soul grew, for now
I was free.
Listen, ye space born, list to my
wisdom, know ye not that ye too
will be free.
List ye again, O man, to my
wisdom, that hearing ye too might
live and be free.
Not of the earth are ye, earthy,
but child of infinite cosmic light.
Know ye not, O man, of your
heritage? Know ye not ye are truly
the light?
Son of the great sun, when ye
gain wisdom, truly aware of your kinship
with light.
Now, to ye I give knowledge, freedom
to walk in the path I have trod,
showing ye truly how by my striving
I trod the path that leads to
the stars.
Hark ye, O man, and know of
thy bondage, know how to free thyself
from the toils.
Out of the darkness shall ye rise
upward, one with the light, and one
with the stars.
Follow ye ever the path of wisdom,
only by this can ye rise from below.
Ever man's destiny leads him onward
into the curves of infinity's all.
Know ye, O man, that all space
is ordered, only by order are ye
one with the all.
Order and balance are the law of
the cosmos, follow and ye shall be
one with the all.
He who would follow the pathway of
wisdom, open must be he to the
flower of life,
extending his consciousness out of
the darkness, flowing through time
and space in the all.
Deep in the silence first ye must
linger until at last ye are free
from desire,
free from the longing to speak in
the silence. Conquer by silence the
bondage of words,
abstaining from eating until we have
conquered desire for food, that is
bondage of soul.
Then lie ye down in the darkness,
close ye your eyes from the rays
of the light.
Center thy soul in the place of
thine consciousness, shaking it free
from the bonds of the night.
Place in thy mind, place the image
thou desired. Picture the place thou
desirest to see.
Vibrate back and forth with thy power.
Loosen the soul from out of its night.
Fiercely must thou shake with all
of thy power, until at last thy
soul shall be free.
Mighty beyond words is the flame of
the cosmic, hanging in planes unknown
to man,
mighty and balanced, moving in order,
music of harmonies, far beyond man.
Speaking with music, singing with
color, flame from the beginning of
eternity's all.
Spark of the flame art thou, O
my children, burning with color and
living with music.
List to the voice, and thou shalt
be free.
Consciousness free is fused with the
cosmic, one with the order and law
of the all.
Knew ye not, man, that out of
darkness light shall flame forth,
a symbol of all?
Pray ye this prayer for attaining
of wisdom. Pray for the coming of
light to the all.
Mighty spirit of light that shines
through the cosmos, draw my flame
closer in harmony to thee.
Lift up my fire from out of
the darkness, magnet of fire that
is one with the all.
Lift up my soul, thou mighty and
potent, child of the light, turn not away.
Draw me in power to melt in
thy furnace, one with all things and
all things in one,
buyer of the life-strain and one
with the brain.
When ye have freed thy soul from
its bondage, know that for ye the
darkness is gone.
Ever through space ye may seek wisdom,
bound not by the fetters forged in
the flesh.
Onward and upward into the morning,
free-flash, O soul, to the realms
of light.
Move thou in order, move thou in
harmony, freely shalt move with the
children of light.
Seek ye and know ye my key
of wisdom, thus, O man, ye shall
surely be free.
Oft dream I of buried Atlantis, lost
in the ages that have passed into night.
Eon on eon thou existed in beauty,
a light shining through the darkness
of night.
Mighty in power, ruling the earth
-born, lord of the earth in Atlantis day,
king of the nations, master of wisdom,
light through sun-tall, keeper of
the way,
dwelt his temple, the master of Unal,
light of the earth in Atlantis day.
Master he from a cycle beyond us,
living in bodies as one among men,
not as the earth-born, he from
beyond us, son of a cycle, advance
beyond men.
Know ye, O man, that Horlick, the
master, was never one with the children
of men.
Far in the past time, when Atlantis
first grew as a power,
appeared there one with the key of
wisdom, showing the way of light to all.
Showed he to all men the path
of attainment, way of the light that
flows among men,
mastering darkness, leading the man
-soul upward to heights that were
one with the light.
Divided the kingdoms he into sections,
ten were they, ruled by children of men.
Upon another built he a temple, built,
but not by the children of men.
Out of the ether called he its
substance, molded and formed by the
power of Tolan
into the forms he built with his
mind. Mile upon mile it covered the island,
space upon space it grew in its
might. Black, yet not black, but dark
like space-time,
deep in its heart the essence of
light. Swiftly the temple grew into being,
molded and shaped by the word of
the dweller, called from the formless
into form.
Builded he then, within it, great
chambers, filled them with forms called
forth from the ether,
filled them with wisdom called forth
by his mind. Formless was he within
the temple,
yet was he formed in the image
of men. Dwelling among them, yet not
of them,
strange and far different was he from
the children of men.
Choose he then from among the people,
three who became his gateway.
Choose he the three from the highest
to become his links with Atlantis,
messengers they who carried his counsel
to the kings of the children of men.
Brought he forth others and taught
them wisdom, teachers they to the
children of men.
Placed he them on the island of
Undal to stand as teachers of light
to men.
Each of those who were thus chosen,
taught must he be for years five
and ten.
Only thus could he have understanding
to bring light to the children of men.
Thus there came into being the temple,
a dwelling-place for the master of men.
I, Thoth, have ever sought wisdom,
searching in darkness and searching
in light.
Long in my youth I travelled the
pathway, seeking ever new knowledge
to gain,
until after much striving one of the
three to me brought the light.
Brought he to me the commands of
the dweller, called me from the darkness
into the light.
Brought he me before the dweller,
deep in the temple before the great fire.
There on the great throne beheld I,
the dweller, clothed with the light
and flashing with fire.
Down I knelt before that great wisdom,
filling the light flowing through
me in waves.
Heard I then the voice of the dweller,
O darkness, come into the light, long
have ye sought the pathway to light.
Each soul on earth that loosens its
fetters shall soon be made free from
the bondage of night.
Forth from the darkness have ye arisen,
closer approach the light of your goal.
Here ye shall dwell as one of
my children, keeper of records gathered
by wisdom,
instrument thou of the light from beyond.
Ready by thou made to do what
is needed, preserver of wisdom through
the ages of darkness.
That shall come fast on the children
of men, live thee here and drink
of all wisdom,
secrets and mysteries unto thee shall unveil.
Then I answered the master of cycles,
saying, O light that descended to men,
give thou to me of thy wisdom
that I might be a teacher of men.
Give thou of thy light that I
may be free.
Spoke then to me again the master,
age after age shall ye live through
your wisdom.
I, when over Atlantis the ocean waves
roll, holding the light, though hidden
in darkness,
ready to come when over thou shalt call.
Go thee now and learn greater wisdom,
grow thou through light to infinities all.
Long then dwelt I in the temple
of the dweller until at last I
was one with the light.
Light there was in ancient Atlantis,
yet darkness too was hidden in all.
Fell from the light into the darkness
some who had risen to heights among men.
Proud they became because of their
knowledge, proud were they of their
place among men.
Deep delved they into the forbidden,
opened the gateway that led to below.
Sought they to gain ever more knowledge,
but seeking to bring it up from below.
He who descends below must have balance,
else he is bound by lack of
our light.
Opened they then by their knowledge
pathways forbidden to man.
But in his temple all seeing the
dweller lay in his iguante,
while through Atlantis his soul roamed free.
Saw he the Atlanteans by their magic
opening the gateway that would bring
to earth a great woe.
Fast fled his soul then back to
his body.
Up he arose from his iguante.
Called he the three mighty messengers.
Gave the commands that shattered the world.
Deep neath earth's crust to the halls
of Amenti swiftly descended the dweller.
Called he then on the powers of
the seven lords wielded.
Changed the earth's balance.
Down sank Atlantis beneath the dark waves.
Shattered the gateway that had been opened.
Shattered the doorway that led down below.
All of the islands were shattered
except Unal.
And part of the island of the
sons of the dweller.
Preserved he them to be the teachers.
Lights on the path for those to
come after.
Lights for the lesser children of men.
Called he then I Thoth before him.
Gave me commands for all I should
do saying.
Take thou O Thoth all of your wisdom.
Take all your records.
Take all your magic.
Go thou forth as a teacher of men.
Go thou forth reserving the records
until in time light grows among men.
Light shall thou be all through the ages.
Hidden yet found by enlightened men.
Over all earth give we ye power.
Free thou to give or take it away.
Gather thou now the sons of Atlantis.
Take them and flee to the people
of the rock caves.
Fly to the land of the children
of Kim.
Then gathered I the sons of Atlantis.
Into the spaceship I brought all my records.
Brought the records of sunken Atlantis.
Gathered I all my powers.
Instruments many of mighty magic.
Up then we rose on the wings
of the morning.
High we arose above the temple.
Leaving behind the three and dweller.
Deep in the halls neath the temple.
Closing the pathway to the lords of
the cycles.
Yet ever to him who has knowing.
Open shall be the path to Amenti.
Fast fled we then on the wings
of the morning.
Fled to the land of the children
of Kim.
There by my power I conquered and
ruled them.
Raised I to light the children of Kim.
Deep neath the rocks I buried my spaceship.
Waiting the time when man might be free.
Over the spaceship erected a marker.
In the form of a lion yet
likened to man.
There neath the image rests yet my spaceship.
Forth to be brought when need shall arise.
Know ye old man that far in
the future.
Invaders shall come from out of the deep.
Then awake ye who have wisdom.
Bring forth my ship and conquer with ease.
Deep neath the image lies my secret.
Search and find in the pyramid I built.
Each to the other is the keystone.
Each the gateway that leads into life.
Follow the key I leave behind me.
Seek and the doorway to life shall
be thine.
Seek thou in my pyramid deep in
the passage that ends in a wall.
Use thou the key of the seven.
And open to thee the pathway will fall.
Now unto thee I have given my wisdom.
Now unto thee I have given my way.
Follow the pathway.
Solve thou my secrets.
Until thee I have shown the way.
Hark ye old man to the wisdom
of magic.
Hark the knowledge of powers forgotten.
Long ago in the days of the
first man.
Warfare began between darkness and light.
Men then as now were filled with
both darkness and light.
And while in some darkness held sway.
In other light filled the soul.
Aye age old in this warfare.
The eternal struggle between darkness
and light.
Fiercely is fault all through the ages.
Using strange powers hidden to man.
The depths has there been filled with
the blackness.
Struggling always against the light.
But others there are who filled with brightness.
Have conquered the darkness of night.
Wherever ye may be in all ages
and plain.
Surely ye shall know of the battle
with night.
Long ages ago the sons of the
morning descending.
Found the world filled with night.
There in that past began the struggle.
The age old battle darkness and light.
Many in time were so filled with darkness.
That only feebly flame the light from
the night.
Some they were masters of darkness.
Who sought to fill all with their darkness.
Sought to draw others into their night.
Fiercely withstood they the masters
of rightness.
Fiercely fought they from the darkness
of night.
Sought ever to tighten the fetters.
The chains that bind men to the
darkness of night.
Used they always the dark magic.
Brought into men by the power of darkness.
Magic that enshrouded man's soul with darkness.
Banded together as in order.
Brothers of darkness they through
the ages.
Antagonist they to the children of men.
Walk they always secret and hidden.
Found yet not found by the children
of men.
Forever they walked and worked in darkness.
Hiding from the light in the darkness
of night.
Silently secretly used they their power.
Enslaving and binding the soul of men.
Unseen they come and unseen they go.
Man in his ignorance calls them from below.
Dark is the way of the dark
brothers travel.
Dark of the darkness not of the night.
Traveling over earth they walk through
man's dreams.
Power they have gained from the darkness
around them.
To call other dwellers from out of
their plane.
In ways that are dark and unseen
by man.
Into man's mind space reached the
dark brothers.
Around it they closed the veil of
their night.
There through its lifetime that soul
dwells in bondage.
Bound by the fetters of the veil
of the night.
Mighty are they in the forbidden knowledge.
Forbidden because it is one with the night.
Hark ye old man and listen to
my warning.
Be ye free from the bondage of night.
Surrender not your soul to the brothers
of darkness.
Keep thy face ever turned towards
the light.
Know ye not old man that your sorrow.
Only has come through the veil of
the night.
Aye man heed ye my warning.
Strive ever upward.
Turn your soul toward the light.
The brothers of darkness seek for
their brothers.
Those who traveled the pathway of light.
For well know they that those who
have traveled.
Far towards the sun in their pathway
of light.
Have great and yet greater power.
To bind with darkness the children
of light.
List ye old man to he who
comes to you.
But weigh in the balance if his
words be of light.
For many there are who walk in
dark brightness.
And yet are not the children of light.
Easy it is to follow their pathway.
Easy to follow the path that they lead.
But yet old man heed ye my warning.
Light comes only to him who strives.
Hard is the pathway that leads to
the wisdom.
the light.
Many shall ye find the stones in
your pathway.
Many the mountains to climb toward
the light.
Yet know ye old man to him
that overcometh.
Free will he be of the pathway
of light.
For ye know old man in the
end light must conquer.
And darkness and night be banished
from light.
Listen old man and heed ye this wisdom.
Even as darkness so is the light.
When darkness is banished and all
veils are rended.
Out there shall flash from the darkness
the light.
Even as exist among men the dark brothers.
So there exist the brothers of light.
Antagonists they of the brothers of darkness.
Seeking to free men from the night.
Powers have they mighty and potent.
Knowing the law the planets obey.
Work they ever in harmony and order.
Freeing the man soul from its bondage
of night.
Secret and hidden walk they also.
Know not are they to the children
of men.
Ever have they fought the dark brothers.
Conquered and conquering time without end.
Yet always light shall in the end
be master.
Driving away the darkness of night.
Aye man know ye this knowing.
Always beside thee walk the children
of light.
Masters they of the sun power.
Ever unseen yet the guardians of men.
Open to all is their pathway.
Open to he who will walk in
the light.
Free are they of dark amenity.
Free of the halls where life reigns supreme.
Sons are they and lords of the morning.
Children of light to shine among men.
Like man they are and yet are unalike.
Never divided were they in the past.
One have they been in oneness eternal.
Throughout all space since the beginning
of time.
Up did they come in oneness with
the all one.
Up from the first space formed and unformed.
Given to man have they secrets that
shall guard and protect him from all harm.
He who would travel the path of
the master.
Free must he be from the bondage
of night.
Conquer must he the formless and shapeless.
Conquer must he the phantom of fear.
Knowing must he gain of all the secrets.
Travel the pathway that leads through
the darkness.
Yet ever before him keep the light
of his goal.
Obstacles great shall he meet in the pathway.
Yet press on to the light of
the sun.
Hear ye old man.
The sun is the symbol of the
light that shines at the end of
thy road.
Now to thee give I the secrets.
Now to meet the dark power.
Meet and conquer the fear from the night.
Only by knowing can ye conquer.
Only by knowing can ye have light.
Now I give unto thee the knowledge
known to the masters.
The knowing that conquers all the
dark fears.
Use this.
The wisdom I give thee.
Master thou shalt be of the brothers
of night.
When unto thee comes a feeling.
Drawing thee nearer to the darker gate.
Examine thine heart and find if the
feeling thou hast have come from within.
If thou shalt find the darkness thine
own words.
Banish them forth from the place in
thy mind.
Send through thy body a wave of vibration.
Irregular first and regular second.
Repeating time after time until free.
Start the wave force in thy brain center.
Directed in waves from thine head
to thy foot.
But if thy findest thine heart is
not darkened.
Be sure that a force is directed
to thee.
Only by knowing can thou overcome it.
Only by wisdom can thou hope to
be free.
Knowledge brings wisdom and wisdom
is power.
Attain and ye shall have power over all.
Seek ye first a place bound by darkness.
Place ye a circle around about thee.
Stand erect in the midst of the circle.
Use thou this formula and you shall
be free.
Raise thou thine hands to the dark
space above thee.
Close thou thine eyes and draw in
the light.
Call to the spirit of the light
through the space time.
Using these words and thou shalt be free.
Fill thy my body O spirit of life.
Fill thy my body with spirit of light.
Come from the flower that shines through
the darkness.
Come from the halls where seven lords rule.
Name them by name I the seven.
Three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine.
By their names I call them to
aid me.
Free me and save me from the
darkness of night.
By their names I implore thee.
Free me from darkness and fill me
with light.
Know ye O man that when ye
have done this.
Ye shall be free from the fetters
that bind ye.
Cast off the bondage of the brothers
of night.
See ye not that the names have
the power to free.
By vibration the fetters that bind.
Use them at night to free thou
thine brother.
So that he too may come forth
from the night.
Thou O man art thy brother's helper.
Let him not lie in the bondage
of night.
Now unto thee give I my magic.
Take it and dwell on the pathway
of light.
Light unto thee, life unto thee.
Sun may thou be on the cycle above.
Hark ye O man and listen to
my voice.
Open thy mind space and drink of
my wisdom.
Dark is the pathway of life that
ye travel.
Many the pitfalls that lie in thy way.
Seek ye ever to gain greater wisdom.
Attain and it shall be on thy way.
Open thy soul O man to the cosmic.
And let it flow in as one
with thy soul.
Light is eternal and darkness is fleeting.
Seek ye ever O man for the light.
Know ye that ever as light fills
thy being.
Darkness for thee shall soon disappear.
Open thy souls to the brothers of brightness.
Let them enter and fill thee with light.
Lift up thine eyes to the light
of the cosmos.
Keep thou ever thy face to the goal.
Only by gaining the light of all
wisdom art thou one with the infinite goal.
Seek ye ever the oneness eternal.
Seek ever the light of the goal.
Light is infinite and light is finite.
Separate only by darkness in man.
Seek ye to rend the veil of
the darkness.
Bring thou together the light into one.
Hear ye O man.
List to my voice singing the song
of light and of life.
Throughout all space light is prevalent.
Encompassing all with its banners
of flames.
Seek ye forever in the veil of
the darkness.
Somewhere ye shall surely find light.
Hidden and buried.
Lost to man's knowledge.
Deep in the finite the infinite exists.
Lost but existing.
Flowing through all things.
Living in all is the infinite brain.
In all space there is only one wisdom.
Though seeming divided.
It is one in the one.
All that exists comes forth from the light.
And the light comes forth from the all.
Everything created is based upon order.
Law rules the space where the infinite dwells.
Forth from equilibrium came the great cycles.
Moving in harmony toward infinity's end.
Know ye O man.
That far in this space time infinity
itself shall pass into change.
Hear ye and list to the voice
of wisdom.
Know that all is of all evermore.
Know that through time thou may pursue
wisdom and find evermore light on
the way.
Ay.
Thou shalt find that ever receding.
Thy goal shall elude thee from day
unto day.
Long time ago in the halls of Amenti.
Ay.
Thoth.
Stood before the lords of the cycles.
Mighty they in their aspects of power.
Mighty they in the wisdom unveiled.
Led by the dweller.
First did I see them.
But afterwards free I was of their presence.
Free to enter their conclave at will.
Oft did I journey down the dark pathway.
Unto the hall where the light ever glows.
Learned I of the masters of cycles.
Wisdom brought from the cycles above us.
Knowledge brought from infinities all.
Many the questions I ask of the
lords of the cycles.
Great was the wisdom they gave unto me.
Now unto thee I give of this wisdom.
Drawn from the flame of infinities fire.
Deep in the dark halls sit the seven.
Units of consciousness from cycles above.
Manifest they in this cycle as guide
of man to the knowledge of all.
Seven are they.
Mighty in power.
Speaking these words through men to men.
Time after time stood I before them.
Listening to words that came not with sound.
Once said they unto me.
O man whatst thou gain wisdom?
Seek for it in the heart of
the flame.
Whatst thou gain knowledge of power?
Seek ye it in the heart of
the flame.
Whatst be one with the heart of
the flame?
Seek then within thine own hidden flame.
Many the times spoke they to me.
Teaching me wisdom not of the world.
Showing me ever new paths to brightness.
Teaching me wisdom brought from above.
Giving knowledge of operation.
Learning of law.
The order of all.
Spoke to me again the seven saying.
From far beyond time are we come
O man.
Travelled we from beyond the space time.
I from the place of infinities end.
When ye and all of thy brethren
were formless.
Formed forth were we from the order
of all.
Not as men are we though once
we too were as men.
Out of the great void were we
formed forth in order and by law.
For know ye that which is formed
truly is formless.
Having form only to thine eyes.
And again unto me spoke the seven saying.
Child of the light O Thoth.
Art thou free to travel the bright
path upward.
Until at the last all ones become one.
Forth were we formed after our order.
Three four five and six seven eight nine.
Know ye that these are the number
of cycles.
That we descend from unto man.
Each having here a duty to fulfill.
Each having here a force to control.
Yet are we one with the soul
of our cycle.
Yet are we too seeking a goal.
Far beyond man's conception.
Infinity extends into a greater than all.
There in a time that is yet
not a time.
We shall all become one with a
greater than all.
Time and space are moving in circles.
Know ye their law and ye too
shall be free.
I free shall ye be to move
through the cycles.
Past the guardians that dwell at the door.
Then to me spoke he of nine saying.
Eons and eons have I existed.
Knowing not life and tasting not death.
For know ye old man that far
in the future.
Life and death shall be one with
the all.
Each so perfected by balancing the other.
That neither exist in the oneness
of all.
In men of this cycle the life
force is rampant.
But life in its growth becomes one
with the all.
Here I manifest in this your cycle.
But yet am I there in your
future of time.
Yet to me time exists not.
For in my world time exists not.
For formless are we.
Life have we not but yet have existence.
Fuller and greater and freer than thee.
Man is a flame bound to a mountain.
But we in our cycle shall ever
be free.
Know ye old man that when ye
have progressed.
Into the cycles that lengthen above.
Life itself will pass to the darkness.
And only the essence of soul shall remain.
Then to me spoke the Lord of
the eight saying.
All that ye know is but part
of little.
Not as yet have ye touched on
the great.
Far out in space where light reigns supreme.
Came I into the light.
Formed was I also but not as
ye are.
Body of light was my formless form formed.
Know I not life and know I
not death.
Yet master am I of all that exist.
Seek ye to find the path through
the barriers.
Travel the road that leads to the light.
Spoke again to me the nine saying.
Seek ye to find the path to beyond.
Not impossible is it to grow to
a consciousness above.
For when two have become one.
And one has become the all.
Know ye the barrier has lifted.
And ye are made free of the road.
Grow thou from form to the formless.
Free may thou be of the road.
Thus through ages I listened.
Learning the way to the all.
Now lift I my thought to the
all thing.
List ye and hear when it calls.
O light all pervading.
One with all and all with one.
Flow thou to me through the channel.
Enter thou so that I may be free.
Make me one with the all soul.
Shining from the blackness of night.
Free let me be of all space time.
Free from the veil of the night.
I a child of the light command.
Free from the darkness to be.
Formless am I to the light soul.
Formless yet shining with light.
Know I the bonds of the darkness.
Must shatter and fall before light.
Now give I this wisdom.
Free may ye be old man.
Living in light and in brightness.
Turn not thy face from the light.
Thy soul dwells in realms of brightness.
Ye are a child of the light.
Turn thy thoughts inward not outward.
Find thou the light soul within.
Know that thou are the master.
All else is brought from within.
Grow thou to the realms of brightness.
Hold thou thy thought on the light.
Know thou are one with the cosmos.
A flame and a child of the light.
Now to thee I give warning.
Let not thy thought turn away.
Know that the brightness flows through
thy body for I.
Turn not to the dark brightness that
comes from the brothers of black.
But keep thine eyes ever lifted.
Thy soul in tune with the light.
Take ye this wisdom and heed it.
List to my voice and obey.
Follow the pathway to brightness.
And thou shalt be one with the way.
Unto thee, O man, have I given
my knowledge.
Unto thee have I given of light.
Hear ye now and receive my wisdom
brought from space planes above and beyond.
Not as man am I.
For free have I become of dimensions
and planes.
In each take I on a new body.
In each I change in my form.
Know I now that the formless is
all there is of form.
Great is the wisdom of the seven.
Mighty are they from beyond.
Manifest they through the power filled
by force from beyond.
Hear ye these words of wisdom.
Hear ye and make them thine own.
Find in them the formless.
Find ye the key to beyond.
Mystery is but hidden knowledge.
Know and ye shall unveil.
Find the deep buried wisdom and be
master of darkness and light.
Deep are the mysteries around thee.
Hidden the secrets of old.
Search through the keys of my wisdom.
Surely shall ye find the way.
The gateway to power is secret.
But he who attains shall receive.
Look to the light, O my brother.
Open and ye shall receive.
Press on through the valley of darkness.
Overcome the dweller of the night.
Keep ever thine eyes to the light plane.
And thou shalt be one with the light.
Man is in the process of changing
to forms that are not of this world.
Grows he in time to the formless.
A plane on the cycle above.
Know ye.
Ye must become formless before ye
are one with the light.
List ye, O man, to my voice.
Telling of the pathways to light.
Showing the way of attainment when
ye shall be one with the light.
Search ye the mysteries of earth's heart.
Learn of the law that exists.
Holding the stars in their balance
by the force of their primordial mist.
Seek ye the flame of the earth's life.
Bathe in the glare of its flame.
Follow the three-cornered pathway
until thou too art a flame.
Speak thou in words without voice
to those who dwell down below.
Enter the blue-liddened temple and
bathe in the fire of all life.
Know, O man, thou art complex.
A being of earth and of fire.
Let thy flame shine out brightly.
Be thou only the fire.
Wisdom is hidden in darkness.
When lit by the flame of the
soul, find thou the wisdom and be
light-born.
A son of the light without form.
Seek thee evermore wisdom.
Find it in the heart of the flame.
Know that only by striving can light
pour into thy brain.
Now have I spoken with wisdom.
List to my voice and obey.
Tear open the veils of the darkness.
Shine a light on the way.
Speak I of ancient Atlantis.
Speak of the days of the kingdom
of shadows.
Speak of the coming of the children
Out of the great deep were they
called by the wisdom of earth-men,
called for the purpose of gaining
great power.
Far in the past before Atlantis existed,
men there were who delved into darkness,
using dark magic, calling up beings
from the great deep below us.
Forth came they into this cycle.
Formless were they of another vibration,
existing unseen by the children of
earth-men.
Only through blood could they have
formed being.
Only through man could they live in
the world.
In ages past were they conquered by
the masters, driven below to the place
whence they came.
But some there were who remained,
hidden in spaces and planes unknown
to man.
Lived they in Atlantis as shadows,
but at times they appeared among men.
Aye, when the blood was offered, forth
came they to dwell among men.
In the form of man moved they
amongst us, but only to sight were
they as our men.
Serpent-headed when the glamour was
lifted, but appearing to man as men
among men.
Crept they into the councils, taking
forms that were likened to men.
Slaying by their arts the chiefs of
the kingdoms, taking their form and
ruling over man.
Only by magic could they be discovered.
Only by sound could their faces be seen.
Sought they from the kingdom of shadows
to destroy man and rule in his place.
But know ye, the masters were mighty
in magic,
able to lift the veil from the
face of the serpent, able to send
him back to his place.
Came they to man and taught him
the secret, the word, that only a
man can pronounce.
Swift then they lifted the veil from
the serpent and cast him forth from
the place among men.
Yet beware, the serpent still liveth
in a place that is open at
times to the world.
Unseen they walk among thee in places
where the rites have been said.
Again, as time passes onward, shall
they take the semblance of men.
Called may they be by the master
who knows the white or the black,
but only the white master may control
and bind them while in the flesh.
Seek not the kingdom of shadows, for
evil will surely appear.
For only the master of brightness
shall conquer the shadow of fear.
Know ye, O my brother, that fear
is an obstacle great.
Be master of all in the brightness.
The shadow will soon disappear.
Hear ye and heed my wisdom.
The voice of light is clear.
Seek not the valley of shadow, and
light will only appear.
List ye, O man, to the depth
of my wisdom.
Speak I of knowledge hidden from man.
Far have I been on my journey
through space-time, even to the end
of space of this cycle.
I glipsed the hounds of the barrier,
lying in wait for he who would
pass them.
In that space where time exists not,
faintly I sensed the guardians of cycles.
Move they only through angles.
Free are they not of the curved dimensions.
Strange and terrible are the hounds
of the barrier.
Follow they consciousness to the limits
of space.
Think not to escape by entering your
body, for follow they fast the soul
through angles.
Only the circle will give ye protection,
save from the claws of the dwellers
in angles.
Once, in a time past, I approached
the great barrier, and saw on the
shores where time
exists not, the formless forms of
the hounds of the barrier.
I, hiding in the midst beyond time,
I found them, and they, senting me
afar off, raised
themselves and gave the great bell
cry that could be heard from cycle
to cycle, and moved
through space toward my soul.
Fled I then fast before them, back
from time's unthinkable end.
But ever after me pursued they, moving
in strange angles not known to man.
I, on the gray shores of time's
space's end, found I the hounds of
the barrier,
ravening for the soul who attempts
thee beyond.
Fled I through circles back to my body.
Fled, and fast after me they followed.
I, after me the devourers followed,
seeking through angles to devour my soul.
I know, ye men, that the soul
who dares the barrier may be held
in bondage by the hounds
from beyond time, held till this cycle
is completed and left behind when
the consciousness
leaves.
Entered I my body, created the circles
that know not angles, created the
form that from
my form was formed, made my body
into a circle and lost the pursuers
in the circles of time.
But even yet, when free from my
body, cautious ever must I be not
to move through angles,
else my soul may never be free.
Know ye the hounds of the barrier
move only through angles and never
through curves of
space.
Only by moving through curves can
ye escape them, for in angles they
will pursue thee.
O man, heed ye my warning.
Seek not the break open the gate
to the beyond.
Few there are who have succeeded in
passing the barrier to the greater
light that shines
beyond.
For know ye, ever the dwellers seek
such souls to hold in their thrall.
Listen, O man, and heed ye my warning.
Seek ye to move not in angles
but curves, and if while free from
thy body thou hearest the
sound like the bay of a hound
ringing clear and bell-like through
thy being, flee back
to thy body through circles.
Penetrate not the mist before.
When thou hath entered the form thou
hast dwelt in, use thou the cross
and the circle
combined.
Open thy mouth, and use thou thy voice.
Utter the word, and thou shalt be free.
Only the one who of light has
the fullest can hope to pass by
the guards of the way.
And then must he move through strange
curves and angles that are formed
in direction not
known to man.
List ye, O man, and heed ye
my warning.
Attempt not to pass the guards on
the way.
Rather should ye seek to gain of
thine own light, and make thyself
ready to pass on the
way.
Light is thine ultimate end, O my brother.
Seek and find ever the light on
the way.
List ye, O man, hear ye my voice.
Teaching of wisdom and light in this cycle.
Teaching ye how to banish the darkness.
Teaching ye how to bring light in
thy life.
Seek ye, O man, to find the
great pathway that leads to eternal
life as a sun.
Draw ye away from the veil of
the darkness.
Seek to become a light in the world.
Make of thyself a vessel for light.
A focus for the sun of this space.
Lift thou thine eyes to the cosmos.
Lift thou thine eyes to the light.
Speak in the words of the dweller,
the chant that calls down the light.
Sing thou the song of freedom.
Sing thou the song of the soul.
Create the high vibration that will
make thee one with the whole.
Blend all thyself with the cosmos.
Grow into one with the light.
Be thou a channel of order, a
pathway of law to the world.
Thy light, O man, is the great light.
Shining through the shadow of flesh.
Free must thou rise from the darkness
before thou art one with the light.
Shadows of darkness surround thee.
Life fills thee with its flow.
But no, O man, thou must arise
and forth thy body go far to
the planes that surround thee
and yet are one with thee too.
Look all around thee, O man.
See thine own light reflected.
Ay, even in the darkness around thee,
thine own light pours forth through
the veil.
Seek thou for wisdom always.
Let not thine body betray.
Keep in the path of the light wave.
Shun thou the darkened way.
Know thee that wisdom is lasting,
existing since the all-soul began,
creating harmony from by the law that
exists in the way.
List ye, O man, to the teachings
of wisdom.
List to the voice that speaks of
the pastime.
Ay, I shall tell thee knowledge forbidden.
Tell ye of wisdom hidden in pastime,
lost in the midst of darkness around me.
Know ye, O man, ye are the
ultimate of all things.
Only the knowledge of this is forgotten.
Lost when man was cast into bondage,
bound and fettered by the chains of
the darkness.
Long, long ago I cast off my body.
Wandered I free through the vastness
of ether, circled the angels that
hold man in bondage.
Know ye, O man, ye are only
a spirit.
The body is nothing.
The soul is all.
Let not your body be a fetter.
Cast off the darkness and travel in light.
Cast off your body, O man, and
be free, truly a light that is
one with the light.
When ye are free from the fetters
of darkness and travel in space as
the sun of the light,
then ye shall know that space is
not boundless, but truly bounded by
angles and curves.
Know ye, O man, that all that
exists is only an aspect of greater
things yet to come.
Matter is fluid and flows like a
stream, constantly changing from one
thing to another.
All through the ages has knowledge
existed, never been changed,
though buried in darkness, never been
lost, though forgotten by man.
Know ye that throughout the space
that ye dwell in are others as
great as your own,
interlaced through the heart of your
matter, yet separate in space of their own.
Once in a time long forgotten, I,
Thoth, opened the doorway, penetrated
into other spaces,
and learned of the secrets concealed.
Deep in the essence of matter are
many mysteries concealed.
Nine are the interlocked dimensions,
and nine are the cycles of space.
Nine are the diffusions of consciousness,
and nine are the worlds within worlds.
I, nine are the lords of the
cycles that come from above and below.
Space is filled with concealed ones,
for space is divided by time.
Seek ye the key to the time
-space, and ye shall unlock the gate.
Know ye that throughout the time-space
consciousness surely exists,
though from our knowledge it is hidden,
yet still forever exists.
The key to worlds within thee are
found only within,
for man is the gateway of mystery,
and the key that is one with
the One.
Seek ye within the circle. Use the
word I shall give.
Open the gateway within thee, and
surely thou too shall live.
Man, ye think that ye liveth, but
know it is life within death.
For as sure as ye are bound
to your body, for you no life exists.
Only the soul is space-free, has
life that is really a life.
All else is only a bondage, a
fetter from which to be free.
Think not that man is earth-born,
though come from the earth he may be.
Man is light-born spirit, but without
knowing he can never be free.
Darkness surrounds the light-born.
Darkness fetters the soul.
Only the one who is seeking may
ever hope to be free.
Shadows around thee are falling. Darkness
fills all the spaces.
Shine forth, O light of the man
-soul. Fill thou the darkness of space.
Ye are a sun of the great
light. Remember, and ye shall be free.
Stay not thou in the shadows. Spring
forth from the darkness of night.
Light, let thy soul be, O sun
-born, filled with glory of light,
freed from the bonds of darkness,
a soul that is one with the light.
Thou art the key to all wisdom.
Within thee is all time and space.
Live not in bondage to darkness. Free
thou thy light-form from night.
Great light that fills all the cosmos,
flow thou fully to man.
Make of his body a light-torch
that shall never be quenched among men.
Long in the past sought I wisdom,
knowledge not known to man.
Far to the past I traveled into
the space where time began.
Sought I ever new knowledge to add
to the wisdom I know.
Yet only I found did the future
hold the key to wisdom I sought.
Down to the halls of Amenti I
journeyed, the greater knowledge to seek.
Ask of the lords of the cycles
the way to wisdom I sought.
Ask the lords this question.
Where is the source of all?
Answered in tones that were mighty
the voice of the lord of the nine.
Free thou thy soul from thy body
and come forth with me to the light.
Forth I came from my body, a
glittering flame in the night.
Stood I before the lords bathed in
the fire of life.
Seized was I then by a force
great beyond knowledge of man.
Cast was I to the abyss through
spaces unknown to man.
Saw I molding of order from the
chaos and angles of night.
Saw I the light spring from order
and heard the voice of the light.
Saw I the flame of the abyss,
casting forth order and light.
Saw order spring out of chaos.
Saw light giving forth life.
Then heard I the voice.
Hear thou and understand, the flame
is the source of all things,
containing all things in potentiality.
The order that set forth light is
the word,
and from the word comes from life
and the existence of all.
And again spoke the voice, saying,
The life in thee is the word.
Find thou the life within thee and
have powers to use of the word.
Long I watched the light flame pouring
forth from the essence of fire,
realizing that life is but order and
that man is one with the fire.
Back I came to my body, stood
again with the nine,
listened to the voice of the cycles,
vibrate with powers they spoke.
Know ye, O Thoth, that life is
but the word of the fire.
The life force ye seek before thee
is but the word in the world
as a fire.
Seek ye the path to the word
and powers shall surely be thine.
Then ask I of the nine, O
Lord, show me the path.
Give me the path to the wisdom.
Show me the way to the word,
answered me then the Lord of the nine.
Through order ye shall find the way.
Saw ye not that the word came
from chaos?
Saw ye not that light came from fire?
Look in thy life for disorder.
Balance and order thy life.
Quill all the chaos of emotions, and
thou shalt have order in life.
Order brought forth from chaos will
bring thee the word of the source.
Give thee the power of cycles, and
make of thy soul a force
that free will extend through the
ages a perfected sun from the source.
Listened I to the voice, and deep
sank the words in my heart.
Forever have I sought for order that
I might draw on the word.
Know ye that he who attains it
must ever in order be.
For use of the word through disorder
has never and can never be.
Take ye these words, O man.
As part of thy life, let them be.
Seek thee to conquer disorder, and
one with the word thou shalt be.
Put forth thy effort in gaining light
on the pathway of life.
Seek to be one with the sun state.
Seek to be solely the light.
Hold thou thy thought on the oneness
of light with the body of man.
Know that all is order from chaos
born into light.
List ye, O man, take of my wisdom.
Learn of the deep hidden mysteries
of space.
Learn of the thought that grew in
the abyss, bringing order and harmony
in space.
Know ye, O man, that all exist
has being only because of the law.
Know ye the law, and ye shall
be free.
Never be bound by the fetters of night.
Far through strange spaces have I
journeyed into the deep of the abyss
of time,
learning strange and yet stranger
mysteries, until in the end all was revealed.
Know ye that mystery is only mystery
when it is knowledge unknown to man.
When ye have plumbed the heart of
all mystery, knowledge and wisdom
will surely be thine.
Seek ye, and learn that time is
the secret whereby ye may be free
of this space.
Long have I, Thoth, sought wisdom.
I, and shall seek of eternities end,
for know that ever before me receding
shall move the goal I seek to attain.
Even the lords of the cycles know
that not yet have they reached the goal,
for with all of their wisdom they
know that truth ever grows.
Once in a pastime I spoke to
the dweller, asked of the mystery
of time and space,
asked him to question the surged in
my being, saying, O master, what is time?
Then to me spoke he, the master,
Know ye, O Thoth, in the beginning
there was void and nothingness,
a timeless, spaceless nothingness.
And into the nothingness came a thought,
purposeful, all-pervading,
and it filled the void.
There existed no matter, only force,
a movement,
a vortex, or vibration of the purposeful
thought that filled the void.
And I questioned the master, saying,
Was this thought eternal?
And answered me the dweller, saying,
In the beginning there was eternal thought,
and for thought to be eternal, time
must exist.
So into the all-pervading thought
grew the law of time.
Ay, time which exists through all
space, floating in a smooth, rhythmic movement,
that is eternally in a state of fixation.
Time changes not, but all things change
in time,
for time is the force that holds
events separate, each in its own proper place.
Time is not in motion, but ye
move through time
as your consciousness moves from one
event to another.
Ay, by time yet exist all in
all, all eternal one existence.
Know ye that even though in the
time ye are separate,
ye still are one, in all times existent.
Ceased then the voice of the dweller,
and departed I to ponder on time,
for knew I that in these words
lay wisdom, and a way to explore
the mysteries of time.
Oft did I ponder the words of
the dweller,
then sought I to solve the mystery
of time, found I that time moves
through strange angles,
yet only by curves could I hope
to attain the key that would give
me access to the time-space.
Found I that only by moving upward,
and yet again by moving to rightward,
could I be free from the time
of the movement.
Forth I came from out of my
body, moved in the movements that
changed me in time.
Strange were the sights I saw in
my journeys,
many the mysteries that opened to view.
Ay, saw I man's beginning, learned
from the past that nothing is new.
Seek ye, O man, to learn the
pathway that leads through the spaces
that are formed forth in time.
Forget not, O man, with all of
thy seeking, that light is the goal
ye shall seek to attain.
Search ye for the light on thy
pathway, and ever for thee the goal
shall endure.
Let not thine heart turn ever to
darkness, light let thine soul be
a sun on the way.
Know ye that eternal brightness, ye
shall ever find thy soul hid in light,
never fettered by bondage or darkness,
ever it shines forth a sun of
the light.
I know though hidden in darkness your
soul a spark of the true flame exists.
Be ye one with the greatest of
all lights, find at the source the
end of thy goal.
Light is life, for without the great
light nothing can ever exist.
Know ye that in all formed matter
the heart of light always exists.
Ay, even though bound in the darkness,
inherit light always exists.
Once I stood in the halls of
Amenti, and heard the voice of the
lords of Amenti,
saying in tones that rang through
the silence words of power, mighty
and potent.
Chanted they the song of the cycles,
the words that open the path to beyond.
Ay, I saw the great path opened,
and looked for the instant into the beyond.
Saw I the movements of the cycles,
vast as the thought of the source
could convey.
Knew I then even infinity is moving
on to some unthinkable end.
Saw I that the cosmos is order
and part of a movement that extends
to all space,
a party of an order of orders,
constantly moving in a harmony of space.
Saw I the willing of cycles like
vast circles across the sky.
Knew I then that all that has
being is growing to meet yet another
being in a far off grouping
of space and of time. Knew I
then that in words are power to
open the planes that are hidden from man.
Ay, that even in words lies hidden
the key that will open above and below.
Hark ye now, man, this word I
leave with thee. Use it, and ye
shall find power in its sound.
Say ye the word, Zenuru, and power
ye shall find.
Yet must ye understand that man is
of light, and light is of man.
List ye, O man, and hear a
mystery stranger than all that lies
neath the sun.
Know ye, O man, that all space
is filled by worlds within worlds.
Ay, one within the other yet separate
by law. Once in my search for
deep buried wisdom I
opened the door that bars them from
man. Called I from the other planes
of being
one who was fairer than the daughters
of men. Ay, I called her from
out of the spaces to shine
as a light in the world of
men. Used I the drum of the serpent.
Wore I the robe of the purple
and gold. Placed on my head I
the crown of silver.
Around me the circle of cinnabar shone.
Raised I my arms and cried the invocation
that opens the path to the planes
beyond. Cried to the lords of the
signs in their houses.
Lords of the two horizons, watchers
of the treble gates, stand ye one
at the right and one at the
left. As the star rises to his
throne and rules over his sign.
Ay, thou dark prince of Arulu, open
the gates of the dim hidden land
and release her whom ye
keep imprisoned. Hear ye, hear ye,
hear ye, dark lords and shining ones,
and by their secret names,
names which I know and can pronounce,
hear ye and obey my will.
Lit I then with flame my circle
and called her in the space planes beyond.
Daughter of light, return from Arulu.
Seven times and seven times have I
passed through the fire.
Food have I not eaten, water I
have not drunk. I call thee from
Arulu, from the realms of
Ekershegul. I summon thee, lady of
light. Then before me rose the dark figures.
Ay, the figures of the lords of
Arulu, parted they before me and forth
came the lady of light.
Free was she now from the lords
of the night, free to live in
the light of the earth sun,
free to live as a child of
the light. Hear ye and listen, O
my children. Magic is knowledgeable
and only is law. Be not afraid
of the power within thee, for it
follows law as the stars in the sky.
Know ye that to be without knowledge,
wisdom is magic and not of the
law. But know ye that
ever ye by your knowledge can approach
closer to a place in the sun.
List ye, my children,
follow my teaching. Be ye ever seeker
of light. Shine in the world of
men all around thee,
a light on the path that shall
shine among men. Follow ye and learn
of my magic. Know that all
force is thine if thou wilt. Fear
not the path that leads thee to
knowledge, but rather shun ye
the dark road. Light is thine, O
man, for the taking. Cast off the
fetters and thou shalt be
free. Know ye that thy soul is
living in bondage feathered by fears
that hold ye in thrall.
Open thy eyes and see the great
sunlight. Be not afraid, for all is
thine own. Fear is the
lord of the dark, a rulu, to
he who never faced the dark fear.
Ay, know that fear has existence
created by those who are bound by
their fears. Shake off thy bondage,
O children, and walk in
the light of the glorious day. Never
turn thy thoughts to the darkness,
and surely ye shall
be one with the light. Man is
only what he believeth, a brother
of darkness or a child of the
light. Come thou into the light, my
children. Walk in the pathway that
leads to the sun.
Hark ye now and list to the
wisdom. Use thou the word I have
given unto thee.
Use it, and surely thou shalt find
power and wisdom and light to walk
in the way.
Seek thee, and find the key I
have given, and ever shalt thou be
a child of the light.
Hear ye, and list ye, O children
of Kim, to the words that I
give that shall bring ye to the
light. Ye know, O men, that I
knew your fathers, ay, your fathers
in a time long ago. Deathless
have I been through all the ages,
living among ye since your knowledge
began. Leading you upward
to the light of the great soul
have I ever striven, drawing ye from
out of the darkness of
night. Know ye, O people, amongst
whom I walk, that I, Thoth, have
all the knowledge and all
of the wisdom known to man since
the ancient days. Keeper have I been
of the secrets of the
great race, holder of the key that
leads into life. Bringer up have I
been to ye, O my children,
even from the darkness of the ancient
of days. List ye now to the
words of my wisdom, list ye
now to the message I bring. Hear
ye now the words I give thee,
and ye shall be raised from the
darkness to light. Far in the past,
when I first came to thee, found
I thee in caves of rocks.
Lifted I thee by my power and
wisdom until thou didst shine as men
among men.
Ay, found I thee without any knowing,
only a little were ye raised beyond beast.
Fanned I ever the spark of thy
consciousness until at last ye flamed
as men. Now shall I
speak to thee knowledge ancient beyond
the thought of thy race. Know ye
that we of the great race
had and have knowledge that is more
than man's. Wisdom we gained from
the star-born races,
wisdom and knowledge far beyond man.
Down to us had descended the masters
of wisdom as far
beyond us as I am from thee.
List ye now while I give ye
wisdom, use it, and free thou shalt be.
Know ye that in the pyramid I
builded are the keys that shall show
ye the way into life.
Ay, draw ye a line from the
great image I builded to the apex
of the pyramid built as a gateway.
Draw ye another opposite in the same
angle and direction. Dig ye and find
that which I have
hidden. There shall ye find the underground
entrance to the secrets hidden before
ye were men.
Tell ye I now of the mystery
of cycles that move in movements that
are strange to the finite,
for infinite are they beyond knowledge
of man. Know ye that there are
nine of the cycles. Ay,
nine above and fourteen below, moving
in harmony to the place of joining,
that shall exist in the future of
time. Know ye that the lords of
the cycles are units of
consciousness sent from the others
to unify this with the all. Highest
are they of the
consciousness of all the cycles, working
in harmony with the law. Know they
that in time
all will be perfected, having none
above and none below, but all one
in a perfected infinity,
a harmony of all in the oneness
of all. Deep neath the earth surface
in the halls
of Amenti sit the seven, the lords
of the cycles. Ay, and another the
lord from below.
Yet know ye that in infinity there
is neither above nor below, but ever
there is and ever shall
be oneness of all when all is
complete. Oft have I stood before
the lords of the all,
oft at the front of their wisdom
have drunken and filled both my body
and soul with their light.
Spake they to me and told me
of cycles and the law that gives
them the means to exist.
Ay, spake to me the lord of
the nine, saying, O Thoth, great are
ye among earth children,
but mysteries exist of which ye know
not. Ye know that ye came from
a space-time below this,
and know ye shall travel to a
space-time beyond. But little ye know
of the mysteries within them,
little ye know of the wisdom beyond.
Know ye that ye, as a whole
in the consciousness,
are only a cell in the process
of growth. The consciousness below
thee is ever expanding
in different ways from those known
to thee. Ay, it, though in space
-time below thee,
is ever growing in ways that are
different from those that were part
of the ways of thine own.
For know that it grows as a
result of thy growth, but not in
the same way that thou didst grow.
The growth that thou had and have
in the present have brought into being
a cause and effect.
No consciousness follows the path
of those before it, else all would
be repetition and vain.
Each consciousness in the cycle it
exists and follows its own path to
the ultimate goal.
Each plays its part in the plan
of the cosmos. Each plays its part
in the ultimate end.
The farther the cycle, the greater
its knowledge and ability to blend
the law of the whole.
Know ye that ye in the cycles
below us are working the minor parts
of the law,
while we of the cycle that extends
to infinity take of the striving and
build greater law.
Each has his own part to play
in the cycles. Each has his work
to complete in his way.
The cycle below thee is yet not
below thee, but only formed for a
need that exists.
For know ye that the fountain of
wisdom that sends forth the cycles
is eternally seeking
new powers to gain. Ye know that
knowledge is gained only by practice,
and wisdom comes forth only from knowledge,
and thus are the cycles created by law.
Means are they for the gaining of
knowledge for the plane of law that
is the source of the all.
The cycle below is not truly below,
but only different in space and in time.
The consciousness there is working
and testing lesser things than those
ye are.
And know, just as ye are working
on greater, so above ye are those
who are also working as
ye are on yet other laws. The
difference that exists between the
cycles is only in ability
to work with the law. We, who
have being in cycles beyond thee,
are those who first came
forth for the source and have in
the passage through time and space
gained ability to use
laws of the greater that are far
beyond the conception of man. Nothing
there is that is
really below thee, but only a different
operation of law. Look thee above,
or look thee below,
the same shall ye find. For all
is but part of the oneness that
is at the source of the law.
The consciousness below thee is part
of thine own, as we are a
part of thine.
Ye, as a child, had not the
knowledge that came to ye when ye
became a man.
Compare ye the cycles to man in
his journey from birth unto death,
and see in the cycle below thee
the child with the knowledge he has.
And see ye yourself as
the child grown older, advancing in
knowledge as time passes on. See ye,
we also, the child
grown to manhood with the knowledge
and wisdom that came with the years.
So also, O Thoth are
the cycles of consciousness, children
in different stages of growth, yet
all from the one source,
the wisdom, and all to the wisdom
returning again. Ceased then he from
speaking, and set in
the silence that comes to the lords.
Then again spake he unto me, saying,
O Thoth, long have we
set in amenti, guarding the flame
of life in the halls. Yet know,
we are still part of our cycles,
with our vision reaching unto them
and beyond. Ay, know we that of
all, nothing else matters
excepting the growth we can gain with
our soul. Know we the flesh is
fleeting, the things men
count great are nothing to us, the
things we seek are not of the
body, but are only the perfected
state of the soul. When ye as
men can learn that nothing but progress
of soul can count in the end,
then truly ye are free from all
bondage, free to work, in a harmony
of law.
Know, old man, ye should aim at
perfection, for only thus can ye attain
to the goal. Though ye
should know that nothing is perfect,
yet it should be thy aim and
thy goal. Ceased again the voice of
the nine, and into my consciousness
the words had sunk. Now seek I
ever more wisdom that I may be
perfect in law with thee all. Soon
go I down to the halls of
amenti to live beneath the cold flower
of life. Ye whom I have taught
shall never more see me, yet live
I forever in the wisdom I taught.
All that man is, is because of
his wisdom. All that he shall be,
is the result of his cause.
List ye now to my voice, and
become greater than common man. Lift
thine eyes upward, let light
fill thy being, be thou ever children
of light. Only by effort shall ye
grow upward to the plane
where light is the all of the
all. Be ye the master of all
that surrounds thee. Never be mastered by
the effects of thy life. Create then
ever more perfect causes, and in time
shalt thou be a son
of the light. Free, let thine soul
soar ever upward, free from the bondage
and fetters of night.
Lift thine eyes to the sun in
the sky-space. For thee, let it
be a symbol of life. Know that thou
art the greater light, perfect in
thine own sphere, when thou art free.
Look not ever into
the blackness. Lift up thine eyes
to the space above. Free, let thine
light flame upward, and
shalt thou be a child of the light.
List ye, O man, to the words
of my wisdom. List to the voice
of Thoth the Atlantean.
Conquered have I the law of time
-space. Knowledge have I gained of
the future of time.
Know I that man, in his movement
through space-time, shall ever be
one with the all.
Know ye, O man, that all of
the future is an open book to
him who can read. All effect shall bring
forth its causes, as all effects grew
from the first cause. Know ye the
future is not fixed or
stable, but varies as cause brings
forth an effect. Look in the cause
thou shalt bring into
being, and surely thou shalt see that
all is effect. So, O man, be
sure the effects that ye
bring forth are ever causes of more
perfect effects. Know ye, the future
is never in fixation
but follows man's free will as it
moves through the movements of time
-space toward the goal where
a new time begins. Man can only
read the future through the causes
that bring the effects.
Seek ye within the causation and surely
ye shall find the effects. List ye,
O man, while I speak
of the future. Speak of the effect
that follows the cause. Know ye that
man in his journey
lightward is ever seeking escape from
the night that surrounds him, like
the shadows that surround
the stars in the sky, like the
stars in the sky-space he too
shall shine from the shadows of
night. Ever his destiny shall lead
him onward until he is one with
the light. Ay, though his way lies
midst the shadows, ever before him
glows the great light. Dark though
the way be, yet shall he
conquer the shadows that flow around
him like night. Far in the future
I see man as light-born,
free from the darkness that fetters
the soul, living in light without
the bounds of the darkness
to cover the light that is light
of their soul. Know ye, O man,
before ye attain this, that many
the dark shadows shall fall on your
light, striving to quench with the
shadows of darkness the light
of the soul that strives to be
free. Great is the struggle between
light and darkness, age-old and
ever new. Yet know in time, far
in the future, light shall be all,
and darkness shall fall.
List ye, O man, to my words
of wisdom. Prepare, and ye shall not
bind your light. Man has risen,
and man has fallen, as ever new
waves of consciousness flow from the
great abyss
below us toward the sun of their
goal. Ye, my children, have risen
from a state that was little
above the beast, until now of all
men ye are greatest. Yet before thee
were others greater
than thee, yet tell I thee as
before thee others have fallen, so
also ye come to an end. And upon
the land where ye dwell now, barbarians
shall dwell, and in turn rise to
light. Forgotten shall
be the ancient wisdom, yet ever shall
live though hidden from men. Ay, in
the land thou callest
Kim, races shall rise and races shall
fall. Forgotten shalt thou be of the
children of men,
yet thou shalt have moved to a
star-space beyond this, leaving behind
this place where thou
hast dwelt. The soul of man moves
ever onward, bound not by any one
star, but ever moving to
the great goal before him where he
is dissolved in the light of the
all. Know ye that ye shall
ever go onward, moved by the law
of cause and effect, until in the
end both become one.
Ay, man, after ye have gone, others
shall move in the places ye lived.
Knowledge and wisdom
shall all be forgotten, and only a
memory of God's shall survive. As
I to thee am a God by
my knowledge, so ye too shall be
gods of the future, because of your
knowledge far above
theirs. Yet know ye that all through
the ages man shall have access to
law when he will. Ages
to come shall see revival of wisdom
to those who shall inherit thy place
on this star. They
shall, in turn, come into wisdom and
learn to banish the darkness by light.
Yet greatly must
they strive through the ages to bring
unto themselves the freedom of light.
Then shall
there come unto man the great warfare
that shall make the earth tremble
and shake in its course.
Ay, then shall the dark brothers open
the warfare between light and the night.
When man again shall conquer the ocean
and fly in the air on wings
like the birds,
when he has learned to harness the
lightning, then shall the time of
warfare begin. Great
shall the battle be, twixt the forces,
great the warfare of darkness and
light. Nation
shall rise against nation, using the
dark forces to shatter the earth.
Weapons of force
shall wipe out the earth man, until
half of the races of men shall
be gone. Then shall
come forth the sons of the morning,
and give their edict to the children
of men, saying,
O men, cease from thy striving against
thy brother, only thus can ye come
to the light.
Cease from thy unbelief, O my brother,
and follow the path, and know ye
are right.
Then shall men cease from their striving,
brother against brother and father
against son.
Then shall the ancient home of my
people rise from its place beneath
the dark ocean waves.
Then shall the age of light be
unfolded with all men seeking the
light of the goal.
Then shall the brothers of light rule
the people. Banished shall be the
darkness of night.
Ay, the children of men shall progress
onward and upward to the great goal.
Children of
light shall they become. Flame of
the flame shall their souls ever be.
Knowledge and wisdom
shall be man's in the great age,
for he shall approach the eternal
flame, the source of all
wisdom, the place of beginning, that
is yet one with the end of
all things. Ay, in a time that
is yet unborn, all shall be one,
and one shall be all. Man, a
perfect flame of this cosmos,
shall move forward to a place in
the stars. Ay, shall move even from
out of the space-time
into another beyond the stars. Long
have ye listened to me, O my children.
Long have ye listened to the wisdom
of Thoth. Now I depart from ye
into darkness. Now go I to the
halls of Amenti, there to dwell in
the future when light shall come again
to man. Yet know ye my
spirit shall ever be with thee, guiding
thy feet in the pathway of light.
Guard ye the secrets I
leave with thee, and surely my spirit
will guard thee through life. Keep
thine eyes ever on the
pathway to wisdom. Keep the light
as thy goal evermore. Fetter not thy
soul in bondage of
darkness. Free let it wing in its
flight to the stars. Now I depart
thee to dwell in Amenti.
Be thou my children in this life
and the next. The time will come
when ye too shall be deathless,
living from age to age a light
among men. Guard ye the entrance to
the halls of Amenti.
Guard ye the secrets I have hidden
among ye. Let not the wisdom be
cast to barbarians.
Secrets shall thou keep it for those
who seek light. Now depart I. Receive
thou my blessing.
Take thou my way and follow the
light. Blend thou thy soul in the
great essence.
One with the great light let thy
consciousness be. Call thou on me
when thou dost need me.
Use my name three times in a row:
Chequetet, Arelich, Volmalites
Mystery, O man, hear ye the wisdom.
Hear ye the word that shall fill
thee with life.
Hear ye the word that shall banish
the darkness. Hear ye the voice that
shall banish the night.
Mystery and wisdom have I brought
to my children. Knowledge and power
descended from old.
Know ye not that all shall be
open when ye shall find the oneness
of all?
One shall ye be with the masters
of mystery, conquerors of death, and
masters of life.
Ay, ye shall learn of the flower
of Amenti, the blossom of life that
shines in the halls.
In spirit shall ye reach the halls
of Amenti, and bring back the wisdom
that liveth in light.
Know ye the gateway to power is
secret. Know ye the gateway to life
is through death.
Ay, through death, but not as ye
know death, but a death that is
life, and is fire, and is light.
Desireth thou to know the deep hidden
secret? Look in thy heart where the
knowledge is bound.
Know that in thee the secret is
hidden, the source of all life, and
the source of all death.
List ye, O man, while I tell
the secret. Reveal unto thee the secret
of old.
Deep in earth's heart lies the flower,
the source of the spirit that binds
all in its form.
For know ye that the earth is
living in body as thou art alive
in thine own form form.
The flower of life is thine own
place of spirit, and streams through
the earth as thine flows
through thy form, giving of life to
the earth and its children, renewing
the spirit from form
into form. This is the spirit that
is form of thy body, shaping and
molding into its form.
Know ye, O man, that thy form
is dual, balanced in polarity while
formed in its form.
Know that when fast on thee death
approaches, it is only because thy
balance is shaken.
It is only because one pole has
been lost. Know that thy body, when
in perfect balance,
may never be touched by the finger
of death. Ay, even accident may only
approach when the
balance is gone. When ye are in
balanced equilibrium, ye shall live
on in time and not
taste of death. Know that thou art
the balance completion existing because
of thy balance of
poles. As in thee one pole is
drawn downward, fast from thee goes
the balance of life.
Then unto thee cold death approaches,
and change must come to thine unbalanced life.
Know that the secret of life in
a minty is the secret of restoring
the balance of poles,
and all that exists has form and
is living because of the spirit of
life in its poles.
See ye not that in earth's heart
is the balance of all things that
exist and have in being on its
face? The source of thy spirits is
drawn from earth's heart, for in thy
form thou are one
with the earth. When thou hast learned
to hold thine own balance, then thou
shalt draw on the
balance of earth. Exist then shalt
thou while earth is existing, changing
in form, only when
earth too shalt change, tasting not
of death, but one with this planet,
holding thy form till all
pass away. List ye, old man, whilst
I give the secret so that ye
too shalt taste not of death.
One hour each day shalt thou lie
with thine head pointed to the place
of the positive pole,
north. One hour each day shalt thy
head be pointed to the place of
the negative pole,
south. Whilst thy head is placed to
the northward, hold thou thy consciousness
from the chest to the
head, and when thy head is placed
southward, hold thou thy thought from
chest to feet. Hold thou in
balance once in each seven, and thy
balance will retain the whole of its
strength. Ay, if thou be
old, thy body will freshen, and thy
strength will become as a youth's.
This is the secret known to
the masters by which they hold off
the fingers of death. Neglect not
to follow the path I have shown,
for when thou hast passed beyond years
to a hundred, to neglect it will
mean the coming of
death. Hear ye my words, and follow
the pathway. Keep thou thy balance,
and live on in life.
Hear ye, old man, and listen to
my voice. Listen to the wisdom that
gives thee of death.
When at the end of thy work
appointed, thou may desire to pass
from this life,
pass to the plain where the suns
of the morning live, and have being
as children of light. Pass
without pain, and pass without sorrow
into the plain where is eternal light.
First, lie at rest with thine head
to the eastward. Fold thou thy hands
at the source of thy life.
Place thou thy consciousness in the
life's seat. Whirl it, and divide
to north and to south.
Send thou the one out toward the
northward. Send thou the other out
to the south. Relax
thou their hold upon thy being. Forth,
from thy form, will thy silver spark fly,
upward and onward to the sun of
the morning, blending with light,
at one with its source.
There it shall flame till desire shall
be created. Then shall return to a
place in a form,
know ye, old man, that thus pass
the great souls, changing at will
from life unto life.
Thus ever passes the avatar, willing
his death as he wills his own life.
List ye, old man, drink of my
wisdom. Learn ye the secret that is
master of time.
Learn ye how those ye call masters
are able to remember the lives of
the past.
Great is the secret yet easy to
master, giving to thee the mastery
of time.
When upon thee death fast approaches,
fear not, but know ye are master
of death.
Relax thy body. Resist not with tension.
Place in thy heart the flame of
thy soul.
Swiftly then sweep it to the seat
of the triangle. Hold for a moment,
then move to the goal.
This, thy goal, is the place between
thine eyebrows, the place where the
memory of life
must hold sway. Hold thou thy flame
here in thy brain-seat until the
fingers of death grasp thy
soul. Then, as thou pass through the
state of transition, surely the memories
of life shall
pass too. Then shall the past be
as one with the present. Then shall
the memory of all be retained.
Free shalt thou be from all retrogression.
The things of the past shall live
in to-day.
Man, ye have heard the voice of
my wisdom. Follow, and ye shall live
through the ages as I.
List ye, O man, to the deep
hidden wisdom lost to the world since
the time of the dwellers,
lost and forgotten by men of this
age. Know ye this earth is but
a portal guarded by powers
unknown to man. Yet, the dark lords
hide the entrance that leads to the
heaven-born land.
Know ye the way to the sphere
of Arulu is guarded by barriers opened
only to light-born man.
Upon earth I am the holder of
the keys to the gates of the
sacred land.
Command I by the powers beyond me
to leave the keys to the world
of man.
Before I depart I give ye the
secrets of how ye may rise from
the bondage of darkness.
Cast off the fetters of flesh that
have bound ye. Rise from the darkness
into the light.
Know ye the soul must be cleansed
of its darkness. Ere ye may enter
the portals of light.
Thus I established among ye the mysteries
so that the secrets may always be found.
Ay, though man may fall into darkness,
always the light will shine as a guide.
Hidden in darkness, veiled in symbols,
always the way to the portal will
be found.
Man in the future will deny the
mysteries, but always the way the
seeker will find.
Now I command ye to maintain my
secrets, giving only to those ye have tested,
so that the pure may not be
corrupted, so that the power of truth
may prevail.
List ye now to the unveiling of
mystery. List to the symbols of mystery
I give.
Make of it a religion, for only
thus will its essence remain.
Regions there are, too, between this
life and the Great One,
travelled by the souls who depart
from this earth.
Do it, the home of the powers
of illusion. Seek Het Hetspet, the
house of the gods.
Osiris, the symbol of the god of
the portal, who turns back the souls
of unworthy men.
Beyond lies the sphere of the heaven
-born powers,
Arulu, the land where the Great Ones
have passed.
There, when my work among men has
finished, I will join the Great Ones
of my ancient home.
Seven are the mansions of the house
of the mighty.
Three guards the portal of each house
from the darkness.
Fifteen the ways that lead to the
do-it. Twelve are the houses of
the lords of illusion,
facing four ways, each of them different.
Forty and two are the great powers
judging the dead,
who seek for the portal. Four are
the sons of Horus.
Two are the guards of the east
and west of Isis,
the mother who pleads for her children,
queen of the moon, reflecting the sun.
Ba is the essence, living forever.
Ka is the shadow that man knows
as life.
Ba cometh not until Ka is incarnate.
These are mysteries to preserve through
the ages.
Keys are they of life and of death.
Hear ye now the mystery of mysteries.
Learn of the circle,
beginningless and endless, the form
of He who is one and in all.
Listen and hear it. Go forth and
apply it.
Thus will ye travel the way that
I go. Mystery and mystery, yet clear
to the light-born,
the secret of all I now will
reveal. I will declare a secret to
the initiated,
but let the door be wholly shut
against the profane.
Three is the mystery come from the
Great One. Here and light on thee
will dawn.
In the primeval dwell three unities.
Other than these, none can exist.
These are the equilibrium, source
of creation. One God, one truth, one
point of freedom.
Three come forth from the three of
the balance, all life, all good, all power.
Three are the qualities of God in
His light home. Infinite power, infinite
wisdom, infinite love.
There are the powers given to the
masters, to transmute evil, assist
good, use discrimination.
Three are the things inevitable for
God to perform, manifest power, wisdom,
and love.
Three are the powers creating all
things. Divine love possessed of perfect knowledge.
Divine wisdom knowing all possible means.
Divine power possessed by the joint
will of divine love and wisdom.
Three are the circles of existence.
The circle of light where dwells nothing
but God,
and only God can transverse it. The
circle of chaos where all things by
nature arise from death.
And the circle of awareness where
all things spring from life.
All things animate are of the three
states of existence.
Chaos or death, liberty in humanity,
and felicity of heaven.
Three necessities control all things,
beginning in the great deep, the circle
of chaos, plentitude in heaven.
Three are the paths of the soul,
man, liberty, light.
Three are the hindrances, lack of
endeavor to obtain knowledge, non
-attachment to God, attachment to evil.
In man, the three are manifest. Three
are the kings of power within.
Three are the chambers of the mysteries,
found yet not found in the body
of man.
In the revolution of the heavens,
they bathe in the fountains of light.
Shattered fourth from the feet of
his throne like the diamond rolled
forth four rivers of flame from
his footstool rolled through the channels
of clouds to the man world filled
was the hall with
spirits of heaven wonder of wonders
was the starry palace above the sky
like a rainbow of fire and
sunlight were formed the spirits saying
they the glories of the holy one
then from the midst of the
fire came a voice behold the glory
of the first calls i beheld that
light high above all darkness
reflected in my own being i attained
as it were to the god of
all gods the spirit sun the sovereign
of the sun's fears again came the
voice there is one even the first
who hath no beginning who hath
no end who hath made all things
who govern all who is good who
is just who illumines who sustains
then from the throne there poured
a great radiance surrounding and lifting
my soul by its power
swiftly i moved through the spaces
of heaven shown was i the mystery
of mysteries shown the secret
heart of the cosmos carried was i
to the land of arulu stood before
the lords in their houses
opened they the doorway so that i
might glimpse the primeval chaos shuddered
my soul to the vision
of horror shrank back my soul from
the ocean of darkness then saw i
the need for the barriers saw
the need for the lords of arulu
only they with their infinite balance
could stand in the way
of the inpouring chaos only they could
guard god's creation then did i pass
around the circle of eight
saw all the souls who had conquered
the darkness saw the splendor of light
where they dwelled
long died to take my place in
their circle but longed i also for
the way i had chosen
when i stood in the halls of
aminti and made my choice to the
work i would do
passed i from the halls of arulu
down to the earth space where my
body lay
arose i from the earth where i
rested stood i before the dweller
gave my pledge to renounce
my great right until my work on
earth was completed until the age
of darkness be passed
list you old man to the words
i shall give you in them shall
ye find the essence of life
before i return to the halls of
aminti taught shall ye be the secrets
of secrets how ye too
may arise to the light preserve them
and guard them hide them in symbols
so the profane will
laugh and renounce in every land form
ye the mysteries make the way hard
for the seeker to
tread thus will the weak and the
wavering be rejected thus will the
secrets be hidden and
guarded held till the time when the
will shall be turned through the dark
ages waiting and watching
my spirit shall remain in the deep
hidden land when one has passed all
the trials of the outer
summing ye me by the key they
ye hold then will i the initiator
answer come from the halls of
gods in aminti then will i receive
the initiate give him the words of
power hark ye remember these
words of warning bring not to me
one lacking in wisdom impure in heart
or weak in his purpose
else i will withdraw from ye your
power to summon me from the place
of my sleeping go forth and
conquer the element of darkness exalt
in thy nature thine essence of light
now go ye forth
and summon thy brothers so that i
may impart the wisdom to light thy
path when my presence is gone
come to the chamber beneath my temple
eat not food until three days are
passed there will i give
thee the essence of wisdom so that
with power ye may shine amongst men
there i will give unto thee
the secrets so that ye too may
rise to the heavens god men in
truth as in essence ye be
depart now and leave me while i
summon those ye know of but as
yet know not
now ye assemble my children waiting
to hear the secret of secrets which
shall give ye power to
unfold the god man give ye the
way to eternal life plainly shall
i speak of the unveiled mysteries
no dark sayings shall i given to
thee open thine ears now my children
hear and obey the words that
i give first i shall speak of
the fetters of darkness which bind
ye in chains to the sphere
of the earth darkness and light are
both of one nature different only
in seeming for each arose
from the source of all darkness is
disorder light is order darkness transmuted
is light of the light
this my children your purpose in being
transmutation of darkness to light
hear ye now of the mystery of
nature the relations of life to the
earth where it dwells
know ye ye are threefold in nature
physical astral and mental in one
three are the qualities of each
of the natures nine in all as
above so below in the physical are
these channels the blood which
moves in vertical motion reacting
on the heart to continue its beating
magnetism which moves
through the nerve paths carrier of
energies to all cells and tissues
akasa which flows through
channels subtle yet physical completing
the channels each of the three attuned
with each other
each affecting the life of the body
form they the skeletal framework through
which the subtle ether
flows in their mastery lies the secret
of life in the body relinquished only
by will of the adept
when his purpose in living is done
three are the natures of the astral
mediator is between above
and below not of the physical not
of the spiritual but able to move
above and below three are the
natures of mind carrier it of the
will of the great one arbiter of
cause and effect in thy life
thus is formed the threefold being
directed from above by the power of
four above and beyond man's
threefold nature lies the realm of
the spiritual self four is it in
qualities shining in each of
the planes of existence but 13 in
one the mystical number based on the
qualities of man are the
brothers each shall direct the unfoldment
of being each shall channel be of
the great one
on earth man is in bondage bound
by space and time to the earth
plane encircling each planet
a wave of vibration binds him to
his plane of enfoldment yet within
man is the key to
releasement within man may freedom
be found when ye have released the
self from the body
rise to the outermost bounds of your
earth plane speak ye the word dory
lilla then for a time your
light will be lifted free may ye
pass the barriers of space for a
time of half the sun free may ye
pass the barriers of earth plane see
and know those who are beyond thee
yea to the highest
worlds may ye pass see your own
possible heights of enfoldment know
all earthly futures of soul
bound are ye in your body but
by the power ye may be free
this is the secret whereby bondage
shall be replaced by freedom for thee
calm let thy mind be at rest
be thy body conscious
only of freedom from flesh center
thy being on thy goal of thy
longing think over and over
that thou wouldst be free think of
this word laum illa gnuver and over
in thy mind let it sound
drift with the sound to the place
of thy longing free from the bondage
of flesh by thy will hear
ye while i give the greatest of
secrets how ye may enter the halls
of aminti enter the place
of the immortals as i did stand
before the lords in their places lie
ye down in rest of thy body
calm thy mind so no thought disturbs
thee pure must ye be in mind
and in purpose else only failure
will come into thee vision aminti
as i have told in my tablets
long with fullness of heart to be
there stand before the lords in thy
mind's eye pronounce the words of
power i give makut el
shab el hel serbin el sabrut zen
ephraim karel relax thy mind in thy
body then be sure your
soul will be called now give i
the key to shamballa the place where
my brothers live in the darkness
darkness but filled with light of
the sun darkness of earth but light
of the spirit
guides for ye when my day is
gone leave thou thy body as i
have taught thee
pass to the barriers of the deep
hidden place stand before the gates
and their guardians
command thy entrance by these words
i am the light in me is
no darkness free am i of the
bondage of night open thou the way
of the twelve and the one so
i may pass to the realm of wisdom
when they refuse thee as surely they
will command them to open by these
words of power i am the
light for me are no barriers open
i command by the secret of secrets
edam el ahim sabur su adam
then if thy words have been truth
of the highest open for thee the
barriers will fall
now i leave thee my children down
yet up to the halls shall i
go when ye the way to me
my children truly my brothers shall
ye become thus finish i my writings
keys let them be to
those who come after but only to
those who seek my wisdom for only
for these am i the key in the
way
you