Happiness is a trap and most people
waste their entire lives chasing it.
As today's guest says, happiness is
a direction, not a destination.
And the real destination you should
be chasing is far more interesting
and potent than mere happiness.
So join me today with Arthur Brooks
as we explore the joys of an
honorable life
lived in pursuit of pleasure, power,
and success instead.
Why is it a trap to think
that you can be happy?
Because happiness is not a destination.
Happiness is a direction.
Happiness is the idea that you can
be blissful and happy all the time.
It's not just unrealistic, it's unhealthy.
It would be terrible if you were
happy all the time.
You'd be eaten by a tiger immediately.
You'd have no negative feelings which
keep you alive.
I mean, the idea of the limbic
system of your brain that's producing
sadness and anger and
disgust and fear, these are the emotions
that have kept you alive.
Mere Pleistocene ancestors would have
been eaten by an animal immediately.
You'd be run over by a car.
You need these things that actually
make you at least temporarily unhappy
or you can't put
one foot in front of the other.
Therefore, happiness is the wrong goal.
The right goal is happier.
So that's really what we're trying
to do.
And to get happier is a process
all throughout your life.
And to be on the path toward
what Oprah Winfrey calls happierness,
you actually need a system that makes
it possible so that you can pursue
it and you need to pursue
it.
The reason people need to watch Impact
Theory, by the way, is because this
is a pursuit of
happiness show.
This is all about pursuit.
This is all about achievement.
It's about trying.
It's about making your life better.
It's about progress.
This is one of the most important
points of human flourishing.
This is about progress.
People often ask, why is it so
relatively easy to lose weight but
impossible to keep it off?
It's because when the scale goes down
each day, it gives you this incredible reward.
But when you hit your goal, the
reward is never eating anything you
like ever again
for the rest of your life.
Everything in life is progress.
And that's why the pursuit matters
so that you can actually be on
the trail toward
happierness.
And that's the right goal for all
of us.
It's really interesting.
I like that a lot.
I think a lot about the traps.
So when I think about what Impact
Theory is and what I'm trying to
make it,
it started out pretty simplistic.
So we're in phase three of Impact
Theory at this point, because it's
really me trying
to figure out, okay, how do you
get out of the spiritual entertainment
and into the real
thing that people need to actually
do and understand in order to make
progress, in order
to be happier, in order to be
more fulfilled is how I think about it.
Um, but the way that people get
trapped is very counterintuitive to me.
And you're the only person that I've
ever heard bring it up.
I don't know if you consider it
the central thesis, but you've talked
about how people
get stuck in their perceptions.
Yeah.
And that to me is very interesting.
And there's really, I think, two ways
that people get stuck by their perceptions.
One is they confuse them with objective reality.
So they just think, oh, the thing
I believe is true.
Right.
And so if you don't believe it,
you just don't see the truth.
And then the other way that people
get trapped by perception is they
identify themselves with
it.
And so they love that they are
on the left or the right.
And so you end up with this
vicious cycle of, I'm proud that I
have recognized the truth.
And I feel good about myself for
noticing how wrong you are.
And so we end up in a
pretty gnarly situation where they're
not actually happy.
That's the freaky thing.
So how do people begin to unwind that?
Well, there's a lot.
There's a lot.
I mean, I agree with everything you
said, but there's so much in what
you said, too, that
helps us understand the bad situation
or the conundrum that our country
is in, the world
is in.
And it has everything to do with
our inability to stop seeing ourselves
in terms of the things
that we think.
This is a classic kind of attachment.
So Buddhists talk about this a lot.
So Thich Nhat Hanh, the great Vietnamese
Buddhist monk who, you know, one of
the most important
Buddhist teachers of the last 50 years
died just a couple of years ago.
And he used to talk about the
worst kind of attachments that we
have in modern life is
the attachment to our views, the attachments
to what we think.
That's just as bad as being attached
to your watch, your car, your television
to say, you
know, I love my, I love my car.
I mean, what's wrong with you?
I love your car.
It's a thing.
You shouldn't, you only use things
and you only love people.
I mean, that's an iron law of happiness.
But the thing is that we do
a version of this ideologically where
we say that we're
so identified with the things that
we think that it becomes an attachment
that it becomes
almost a love attachment in our lives.
Now, that's really alienating.
That's incredibly alienating because
you are not your views and I
am not mine.
And that's incredibly important for
us to be able to learn for
this pursuit of happiness
for progress in and of itself is
to not be the things that we
think and to recognize
that we think many things that are wrong.
We just don't know which they are.
The reason people watch this show
and listen to this show is because
they want to learn
more so they can update their views,
which is an acknowledgement that their
views weren't
perfect to begin with, that their
knowledge wasn't perfect to begin with.
Now, when you're being taught by a
baby boomer culture warriors that
are trying to
conscript child soldiers into their
culture war, they will say, if you
don't think these
things, something is morally defective
about you.
And you will have the perfect truth.
You will have the secret Gnostic truths
if you do believe these things.
And at that point, our beliefs, including
political beliefs, have just become
a religion.
They've just become a cult.
And that's really what we see.
And so people are inducted into these
competing cults all the time.
And I have a traditional religion
and I identify with my religion, but
I don't know if I'm
right.
Even on that, I don't know the
things that are right.
And that's been incredibly freeing
for me.
And that's ultimately what we all
have to acknowledge.
I think these things, but I'm willing
to be corrected if I get better information.
And the only way I'm going to
do that is to go to people
who disagree with me, people
who think differently than me, people
who threaten my preconceived notions
and, and
to take it in and say, you
disagree with me, Tom, come sit next
to me, man.
I got to hear it.
Why is that freeing?
Why is it freeing to acknowledge that
you almost certainly are wrong and
to invite people
to challenge those ideas?
For most people that that's like arresting.
Yeah.
Well, that's a hard thing to do
because that actually goes against
that, that, that,
that contravenes evolution.
Evolution is, tells us that we need
to believe particular things and to
defend them.
And the ego threats are actually dangerous
to us because if, you know, if
we're, if we
show ourselves to be wrong to others,
then that makes us look incompetent.
Then we're less likely to survive.
We're less likely to thrive in a community.
We're less likely to rise in a hierarchy.
We're less likely to find mates.
And so the result is that you
defend, defend, defend, defend, but
we don't have to do that.
That's hugely maladapted in modern
life, particularly with modern technology.
I mean, think of the technology that
we're using right now to record this
show and that
people are using to watch us right now.
That's an updating learning technology.
And if you're stuck in the static,
the stasis of, of here's this body
of information that
I have, and it must all be right.
You've basically said that you can't
grow and learn.
So you have to relax that evolutionary imperative.
You have to fight back against what
mother nature is putting into you.
That's in, you know, this is the
way that philosophers will always
talk about sort of
the animal path and the divine path.
The animal path is going according
to your evolutionary imperatives.
These are the things that I, it's
like, if it feels good, do it.
The best way to ruin your life.
The divine path is to stand up
to the things that feel unnatural.
You know, we do this all the time.
I mean, you and I work out
every day, right?
And, and that's, it's the, the nature's
path is sit on the couch, right?
Nature's path is eat that sweet thing, right?
And, and the divine path is to
do things that are hard, that don't
feel natural because
you know, you're, you're, you've been
given a prefrontal cortex where you
can make conscious
decisions that are better than what,
what your feelings tell you that they
should be.
So mother nature says, defend your
opinions at all costs, because if
you don't, it's
an ego threat and they could have,
you know, could have catastrophic
consequences for your
position in the hierarchy.
But you know, that if you don't
defend your positions, if you admit
to the possibility
that you're not right, that you learn
and you update.
And when people say things that you
think are crazy, you say, tell me
more, that you're
actually going to get better.
And that's a conscious decision.
Yeah.
So one, the fact that it's a
conscious decision, I think is really
important for people.
Something you talk about in the book
that when people have collision of
values, they
can really run into a problem.
One of the things, going back to
the question I was asking, one of
the things that I think
really causes problems for people
is they have a value system.
They've never articulated it to themselves.
They've never documented it, written
it down.
So they know these are my actual values.
And then they don't realize that those
are choices.
Again, they're mistaking them for,
this is how the world ought to be.
And when they collide with other people,
they just assume you don't recognize
the way the
world ought to be.
You are bad.
You're a moron, whatever.
And now you get these conflicts.
And you said in the book that
families break up because, you didn't
say collision of values,
but that's how I read it to mean.
And people expect it to be something else.
I forget what you said, people expect
it to be.
Well, they think it's because of a
behavioral discrepancy.
It's usually a values discrepancy
is the way that it works out.
So the way that families tend to
break apart, and again, no joke, one
in six Americans is
not talking to a family member today
because of politics, which is craziness
for happiness.
It's great.
There's one reason of a schism with
family and that's abuse and political
differences that
there should be.
Yeah, that's the only legitimate reason
to have a schism in your family
is because of
abuse and differences of political
opinion are not abuse.
At least they weren't, they didn't
used to be abused.
But if you're being convinced by leaders
who are trying to bring you into
their culture
war, trying to make you a soldier
in their culture war, they'll say
if somebody disagrees
with your view on Supreme Court decisions
or something that they're somehow
erasing your
value as a human being.
I mean, that's this wild leaps of logic.
And we hear about this on college
campuses where I spend a lot of
my time, obviously,
that we're telling people that if
people disagree with you, that they're
erasing you,
that they disagree with your existence
or something.
It's just this crazy existential language
that we're using that's way out of proportion
to everything.
So the only reason to have these
schisms is actual abuse.
And again, people disagree what abuse
is, but it's not that.
Okay.
Now, what do we find with when
people tend to really have a bad
problem in their family?
People think that, for example, I
deal with a lot of students and
they're building their
and figuring out how they're going
to live their own lives.
And it turns out that they disagree
with their parents on a lot.
They come home from college saying
different things.
For example, they're living in a particular
different way, things that their parents might
really disagree with.
It turns out that how you live
your life doesn't matter.
It almost never matters and almost
never leads to schism.
What you say about somebody else's
values is what really matters.
So if you want to have a
really big...
So to all the people in college
who are watching us, I know you
have a huge audience in their
late teens and 20s who are Impact
Theory fans, which is great.
If you want to live your life,
but have a relationship with your
parents, live your
life, but don't tell your parents
that their values are stupid.
That turns out to be a direct
-on attack.
And that leads to bigger problems.
One thing that's become really popular,
though, is tell your dad or your
uncle who says the
racist thing at Thanksgiving, what
you think.
Should they not do that?
No, it's perfectly fine to do that.
But don't freak out.
Don't freak out.
You say, I see it different.
Hey, Uncle Mark, I see it differently.
And as you do, say to yourself
before you begin, I love Uncle Mark,
and I'm going to
use my values right now as a
gift and not as a weapon.
Anytime you use your values as a
weapon, you've denigrated their moral content.
You've eviscerated the effectiveness
of your approach.
But if you use your values as
a gift, it might not always be
taken in a charitable way.
But you're using them for the right reason.
And you've got the odds-on chance
of actually having a good impact.
Okay, this is really interesting.
I had Sam Harris on the show,
who I have a great deal of
respect for.
He has become very unpopular in certain
circles for the way that he is
approaching the problem
of free speech.
I want to be abundantly clear that
my value system tells me that free
speech is worth
dying for.
And so it isn't the thing that
I would expect anybody to reach for
and say, okay, we're
going to clamp down on that.
Now, Sam sees it differently.
And as I try to tease out,
when a smart person, when I learned
one immutable truth, when two
smart people who are sincere think
each other are stupid, then odds are
that they have different
base assumptions.
And when I look at Sam and
I say, okay, Sam's base assumption
is that if something is an
existential threat, then it's worth
stripping away any right to make sure
that we don't
succumb to said existential threat.
And then I was like, okay, because
I don't know that I would disagree
with that.
If I knew there was an asteroid
hurtling towards Earth and it was
life or death and
we were all going to have to
get on the same page and do
XYZ thing, if I really knew that
it was do X survive, do Y,
everyone dies, then I would for sure
say do X.
It makes sense.
But I don't think people know how
to agree on what is the right
course of action.
On when-
Nor do you have perfect knowledge.
Right.
So no perfect knowledge.
You don't know if it's actually an
existential threat.
And so I'll take it out of
that realm for a second.
That's the problem, right?
People don't have perfect knowledge.
They don't know, but, and now I'll
take it in the realm that I
do understand very well.
When you're building a business, you
must give your team certainty.
Right.
It's what I call intoxicating them
with certainty.
It's the only way to get them
to follow you.
Right.
Now the catch is as a leader,
you have to balance.
You know that your team has a
need for certainty.
It's the only way to get them
moving in the same direction.
Right.
But you have to balance that with
what we were talking about before,
what I call the
physics of progress.
That the only way to make progress
is to constantly hunger for how am
I wrong?
So you have to, okay, I was
wrong here.
I need to update my thinking.
I need to update my approach.
If you don't do that, you're screwed.
But now there's tension between, I
need to present to my team, hey,
this is the way,
but I also need to beg my
team to tell me at all times
how I'm wrong.
Right.
Because they're the ones that are
going to recognize the flaw in your
thinking that are
going to show you a better way.
Right.
So it's this absolutely fascinating tension.
Now, when this plays out in the
bigger world with the speed of information
that we have
today, thanks to the internet and
social media, you get this, which
I would say has a level
of pathology in it that scares the
life out of me.
So how do we manage that tension
of it's imperfect knowledge, but I
must give certainty
in order to get a country or
a globe moving in the right direction
and an easy way to
give people certainty is to say, we're
all going to die.
Right, right.
Which is the thing that people reach for.
Right.
But if you don't give people certainty,
everybody runs in weird directions.
Well, the Buddhist would say the answer
to that question is intention without attachment.
Okay.
So certainty is this is the direction
that we're going.
This is the goal.
This is the target as far as
I can see it.
But I'm not attached to that because
this is subject to updating.
So you'll find, for example, you look
at the ancient navigational course
of Columbus
or, you know, the explorers, you know,
that had very imperfect tools.
They had a concept of the direction
that they were going and they had
a particular goal
and they were going toward that goal
with complete certainty.
It was, you know, Columbus was an
entrepreneur and he was taking his
team, the Nina Pinton
Santa Maria toward this particular goal.
And it turned out to be completely wrong.
But the point is that the certainty
was the intention.
The fact that they got something else
that was arguably better was the lack
of attachment
to the object of the intention.
And this is what we're trying to
do in our companies, in our families,
and indeed in
the enterprise, the ultimate enterprise
that we need to impact, which is
our lives.
I mean, it's like you're Tom Inc.
That's the real enterprise of you.
I mean, it just manifested itself
and all these other cool businesses
and the things
are really successful.
But all those were just expressions
of the real enterprise.
And each of us is an entrepreneur
in the startup of our lives.
That's what really matters.
And what we need is to always
have a clear intention, but not attachment
to the object
of that intention, because that makes
you dogmatic.
And the problem that we have right
now is we have fuzzy intention and
strong attachment.
We have exactly the opposite of what
we need in our politics today and
the way that people
talk to each other, the way that
people debate.
And so if I have a strong
intention and the things that I believe,
even politically, but
a lack of strong attachment, I can
have a conversation.
And Sam Harris and I had a
similar conversation, except it was
about religion.
And I'm a traditionally religious
person and he's an atheist.
And the way that we went at
it before we hit record on a
show, we said, we're going
to talk about this to learn.
We're not going to talk about this
to argue.
We're going to talk about this to learn.
Right.
And so when he would say something
I thought was like, whoa, I'd be
like, dude, tell me
more.
And he would say, explain this to
me because this sounds crazy to me.
So truly explain this to me.
So what is that?
That was, we both had this intention,
but we didn't have the attachment.
And so we're willing to update.
And so doing, we got better.
Now, when you're running a team, if
you've got a company, and I've been
a CEO, so I've
made all these mistakes over the years.
If they see that you have this
very clear intention, we're running
this direction.
This is what we think.
This is my best judgment.
But my attachment to these things
is not absolute.
You can throw me off this if
you actually bring the best possible
information to me.
And you can tell me that the
way I'm thinking about it is not
quite right, then I'm going
to change the intention.
But in the meantime, this is the
direction that we're all going.
That turns out to be the way
to square the circle.
This turns out to be the way
to solve this problem personally,
in families, in communities,
and in companies, is intention without attachment.
All right.
That's amazing.
But how do you do that?
How do you, I have a feeling
that a big part of the problem
is people have accidentally
constructed their identity around
that which they think they are.
So I am, in fact, oh God,
if I can remember, this is maybe
a paraphrase, but it's really
damn close to something you said.
We need less activists and more volunteers.
And when somebody-
You read my column.
I have tried to immerse myself in
your world.
One, for this, and two, you are
incredibly helpful for navigating
people trying to do
extraordinary things in their life
in a way that makes their life
better and not worse.
So the striver's curse, I forget the
exact words you used.
The striver's curse.
But perfect.
Yeah, you're good.
So if people identify as an activist
or a volunteer, that simple, like
even you just
giving me the language, I was like,
oh, whoa, I get what you're trying
to say.
Helping others versus like my identity
is this thing and I'm going to
fight to the death
for this.
But how do you begin to extricate
your identity from the things that
you believe so that you
can have non-attachment?
To begin with, we have to ask,
who am I?
And you're going to define that or
you're going to discover that?
Well, you ultimately discover that,
but you have to have an understanding
of that that's
not brittle and that's not based on
the outside world.
There's a philosophical concept that
William James talked about, but the
Eastern philosophers
talk about this a lot too, which
is what William James called the I
-Self versus the Me-Self.
The I-Self is, say you're looking
in a mirror and when you look
in the mirror, there's actually,
there's two of you.
There's the one who's looking and
the one who's being looked at.
The one who's looking is the I
-Self, the observer of the world.
The one who's being looked at is
the Me-Self, which is the observed.
You're going through life as I-Self
and Me-Self.
You need Me-Self to know who
you are and where you stand in
society and where you are
on the team and where you are
in the hierarchy and where you are
in traffic for that matter.
But you need the I-Self so
that you can learn and you can exist.
We are all too heavy on the
Me-Self, on the observed, and none
of us, almost none of us
is heavy enough on the observer part.
So one of the exercises I'll give
my students at Harvard Business School,
they take this
happiness class, which is about the,
it's called leadership and happiness,
the serious science
of the business of you.
And I'll say, we're going to go
through an hour.
You're going to take an hour where
you're not going to be observed.
You're simply going to observe.
And now this means a lot.
This means, for example, you say like,
you don't say, yeah, this coffee is bitter.
You say, hmm, this coffee has a
bitter flavor.
Nothing more than observation.
There's no mirrors.
There's no notifications on social media.
There's no judgments.
There's just observation of the world
to get better at that.
And this is incredibly important if
we want to learn and we want
to update.
This also gets us away from this
whole concept of my identity in my ideology.
Because what that fundamentally is,
is just me, me, me, me, me,
me, me, me, me.
It's like, who am I?
I am the things that I think.
If somebody disagrees with me, then
they're attacking me.
That's insanity.
That's pure vanity.
That is just looking in a mirror
all day long saying, mirror, mirror
on the wall, who's
the most beautiful of them all?
It's me and my political beliefs.
That's craziness.
There's no way to live.
And by the way, that's the fastest
way to become a truly unhappy person.
The reason is because you need the
grandeur of the world to actually
give you what you
need, the experience of day-to-day life.
And living in the image of yourself
is just boring.
It's just tedious.
Thinking about me and what they think
of me and whether or not they
agree with me and
whether or not these things are going
to satisfy me, me, me, me, me.
It's like watching the same episode
of the same season of Better Call
Saul every single
day for the rest of your life.
It was okay the first time.
It was not that great the second time.
And it's awful every time after that.
And being forced to do that, that's
identity politics.
That's the world of identity.
That's the world of mirrors.
That's the world of social media notifications.
That's the world of the me-self
is what it comes down to.
So, if we really want to be
happy, get into the I-self, the
learning space, the observation,
the awe of the outside world and
your life will change.
It'll just change.
And it's fast.
You can reboot your life, your health,
even your career, anything you want.
All you need is discipline.
I can teach you the tactics that
I learned while growing a billion
-dollar business that
will allow you to see your goals through.
Whether you want better health, stronger
relationships, a more successful career,
any of that is possible with the
mindset and business programs in Impact
Theory University.
Join the thousands of students who
have already accomplished amazing things.
Tap now for a free trial and
get started today.
So, in the book, you say that
basically exactly what you just said,
that happiness isn't the
feeling, but the feeling is evidence
of the happiness.
Right.
So then what is the happiness?
What is the meat and potatoes?
Yeah, that's a good analogy because
it's either the courses or really
the macronutrients
and the thing that is happiness has
three parts to it.
And we know this from measuring people
who have high levels of well-being
versus those
who don't.
High well-being is associated with
high levels of enjoyment, satisfaction
and meaning in
life.
Those are the three things that we
need to actually pursue.
The pursuit of happiness is the pursuit
of enjoyment, the pursuit of satisfaction and
the pursuit of meaning.
And there are three different goals
with three different sciences and
three different strategies
to it.
When somebody only pursues one, they're
not going to be happy.
You need a balance and abundance across
this macronutrient profile for happiness
if you're
going to get it.
I meet people all the time who
have great enjoyment in life, but
very little meaning
and they're not happy.
I know people, hardworking entrepreneurs
who have tremendous meaning and no
quality of
life, no enjoyment.
They're not happy.
And so I have to coach people
in different ways about this.
Satisfaction is the hardest of them.
I was going to ask.
Because you can't keep it, you know?
And so they each have a science.
Why can't you keep satisfaction?
Because the brain is something has
a tendency to be homeostatic.
Homeostasis is the tendency of the
brain to always take you emotionally
back to equilibrium.
So you'll be ready for the next
set of circumstances.
Interesting.
Can I push back on that?
Yeah.
So one, obviously I agree with homeostasis,
but the way that I've always thought about
how transient satisfaction is going
back to understanding the science
is from an evolutionary
standpoint.
If you ate a meal and it
was satisfying forever, you would
starve to death.
Right.
Because you would only eat once.
And so knowing that evolution will
conserve, conserve, conserve.
If I have this mechanism that makes
sure that I go do the thing
again, that is basically
this rise and fall of satisfaction
that happens with everything that
I would be in trouble
if I only did once.
Right.
So thirst, satisfaction going to rise
and fall.
Hunger, rise and fall.
Sex, rise and fall.
Right.
Consumption.
Consumption, pursuit, hierarchy, prestige,
the watch, the car, the house, all
of it.
Well, now it's interesting.
Now I wonder if that is homeostasis.
That is homeostasis.
Because the watch losing its thing,
although it's probably the same mechanism,
because it's trying to get me to
go do more, go do more.
Right.
And here's the thing about it.
The reason that we don't ever realize
that when you think, when people say,
I move to California because then
I'll be permanently happy because
of the sunshine.
No, the big benefit that you get
from, mood benefit from sunshine is
six months,
but the taxes are forever.
Yeah.
So I have to tell you.
Tell me about it.
So I'm not trying to hurt you, man.
So the key thing to understand about
homeostasis is that Mother Nature
doesn't want you to know
it exists.
Mother Nature has homeostasis so that
you'd be ready for the next set
of circumstances,
but fools you again and again and
again into thinking that this time
the satisfaction
will be permanent.
And it never is.
By the way, this is physical too.
So you step off the treadmill and
your heart is going 135 beats per minute,
which you're doing for good cardiovascular health.
Within 15 minutes, your heart rate
has gone back to its base rate.
So you don't die.
Well, the same thing is true with
your emotions.
Homeostasis has to reset you.
But when it comes to the satisfactions
that we seek, you know, caloric or,
you know,
propagation of the genes through mating
and all the stuff that we want
to do.
We always think that that relationship
will give me permanent satisfaction.
Because if you knew, if you knew,
then you'd be like,
that's going to give me 10 minutes
of happiness.
I'm not even going to do it.
And you'd stop being, you wouldn't
be in the hustle.
You wouldn't be in the fight anymore.
You wouldn't go get the banana off
the top of the tree and risk
your life.
You wouldn't trudge across the savannah
to get that meal.
You would lose your motivation.
And Mother Nature wants you to be motivated.
And she does that by fooling you.
So that you think that this time
I'm really going to love that car forever.
And it's like a month, it turns out.
So that's, so satisfaction is a real conundrum.
Only when you understand the science,
can you short circuit the science.
Only when you, when you understand
the matrix, can you find a glitch?
Can you find the glitch in the matrix?
That's why it's so incredibly empowering.
Because there is a way around that
for satisfaction.
The same thing is true for enjoyment,
by the way.
Everybody thinks they enjoy it.
It's just, you know, pleasure.
Wrong.
Pleasure is not the secret of happiness.
Pleasure is the short way to get addiction.
And nobody ever says, man, you know
the secret to my happiness?
Methamphetamine.
Never.
Nobody ever says, oh yeah, it's like
partying away my entire paycheck in Vegas.
And then my wife leaving me.
That's, that's not the secret of happiness.
That's the secret to pleasure.
And pleasure is not connected to happiness
unless you take pleasure and you add
two things.
People and memory.
If you add pleasure plus people plus
memory, you get enjoyment.
Those must be stand-ins for something.
What are the people and the memory
stand-ins for?
Communion and consciousness.
So just, I'm a social species and
I'm going to get tremendously rewarded.
This is a good time to bring up.
So I'm really obsessed with this idea
that running in the back of your mind
are evolutionary algorithms and there's
no escaping them.
And so there are just certain things
you are going to have to do
if you want to,
I don't know if you're going to
agree with this framing,
but if you, if you're going to
feel the way you want to feel,
you must be aware of these algorithms.
You must acknowledge them.
Right.
So I've always tried to migrate people
away from happiness.
Not as you define it, as the
smell of the turkey.
Right.
Stop worrying about the emotion.
Stop worrying about happy feelings.
Right, exactly.
Because they're so transient.
Correct.
And get to fulfillment.
And fulfillment for me has a formula.
I'll be interested to see if you
agree with this.
These are based on what I consider
the evolutionary algorithms running
in your mind
that there is no escape from.
So you are going to have to
work hard.
Anything that comes easily will just
not, it won't resonate.
That's the satisfaction issue, by
the way.
Satisfaction is the joy that comes
after struggle.
That's what satisfaction is.
So you get satisfaction.
Does it always have to come from struggle?
You have to do something and it's
the sense of earning something.
So for example, if you cheat on
the exam and you get an A,
there's no satisfaction.
True.
But I feel deeply satisfied after
good sex.
Do I feel like I earned it?
I don't know.
I have not investigated this feeling.
Yeah, but that's actually, that's
not satisfaction.
That's enjoyment.
Is it?
That's what you, and satisfaction.
You don't feel sexually satisfied?
Well, that's a word that we use,
but it's different than what we're
talking about here.
So again, we're defining the terms
of the problem.
Which I think is important.
Super important.
Because you may be about to have
me separate two ideas that,
because I don't have words for, I
don't see the difference.
Sexual satisfaction, where they're
talking about a sexual enjoyment.
So an enjoyment is a better word
for it.
So when I am overcome with desire,
the right way to think of it
for me is hunger.
It feels the same.
I've got to have this thing.
I really want it.
Anticipatory chemicals.
Oh my God.
And then I get it.
And so like, I'll differentiate between
masturbation and sex.
When I masturbate, I don't necessarily
feel satisfied.
That's one of the things that makes
that such a whatever pursuit.
Whereas when I have sex, I feel satisfied.
Like there's some deeper thing in
me and it is an extinguishing of
the hunger.
But because I have oxytocin and vasopressin,
it's like, oh man, I feel so good.
So it's this combination of the calming
of that like seeking behavior with like,
and I feel so bonded and connected
to this person.
Yeah.
This is just terms.
So the way to think about it
in this particular framework is pleasure
versus enjoyment.
Got it.
Okay.
So pleasure is something that pornography
is associated with pleasure.
Sexual activity in a pair bonded relationship
is associated with enjoyment because
it has
people in memory.
And so one of the things to
keep in mind, a strategy, especially
for a lot of young people,
a lot of young men, is if
you like something, it's best if you're
not doing it alone.
Because then you're probably-
Full stop?
Not necessarily.
This is just kind of a rule
of thumb.
This is not an iron law, but
it's a rule of thumb.
Doing it alone is associated with pleasure.
So Anheuser-Busch doesn't do ads about
beer where they show a dude pounding
a 12-pack
alone in his apartment.
Why not?
Because that would be-
Accurate ad.
That would be, yeah, because a lot
of people use alcohol for pleasure.
Right.
Which leads to addiction and misery.
They see you and me cracking open
a Bud Light and clink and talking
about how great it is
and because we're friends and we're
making a memory.
And that's enjoyment, which is associated
with happiness.
So we have a basic idea of that.
The same thing is true with the
example of sex that you talked about
a minute ago.
It can be pleasure or it can
be enjoyment.
And everybody knows the difference
between sexual experiences that are
pleasurable or
enjoyable.
Enjoyment is the goal because that's
one of the macronutrients of happiness.
We talk about in terms, in the
terms that you defined about satisfaction,
but it's
really in this terminology.
And again, you know, you have to
just defining terms.
These are just words, but the concepts
underlying them are critical.
In the book, you give a really
good example of pleasure without enjoyment.
Yeah.
Which you mentioned obliquely a minute ago.
But when you think of a drug
addict, they're doing the drug.
Right.
They're theoretically getting the
pleasure, but they're not getting
any of the enjoyment.
Right.
They're getting tons of pleasure.
It's because they're loading only
on pleasure, but no enjoyment because
it's not social and
it actually is not engaging the prefrontal
cortex and the hippocampus to create memory.
And so you will, you simply will
have a transient experience and the
transient experience will
be unsatisfying.
And so you'll hit the lever again
and again and again and again, and
it will lower your
quality of life.
So that's the key thing.
If there's something you really, really love.
So for example, I'll ask people will
talk about, because I've done a lot
of work on the
science of addiction.
And it's a very interesting subject.
People say, how do you know if
you're addicted?
Because these are behavioral constructs.
You know, you can't take a blood
test to know if you're, if you're
an alcoholic, if you're,
you know, so it's, these are behavioral.
And the big behavioral thing is, do
you prefer to drink alone?
Do you prefer to actually become inebriated alone?
That means you're looking for pleasure
versus enjoyment.
And that is a, that has a
lot that will lead you more to
addiction, more toward addiction
and away from happiness is the way
that that works.
That's the reason that people say,
never drink alone, but they don't
know what they're
saying is they're saying, enjoy it.
Don't have it be a source of
pleasure because that's dangerous.
So that gives you an idea.
So we've talked a little bit about
satisfaction, like a little bit of enjoyment.
These are heavy, heavy topics in terms
of the social science and neuroscience
for sure.
And we haven't even touched on meaning,
which is the heaviest of them all,
which is the
hardest of them all.
So you can become an, what I
really want is I want people to
be, to be obsessed with,
to have their hobby be the science
of happiness and how they can get
it and spread it.
Because that would be a really meritorious movement.
If people were like, yeah, more of
the science, more understanding it.
I want to be excellent at this.
I want to be most excellent.
My hobby is getting better at happiness
and it's changed my life.
It's a good hobby.
It's really been a good hobby for me.
I made it into a career.
That you most certainly did.
So I want to close the loop
on the fulfillment recipe and get
your take on that.
So you have to work really hard
because that's just nature ensures
that you're going to do
that so that you're out doing the
hard things like getting a meal, protecting
your family,
et cetera, to acquire a set of skills.
That's a big lean on progress because
I agree progress, I think is a
foundational pillar
of human happiness.
So you're going to work really hard
to gain a set of skills that
allow you to serve yourself
and others.
And it needs to be in a
way that you find exciting.
So that to me is, those are
the things that nature is going to
ensure that you do.
And if you're doing it for not
only yourself, but others is the meaning
portion of this.
Why do, is it that people never
stop to identify what gives them meaning?
Is it that they confuse meaning?
Is that they're stuck in the me self?
Why do so few people end up
cracking that code?
Part of the reason is because they're
not specifically trying to find meaning.
They don't make it a goal.
They just, a lot of people believe
that if I do what I'm really,
really good at,
and I can be successful at, that
it's going to give me a ton
of meaning automatically.
And that's not right.
Like anything else, you have to do
things on purpose.
Did you get meaning when you were
a classical musician?
No, that was the reason.
That's the reason I'm not a classical musician.
Could you have gotten meaning out
of it?
Many people do, but here's the thing.
My favorite composer is Johann Sebastian Bach.
Maybe the greatest composer who ever lived.
That's a great story.
Yeah.
I mean, 1685 to 1750, 20 kids.
He had 20 kids?
Yeah, he was productive as a composer
and as a father.
I would say, was he Catholic?
He wasn't, he was Lutheran, but he was...
I say that because I know you're Catholic.
For those listening who wonder why
I made a joke about Catholicism.
He was just a sexy Lutheran.
But, and Bach was asked near the
end of his life why he wrote music.
The why question.
Our friend Simon Sinek always talks
about start with why.
And it's fantastic.
I mean, it's been, cause it really is.
People are going around asking what
and hoping to get the why for free.
And Simon's entrepreneurial twist
is start with why,
and then the what will come automatically.
And you'll be a lot more satisfied
because you'll find the source of meaning.
So Bach's why, when he was asked,
why do you write music?
Was the aim and final end of
all music is the refreshment of the soul
and the glorification of God.
Okay, not bad.
Not bad at all.
But I read that in my late
20s when I was still,
I was in the Barcelona Symphony in
those days.
And it was a good job.
And it was, you know, I love
the music.
I was really into it.
It's kind of a high prestige job,
you know, playing the greatest...
It sounds cool.
Yeah.
But I couldn't, I couldn't answer
like that.
I couldn't answer like that.
I didn't feel like I was refreshing
souls particularly.
I certainly didn't feel like I was
glorifying God.
I was gonna...
Could you have built that in though?
Cause this is one thing.
I always think people think they're
gonna find meaning.
It wasn't my thing.
It just wasn't my thing.
And so I went in search of
something where I could answer my
why question like Bach.
I became a social scientist.
That was the thing?
That was it.
Because, you know, when I...
Because after that, you also, you
go on to run the think tank
after that, right?
Right. Yeah.
So I got my PhD.
I actually finished college a month
before my 30th birthday by correspondence.
So this is not a typical path
to, you know, a professorship at Harvard.
Obviously, this is not typically the
way it gets done.
This is a great country, isn't it?
I agree.
Yeah.
A kid from Puyallup can do this.
It's fantastic.
Crazy.
I love that.
So, and then I went and I
got so interested when I was doing
my bachelor's degree in human behavior
and the fact that you can model
it and you can study it that
I went back and got my master's
and PhD as a social scientist, as
a quantitative social scientist.
I was doing...
For a living, I was doing military
operations research at the RAND Corporation for,
you know, like secret stuff for the
Air Force and all that.
But, you know, using...
And you felt the sense of meaning
in all that?
I was, what I felt the sense
of meaning in was I was learning
so much that was
so critically interesting.
And I had a strong sense that
I was going to, I was learning
how to
ask and answer original questions
about human behavior that are going
to push the boundary
of what we knew so that people's
lives could get better.
I had a very strong sense that
it was going to, it was in
the offing.
It was going to take decades.
Was the part about so people's lives
could be better?
Was that a critical part of that?
It was a critical thing.
To earn my success, I needed to
do something where my work created value
in my life and the life of
other people.
That's what I felt like I needed
to do.
I think that that is so big.
And look, you cover this in the book.
So I know this isn't mysterious to
you, but focusing outward.
Like if you want to be happy,
we don't need, this is me paraphrasing
you again.
We don't need self-care.
We need other care.
Right.
And I just have learned through unfortunate
trial and error
that if I'm doing something only for
me, I'll run ashore on the me,
me, me problem.
Totally.
And so you get into the me
-self world.
It's all me-self.
You know, other care is I-self.
It's I'm going to look outward at
what other people need.
I'm going to be thinking more about
them, which gets me away from the
boring, repetitive tedium of the me,
me, me soundtrack to begin with.
I mean, it has, I mean, it's
just simple.
You're distracted from the stuff that's
so boring.
And yet, so you look at so
obsessively over the course of your life.
So that's critically important.
And you find, I mean, again, there's
tons and tons of studies that actually
show that the
more you give, the happier you get.
The more you give, the richer you get.
The more you give, the better looking
you are.
It's a wonderful study.
What?
It's all perception.
So there's this one study where these
guys, these social psychologists,
they bring men.
It's men in the lab who are partnered.
And it's all heterosexual couples.
And they bring them in.
Some have been dating for six months
and some have been married for 50 years.
And that the guys in white lab
coats and they say, okay, it's a
simple experiment.
I'm going to, sir, I'm going to
give you these coins, put them in
your pocket.
You and your wife or girlfriend, you're
going to walk down this little path
to that other
building down there.
And my colleague is going to interview you.
And then you get to keep the money.
That's it.
So I walked down this little path
outside and there's an alleyway between
the buildings.
And this homeless guy comes ambling
out of the alley and panhandles the
husband or boyfriend.
He's a confederate to the experiment, obviously.
He says, hey, you got some change?
He does.
They know he does because they put
the money in his pocket.
And he has to make a decision
in front of his wife on whether
he's going to help the
homeless guy.
They get to the other building.
And the first question in the interview
is, did you help the homeless guy?
How much did you give him?
And then the second question is to
the wife, how attractive do you find
him right now?
The more you support the homeless
guy, the hotter she finds you.
That's so interesting.
That's the reason on a first date,
you're like, I love humanity.
I support, you know, I build houses
for the poor.
I love dogs.
I love babies.
You're trying to look like, you know,
Albert Schweitzer on a first date.
That's hilarious.
Because you're more handsome.
That is very interesting.
Okay.
So we know that being outward focus
is going to be beneficial.
But you were talking about you needed
to find the answer to your why.
What is going to be that thing
that I could answer in the way
that Bach does?
I find in life, basically, nobody
finds that.
Like that is so rare.
And when they do find it, it
ends up being very transient.
So how did you navigate?
Because for people that don't know,
we did another interview, which I
highly encourage
them to go watch.
And so we covered this.
I don't want to tread a ton
of the same ground.
But I think it's worth telling people,
would you say that your career has
been spiral?
Yeah, for sure.
Okay.
You gave me the language.
Mine has for sure.
It's interesting.
You make me question whether that's
just my personality.
And I was going to end up
there no matter what, or if it
really was what I, the story
I've told myself my entire life, which
is I did all of this just
to get into storytelling
and I needed to control the assets.
Maybe we'll get into that.
Well, those are endogenous to each other.
Yeah, maybe.
But what I want to know now
is, did your why run out?
And that's why you reinvented yourself?
Did it just migrate?
Like, how have you kept that alive
in your life?
I took opportunities that were put
in my path that I thought were
in line with this
vision of how I was trying to grow.
So I had an intention, but I
didn't have attachment.
So when I was a French horn
player, leaving that and becoming
a social scientist, I had
an intention to do this work on
human behavior to help myself and
others, to make life better,
to increase love and happiness in
other people's lives.
But I was not attached to what
manifestation that was going to take.
And that's what I urge all young
people to do, to have a virtuous,
beautiful intention
without attachment with respect to
the expression that it's going to
take at any particular
time.
I taught for a number of years.
I loved it.
Super great.
And then I thought, I should run
something that I think is going to
be good for humanity
and for society, you know?
I ran this think tank, this big
think tank in Washington, D.C.
I have 300 employees, mostly just
raised money.
I had to raise $50 million a
year to keep the doors open.
And it was a thrilling experience.
It was exhausting to be sure.
But what I was trying to do
was to use my background as a
social scientist to create
better public policy, to hire really
good people that was going to make
the country
and the world freer and better with
an emphasis on opportunity for people
at the margins of
society, which is what my think tank
was engaged in.
After about 10 years, I knew I
was getting stale, man.
I was getting stale.
So I had the same intention, but
I had no attachment to Arthur Brooks,
president of
the American Enterprise Institute.
That would be a disordered attachment
because that's not who I am.
I'm Arthur Brooks.
I'm a husband.
I'm a father.
I'm a child of God.
And I am put on earth to
lift people up in bonds of love
and happiness using science
and ideas.
What's the next assignment?
And the next assignment was to do
what I do now, which is I
have a company that teaches,
writes, speaks and teaches widely
and does media on the science of
happiness to popularize,
to see the world as a classroom
and an enormous course of study of
the science of happiness
to lift people up.
And that, you know, so I can
write a column in Atlantic and I
read books and I get to
talk to you and I get to
travel and speak.
I teach at Harvard and it's phenomenal.
But that's not, I'm not attached because
I know this is not the last assignment.
I have intention, but the attachment,
no, no, no, no, no, no.
The attachment is the killer of all
of these things.
And you too.
It's like, next assignment, please.
But here's the direction we're going in.
I need to do this thing.
This thing is going to serve.
And when you're really in the zone,
it's a thrill.
It's a thrill.
You just can't get it off of
it when you're really in the zone too.
But it's not because you're going
for the thrill.
It's because you're going for the value.
You want the, you want to hit
that vein of value, right?
And when you run that vein out,
then you go look for it.
You dig a new mine.
What does it mean to run the
vein out though?
So, okay.
How pure was your move into the
think tank?
Because you talk about idols.
I've listened to enough of your content.
I know what your idol is.
I think we share an idol.
So, nothing is either good or bad,
but thinking makes it so.
So, I don't know that having an
idol is bad.
I have a feeling that it's nature's
way of getting us moving
and making us an active species.
And it is how we use it
for great good.
But if it's the end goal, if
an idol of money or power
or pleasure or fame is the end goal,
we'll be onto you and we'll be
onto the world.
But if it's an intermediate goal to
lifting people up
and bringing them together, if you
can use the prestige
that you have in your job and
the admiration of other people
to get them interested in something
that's truly generative
and good and improve their lives,
which by the way,
you're doing with the show, right?
I mean, you've got lots of prestige,
you're a famous guy,
but you're using it so that people
will watch it
and change their lives.
So, this is the end goal to problem.
If it's an intermediate goal, then
it's good.
I want to restate this in my language
to see if I really understand this.
Okay, so the me self is getting
caught up in my emotions.
I'm confusing the emotion for the
perception of the emotion.
So, knowing that in the brain, pain
and suffering
are two separate spaces, knowing literally
two different regions of the brain,
not making that up for people listening.
And then in meditation, I am to
your point earlier
about the bitter coffee.
There's a difference between my knee hurts
and witnessing that I'm having a sensation
in my knee
that one might articulate that pain.
But my knee hurts versus I don't
like how my knee feels.
Right.
That's really a big difference because,
you know,
it's my knee hurts.
That's a statement of fact.
Right.
Right, it's a signal.
And the one last thing I'll wrap
on that
to see if I really get this.
So, Viktor Frankl talked about the gap
between stimulus and response.
Now, for people that haven't heard
that name,
he was in a concentration camp, lost
his wife,
mom, dad, I mean, just unimaginable
amounts of loss.
His whole family, right.
And came out of it, psychiatrist,
came out, or actually, I think a neuroscientist.
Psychiatrist, and he was a psychiatrist
and a psychoanalyst.
Okay.
Which is an interesting combination.
Very interesting.
Writes a book about that time, basically saying,
if you could find meaning in your suffering,
that you could make it.
But if you lost that sense, he
was like,
you could literally predict when somebody
would die
because once they gave up
and they could no longer associate meaning
with why they were going through the suffering,
that was it.
And so, that idea of there's this gap
between stimulus and response,
and you get to decide how you
interpret that thing
is everything.
Right.
Is that what you're talking about?
When that gap goes away, you're now
in me territory.
Yeah.
So, there's so much in this.
And we've referred to the new book.
And the whole front part of this
new book
is emotional self-management based
on the science
of how your brain gives you signals
that are called emotions.
Getting away from the idea that bad emotions
are unfortunate, we should get rid
of them.
Or that unhappiness for them is bad,
and we should get rid of it.
So, understanding the science of how
this works
and what these things are for,
and then being able to learn, grow,
and manage the feelings that we want
such that we can adapt best to
the current world,
and we can make growth toward happierness.
That's the whole front part of this book.
The back half is, okay, now that
you've done that.
Build the life you want.
Co-authored with Oprah Winfrey.
Exactly right.
It's a good book, by the way.
I'm glad you like it.
Thank you.
It was a joy to write it.
It's a joy writing a book with
Oprah Winfrey, too.
What an experience.
It was really an interesting experience.
And recording the book, the audio
book, too,
because you keep thinking,
oh, I know that voice.
Not mine.
So, emotional self-management comes
down to,
number one, understanding that emotions
that you have
are not just nice to have and
bad to have.
All they are are signals.
They're like the machine of your brain
perceives outside stimuli
and turns it into a universal language
that can send signals to the neocortex
of your brain,
the outside wrinkly area of your brain,
especially the prefrontal cortex,
which is the most modern part of
the human brain,
to send a signal so that you
can decide
how to react according to them.
And it doesn't matter what language
you speak
or where you grew up.
Everybody gets the same signals.
They get the basic emotions of joy,
of interest,
which are the two positive basic emotions.
The negative emotions,
which doesn't mean that they're bad,
just means that they're negative.
Anger, disgust, sadness, fear.
And all those things are then blended together
into these complex emotions.
So, anger and disgust, you blend them together,
you get contempt,
which is the conviction of the worthlessness
of something.
So, it's this multiplicity of emotions
that we get.
They exist to send signals, universal signals,
and then we get to decide how
to react.
Here's the problem.
Most people don't take that opportunity.
Most people take their emotions as given,
regret them, like them, and act according
to them
without doing that last trick,
that last entrepreneurial trick,
which is deciding how to react.
You get to decide.
This is Viktor Frankl's point.
The book is Man's Search for Meaning.
And what he learned in the concentration camp
was that all these bad things are happening
and good things happen in life.
You decide how you're going to react
to these things.
That's the ultimate entrepreneurial
task of human life
is deciding how you're going to use
the resources
under your control.
And the first set of resources you
get are your emotions.
Okay, so the time between the stimulus
and response,
the time between the emotions
and the reactions that you decide,
that's the gap that Viktor Frankl
is talking about.
You want that to be as wide
as possible.
That's why, and every time you have
an emotion,
the most important thing to do is
to not react,
is to practice not reacting when you
feel something,
good or bad.
Wait.
Tell me why.
Because this is where I see people
get lost all the time.
They trust their emotions.
They think their emotions are right.
They are a map of actual reality.
And that if you feel angry, you
should act angry.
And that's a great way to live
an unhappy life
and make other people unhappy around you.
I agree so violently.
I can't even tell you.
Yeah, yeah.
And think about all the times
when you're building your companies
that you felt something negative.
And if you just yelled it, you
snapped at somebody
or said that was on your mind,
you would have done catastrophic brain damage
to your company.
It would have been terrible.
Instead, or you get that email.
You know, you get an email and
it's like,
I want to answer right now.
Don't.
Never answer a bad email on the
day you get it.
Never.
Just have an automatic, as a matter
of fact,
have somebody who's managing your
email for you
so you don't see them.
You see them and you think about it,
but you can't answer it
because it disappears from your inbox
for 24 hours.
Make a deal with somebody.
Why?
Because you want your prefrontal cortex
to be in charge.
You don't want your limbic system
It's a two-year-old.
You know, when kids, when you have
little kids
and, you know, I have grown kids,
but now I have grandchildren and they yell.
And what you tell little kids always
is use your words.
What you're telling them is put more time
between stimulus and response
and choose the response that you want.
You're not going to say that to
a little kid.
You're going to say something that's truncated,
like use your words.
And people who are reactive,
what we say as social scientists,
we call them limbic people
because they're acting according to
their limbic system.
This is the most unentrepreneurial
thing to do.
That's basically like, I got a dollar,
I spent a dollar.
Revenue comes in, you decide what
to do.
Should you invest it?
Should you distribute it?
Should you buy something with it?
What should you do?
That's what good entrepreneurs do
with their lives,
but that's how we need to see
our emotion.
So that's the most important point.
Now, what you do in that gap
is called metacognition.
And this is where it gets really,
really interesting.
In that gap, the best thing that
you can possibly do
is to think about the emotions that
you're feeling,
what they mean, and how best to
use them.
So that, and this is really the engagement
of your prefrontal cortex.
That's what meditation practices tell
you to do.
This is what prayer helps you to do.
This is what walking in nature helps
you to do.
So all these metacognitive practices,
this is what therapy is supposed to
do too, by the way.
It's supposed to give you expertise
in expanding that gap.
Then on top of that, there's all
of these ideas
that you can use.
Once you've got this time, you can
make these decisions.
You can substitute emotions.
You can say, that's not the right emotion.
Here's a better emotion.
You can literally do that.
How's that not just faking it?
It's not, it's what it's...
So for example, I've talked a lot
and I've been palling around lately
with, you know, Rainn Wilson, who's
the actor
from The Office.
Yeah, I've had him on the show.
He's terrific.
And we grew up, he grew up
in Ballard.
Yeah.
And so five miles away from me.
He's just the same age as me.
He was a classical musician, just
like I was.
I didn't know him, but we have parallel.
Wait, did he play like Bassoon or something?
He played the Bassoon.
I played the French horn.
We probably overlapped in Allstate Band
or something as we were kids,
but we have the same childhood basically.
And so it's interesting.
And so we really connect on this.
But for example, he talks about the
fact that most,
he believes that most comedians
suffer from depression.
And one of the reasons they're such
good comedians
is because they choose the substitute emotion
when they're feeling sadness of humor,
which is also an appropriate response
to things that are making you sad.
You make them into a joke
and people think of it as the
defense mechanism.
No, it's an emotional substitution.
It's the, when you drink coffee,
the caffeine molecule,
it looks just like the adenosine molecule,
which is a neuromodulator that is inhibitory.
It makes you feel tired.
It goes into the slot,
into the receptor for the adenosine.
And so you don't get adenosine.
That's what makes you feel peppy.
It blocks the thing that makes you
feel tired.
That's how caffeine works.
Emotional substitution works in the
same way.
The humor molecule goes into the sadness receptor,
but you can't do that unless you're
taking time.
You cannot do that unless you actually
expand the time
between stimulus and response
until you understand exactly how the
science works
and getting as much time as you
possibly can.
Was that the angle that you took
to understand the science
or did you come at it from
a God says
that this is the way to go
about life?
I'm a scientist, you know,
and one of the reasons that I
am religious
is because of my,
because what I've learned intellectually.
So for me, that was the thing
that freed me as well was,
so I'm call it 22.
I am very unhappy,
like really scary sliding towards
depression and happy.
And I started reading about the brain
and I don't remember what gave me
that impulse.
It was probably something I learned
in college
plus Taoism, whatever,
but it like really made me think
about the way the brain worked.
And I started reading about how brain plasticity
was this hotly debated thing.
And maybe you really could teach an
old dog new tricks.
And one day I just decided
I'm going to act as if brain
plasticity is real.
And then the more studies came out
that showed that it really was real.
Like the more I felt like I
could grab ahold of that,
but it was a science based insight
that allowed me to really change the tenor
of my entire life.
For sure.
I mean, it's interesting
because people back when I was a kid,
I'm 10 years old,
a little over 10 years older than you.
And when I was a kid
or even when people were older than me
were coming through the whole idea
was that biology is just psychology.
You know, that you can think bad
things away.
And that was supposed to be really
incredibly empowering.
Now, really what we believe with the
advent of,
you know, the advances in neuroscience,
you know, as a social scientist,
I have to know tons of neuroscience.
Teaching happiness is 30% neuroscience.
What I teach, I'm talking about the
brain constantly.
It's much more the case.
We believe that psychology is actually biology.
And that sounds like it's not empowering.
Like this is all determined.
Wow, it's super empowering.
It's super empowering
because once you actually understand
the process,
you can intervene in the process.
I talked to young executives, for example,
and I say, one of the biggest
threats to your career
is an inappropriate sexual relationship
in the workplace.
Dude, that's so hilarious to me.
It's and so we say,
so let's understand how this is going
to work.
And you can psychologize it and say,
you know, you need to get some therapy.
What happens is the first thing
when you have attraction towards somebody
who's a potential romantic partner,
there's the first thing that happens
is sex hormones,
which testosterone and estrogen.
And in combination in both males and females,
this is happening.
The second thing that happens
in the neurochemical cascade of falling
in love
is there's an up and there's an increase
in norepinephrine and dopamine
so that you get the sense of
euphoria and anticipation.
The third thing that happens is a
drop in serotonin.
Now what happens when serotonin, a
drop in serotonin?
Interesting.
When serotonin drops, it makes you ruminate.
That's the reason it's associated
with clinical depression
because of the rumination procedure.
And so there's a part of the brain
called the ventrolateral prefrontal cortex,
which is incredibly active when you're ruminating.
It's one of the things when you're ruminating
on a business plan, on an opera,
on a poem,
on somebody who's rejected you.
So you see it incredibly active in depression
and creativity and falling in love
and all of these things that all
have rumination,
you know, iterative rumination involved
in it.
So it all is involved with a
drop in serotonin,
which is why you don't want to
have that early stages
of falling in love for the rest
of your life
because you'll want to die.
And then the last-
You'll want to die.
The early stages of love made me
feel like
I'd never get anything done again.
Yeah, yeah.
It makes you feel out of control.
Your brain looks suspiciously like
an MRI
in the brain of a methamphetamine addict.
Yeah, yeah.
That's how it felt.
I legitimately felt like I was on drugs.
And then you get the tide, the
warm tide
that comes in of the increases in oxytocin,
which is a bonding neuropeptide
that functions as a hormone in the brain.
Do you get that before it's reciprocated?
You-
Well, I mean, it happens when you
have eye contact
with somebody in a love connection,
eye contact, so you're both getting it.
The biggest bolus that you get of that
is when you first lay eyes on
eye contact
with your newborn baby.
Really?
Yeah, it's just like 4th of July
in your head.
But anyway, so it's one, two, three, four.
That's the neurochemical cascade.
The reason I bring this up
is when I'm talking to young people
in business,
I say, if you do not intervene
early enough
in this neurochemical cascade,
you're going to be in trouble
because it'll be out of control.
It'll be like, you know, no brakes
on the roller coaster.
And it's like, I have this incredible career
and this incredible job.
I don't know what happened.
We slept together and now I'm fired.
And you see it all the time.
Like Harvard Business School case study.
What happened?
Well, they let the neurochemical cascade
go too long
and you have to intervene.
Number one, don't put yourself in
a position
where you go to step two.
Don't put yourself in a position
where you go to step three.
What are you doing?
You're managing your brain.
And if you don't know the brain science,
you can't do that.
That's why this stuff is so incredibly empowering.
And when you read that stuff for
the first time,
you're like, oh, there's something
I can do here.
Now there's something I can use.
It's not just psychology.
Now it's something that's more tangible
than that
because the grandeur of this entire experience
has a biological basis
and one that I can understand
and one I can actually manage.
Yeah.
For me being able to picture the thing,
that helps a lot.
Yeah.
Once I could understand the myelination process,
I was like, oh, okay.
Now I get why this is something
I need to repeat.
Once I understood that the brain is
a caloric hog
and from an evolutionary standpoint,
that means anything that you do repeatedly,
it's going to hardwire just to make
it more efficient.
And so all of that coming together
really allowed me to begin to-
Improve your habits.
Because your habits, what they were doing
was improving the management of the organ.
And that was affecting your psychology
and your effectiveness and your happiness
and the whole progress that you're
making in your life.
That's why the information is so critically important.
That's why it can be so life-changing
to learn science actually.
For sure.
So what are then the habits of happiness
or maybe a better way,
this is a language you use in
the book,
the macronutrients of happiness.
Like what are those things
that we want to begin building our
lives around
if we really want to thrive?
So people define happiness in a lot
of different ways,
but the biggest mistake that people make
is thinking that it's a feeling,
that happiness is a feeling.
It's not a feeling.
Isn't it?
No, happiness has feelings associated
with it.
Okay.
But to say that my Thanksgiving turkey
has a smell
is different than saying that the
smell of the turkey
is the Thanksgiving dinner.
Right.
So that's a really big distinction
that it's important to make.
So your Thanksgiving dinner
is protein, carbohydrates and fat.
That's literally what your Thanksgiving
dinner is.
It also has a delicious smell
that attracts you to it and that
you want.
And if it didn't have that or
had the wrong smell,
it smelled like you're microwaving trash
when you walked into mom's house for Thanksgiving,
you'd be like, something's wrong here.
So, but getting past the feelings
on happiness
is what will set you free
to be able to manage it appropriately.
Growing a business is hard.
NetSuite is the number one cloud financial system,
streamlining accounting, financial management,
inventory, HR, and more.
Manage risk, get reliable forecasts,
and improve your margins.
Right now, you can download NetSuite's
popular KPI checklist,
designed to give you consistently
excellent performance,
absolutely free, netsuite.com slash theory.
What I want to understand
when you started the think tank and
when you stopped,
obviously because we did the other interview
and I know your other book,
From Strength to Strength,
and I know the two big movements
in somebody's life
where you go from fluid intelligence
to crystalline intelligence,
where you're really bringing wisdom
to the table,
and that was your transitional moment
between those two.
So I understand all of that.
But at the same time, I do
wonder if
there were just other things caught
up in it
and that maybe the either,
I've heard you say you were no
longer making progress
when you were a French horn player,
and that's what made you want to
leave that.
I'm wondering if you felt like
you were no longer making progress
in the think tank,
and that's why you wanted to leave that.
Is that the moment where we all go,
oh, that's my cue now to find
that next assignment?
That's what we should use as a cue,
the natural cadence of the value that
you're creating.
Very, very few people get to create
more and more and more value
in one exact thing over the course
of their lives.
And we have an economy that accommodates change.
So it's really incumbent upon us
to have our antennae up and pay
attention to that
because we want to be able to
create that value
and be open to the next assignment.
So yeah, I mean, my motives are
never pure
because I'm just a guy.
But I do have a process of discernment.
Every philosophical and religious tradition
has a process of discernment.
Discernment is when you don't know
what to do, how you figure it out.
This is hard, the decision-making process.
And so I'll have students who are like,
I don't know, should I do a startup
or go work in investment banking?
Or should I marry this person or not?
Or should I go to law school
or stay at work?
Or some things are even more personal
and delicate and difficult.
But at any particular time,
a third of the people who are
watching us
are agonizing over a particular decision.
So the question is,
how do you make these difficult decisions?
And every philosophical tradition
has a process
on how to make a decision.
And here's the key thing that they
all have in common.
You got to do the work.
And to do the work means you
need to think about it.
It doesn't mean you need to think
about a particular thing.
You need to think about that decision process
every day.
What are you thinking about?
So when I have students that haven't
even begun this process,
I'll say, okay, 15 minutes a day,
I want you to start by sitting
alone at your desk,
no music, no phone is not there.
Write lists of things you like.
You got to start getting in touch
with the things that are attractive
to you.
Because some people are completely
even divorced from that.
They have no, they're so far away
from being able to discern what they
want to do
that they don't even know what they like.
And so just starting to write places
I've gone
that I really enjoyed,
not because you're deciding where
to go next,
but just because you're trying to
get that
in order in your head.
What are the things that are attractive
to me?
What are the things that I actually like?
I'll tell people that they should,
to be thinking about just a process
to let the discernment happen.
You have to be very quiet and
very concerted
in the effort to do so.
To walk for an hour before dawn,
every day with no devices.
And to do that.
So people who are really religious,
I'll say 15 minutes a day praying
about this
to be given the discernment,
to be given proper discernment,
15 minutes a day on your knees.
So, and, or meditation practice.
There's lots of ways to do this.
What's the difference between prayer
and meditation?
Is there one?
Well, there's lots of forms of prayer
and lots of forms of meditation.
So there are a lot of meditation techniques,
single point meditation, analytical meditation,
meditation of compassion,
all different sort of Theravada, Mahayana traditions.
Are you trying to make your best
case to God?
Or are you just repeating an idea
in your head?
Like, please grant me the discernment
to understand what I should do in
this moment.
So there are different ways to do it.
There are different forms of prayer,
even Christian prayer, even Catholic prayer,
which is what I engage in.
So every night I pray 25 minutes,
which is called the Rosary,
a thousand-year-old meditative prayer
before I go to sleep every night.
And that's a thing you repeat.
And it's a thing that you repeat
while you're meditating on particular mysteries
that happened in biblical tradition.
And what are you doing?
You're focusing,
you're seeing your life through the lens
of these great stories.
And what that does is helps you
understand yourself better
in all kinds of insight.
Insight comes to you over the context
of this process.
That's a kind of a centering prayer.
There are other prayers that are called
mental prayer,
which the Buddhists call analytical meditation.
The Dalai Lama wakes up every morning
and the first two hours are analytical meditation
where he'll just think deeply
about a passage in Tibetan Buddhist scripture.
He's thinking about it.
He's not reading it.
He's written down a few lines
and he's looking at it and thinking
about it
for two hours.
He gets 88 and he's doing that
for the first two hours of every day.
That's analytical meditation.
That's not just like looking at a flame
or doing soul cycle or something.
That's not, he's, and that's also meditation,
incredibly important.
Mental prayer is the same thing
where you'll read a passage of scripture,
whether your scripture is the suttas
or the New Testament or whatever your
thing is.
And you read it and you say,
and you say, what is this meaning
to me?
Where am I in this?
How is this impacting my life?
Two sentences, 15 minutes, more.
It's crazy how much insight
you can actually get from that.
There's compassionate meditation
or compassionate prayer
where you bring into your mind
the people that are giving you struggle
and you think about,
you visualize good things happening
to them
and you ask God or you ask
the cosmos
that good things,
that blessings be rain down upon them
and you change the nature
of your orientation toward them.
The biggest reason that you have enmity
with other people
is because of your enmity toward them,
not theirs toward you, typically.
And you can literally change that
and this is one of the techniques
for doing so.
So different kinds of prayer and meditation,
they have different functions,
but we have to use them as such
and not just be kind of like,
all right, like a little kid,
like God, I sure hope I get
an A on that exam.
Can you please help me get an
A on that exam?
You have to be a grownup about
this stuff
and it's super exciting.
And it, so that's the process of discernment
when you're trying to figure out what
to do
is you have to concentrate on it.
The ancient Greeks called it sunesis.
In the Pali Buddhist tradition,
in the Mahayana Buddhist tradition,
it's called panna.
And in this discernment of spirits
in Ignatian Catholic spirituality,
every tradition has it
where you're focused on it,
focused on it, focused on it
for a particular period of time.
If you do the work
where you're focused on the decision,
looking for the insight for 15 minutes
a day
for two months, you'll have clarity.
That's the guarantee.
It's amazing.
But the reason that people can't get clarity
is because they don't do the work.
They don't do the analysis.
Yeah, for sure.
Okay, walk me through the idols.
What are the idols
and how do we use them well
instead of being used by them?
So this is a tradition
that comes from Neoplatonism,
sort of from Plato
as best stated by his great pupil, Aristotle,
and then translated
into the Islamic Jewish
and Christian traditions
in the Middle Ages.
So Averroes, who is the, you know,
the Muslim philosopher
for me from southern Spain,
Moshe ben Mammonides
and Thomas Aquinas.
So these are the, you know,
St. Thomas Aquinas,
these are the great figures of this.
And they really, they translated Aristotle
into saying that Aristotle
was the greatest
of all the social scientists.
I mean, I realize
I'm cheapening Aristotle
in this way by saying it,
but it's kind of a conceit
that everybody you love is like,
Tom, you're a great social scientist.
That's like the ultimate compliment
from a social scientist.
So by the way,
you're a very good social scientist.
So for example,
Aquinas said that there's
four substitutes for God,
that he believed,
as did Averroes and Mammonides
and all of the monotheistic
religious leaders,
that what we ultimately want is God.
Now, atheists watching us
or agnostics disagree with that,
but we all want something.
Can you define what that means then?
To define, to want God?
Yeah, because I have a feeling
even atheists want a thing
to fit that God-shaped hole,
but I've never taken the time
for myself to define
what the God-shaped hole is.
So I'd love to know.
Yeah, so this is the thing,
for example,
you're looking for something
that's defined by your craving.
You know, when you're really,
really hungry,
it proves the existence of food.
When you're really, really horny,
it proves the existence of sex.
Right?
And so when you're really,
really are seeking
the complex singularity,
the source of all truth,
the cosmic oneness,
it's proof that it exists.
But what is it?
Okay, so that's what different traditions
have been trying to explain
for the longest time.
This is really interesting though,
by the way,
I don't want to just let that
roll past.
Hunger is the proof
that there is food.
The desire for sex is proof
that there is sex.
The desire for it.
Or it's evidence that there is sex.
It's not a proof in the classical sense,
but it's evidence that it exists.
Evidence.
And so it'd be really,
really, really weird
if you had a craving for something
and the object of the craving didn't exist.
It doesn't really make sense.
And so if you have a craving
for the oneness.
Arthur Brooks, this is good.
And this is, by the way,
this is one of the reasons
that when all of the conversations
that we're having about AI,
they're all misguided.
AI can't give us what we want.
It can't.
Because all it does
is gives us complicating
engineering solutions
for a simulacrum for the thing
that we're for a simulation
for the thing that we really, really want,
which is a different species of problem.
You know, what we really want
is the object of all the complexity
of the universe.
Complexity is simple to understand
and impossible to solve.
Complication is hard to solve,
but possible.
All of the reasons
all these things that we do in tech
that are that promise everything
and deliver nothing but loneliness.
The reason is because
they're complicated solutions
to complex needs.
Love is complex.
It's very easy to understand
and impossible to figure out.
Your cat is complex,
very simple,
but impossible to know
what it's going to do.
All the things we really want in life,
all of our deep desires are complex.
All of our solutions are complicated.
And we're throwing
complicated solutions at complex problems,
and we're not getting happier.
And so the only way that we
can do this
is to take quiet time
in contemplation of the complex.
That's the solution.
Now, are you going to find it?
No, no,
but it's just like happiness.
You're not going to find it.
You're going to make progress toward it.
The goal, the metaphysical goal,
the transcendental goal
of a spiritual or philosophical life
is the approach to the complex oneness,
to the ultimate truth that we crave.
And you got to do the work.
Stop distracting yourself with social media.
Stop distracting yourself by saying,
if I make the money,
then everything will be okay.
Or if I have the precision,
this gets us back to the idols.
Aquinas said that we crave God,
but God is complex and hard to understand
and has all kinds of demands
and winds us up
in all sorts of one-sided conversations.
And so, we take a complicated solution
to the complex problem
and things that are kind of God-like.
You know, social media
is kind of social life-like,
which is why when we're lonely,
we'll binge it,
but it doesn't help.
And the social media equivalent
for what we want in God,
according to Aquinas,
is fourfold, money, power, pleasure,
and honor,
by which he meant fame or admiration
or prestige.
That's what he said to the four things.
And those are the idols.
And everybody's got their idol
that when they're not on their game
looking for the cosmic oneness,
despite the fact that they'll never
find it,
they'll say, okay, fine, I'm tired.
I'm gonna go do that thing
that's a simulation for it.
And it always runs you in the
wrong direction.
It runs you in the wrong direction.
And only when you know what your
idol is,
can you actually manage yourself.
So you say, oh, I'm doing that again.
I'm doing that again.
I'm looking for money again
when what I really wanted was love.
I'm looking for admiration again
when what I really wanted was enlightenment.
Because you didn't want to do the
work for enlightenment.
So you went and did the easy thing,
which was getting the idol.
So is enlightenment a stand-in for God?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I mean, the whole point is that
these are...
Enlightenment is something...
Enlightenment would be what Christians
or Muslims
would call the beatific vision,
which is to finally lay your eyes
on the face of God,
which is actual truth.
If you're a Buddhist,
it means because you finally understand.
You're sitting under the Bodhi tree
and you finally get it is what
it comes to.
You know, we in the monotheistic traditions,
we don't believe you get it on
this side of death.
Buddhists think that you actually
can achieve it,
but be that as it may.
I mean, I don't know.
I have my hypothesis.
But I do know that we all
need to move toward it.
We all need to do the work
toward it.
And getting the AI is not going
to do it.
Anymore than Facebook is going to
do it.
Interesting that you're linking...
Because I don't think of AI as God,
but I hear a lot of people
talk about that,
that it will end up being God-like.
So it's interesting if they really
are looking for that in AI.
I think what I'm looking for...
I'm trying to fill the whole God
-like hole with it,
is all I'm saying.
So I will grant you that for
anybody doing that,
that would be a tremendous mistake.
And I'll give you my thesis on
what I think all this is in
a second.
But AI, I think, for me anyway,
it is to finally get answers to
the complex,
which may be your entire definition
of God.
But that's an exercise in futility.
That's interesting.
I don't know that I would agree
with that.
So I feel like...
Look, I don't have...
The data that I have to back
up the following is merely physics.
Right.
As we grow...
Huh?
Well, we don't understand physics.
Simple physics.
The reason I bring that up is
because as we strip layers off that onion,
it unlocks things that we couldn't
do before.
And all of us have grown up
in a world where Einsteinian,
Einsteinian, whichever way you would
say that,
physics already exists.
Yeah.
And not realizing that before that
it was Newtonian physics.
Right.
And that the shift between the two
unlocked the modern world.
Right.
And we think of him as just
sort of this crazy haired guy.
And we forget that so many of
the things that we rely on in
the modern world
required us to understand that breakthrough.
But it isn't the universal principle yet.
We haven't gotten there.
We haven't got Higgs boson, which
will show...
Which will render Einsteinian physics
obsolete in all kinds of ways.
Fingers crossed.
So as we begin to unlock these
things and truly understand them,
it really does open up avenues of technology.
Now, one has to be careful not
to view technology as a God.
But if we can use AI to
either augment our own intelligence
or for it to itself be intelligent.
Now, I'm wildly conflicted by AI.
Let me be abundantly clear.
We all are.
Yes.
Deploying it as fast as I can.
And at the same time, I'm terrified.
But I want those answers have real
world implications.
That's the moral of my story.
Yeah.
Yeah, for sure.
Absolutely.
They do.
But the point is that AI and
all of these particular tools,
they solve a different species of problem.
Yeah, they are not going to answer
the God.
They're not going to, because they can't.
And the whole idea is that there's
always this concept
that we could understand everything
if we had sufficient computational horsepower.
But that's not right.
Because you can't solve complex problems,
which are mathematically different
than complicated problems.
Yes.
Give me an example of...
So for people that don't know,
you did applied mathematics for a while.
So it's not me asking some random
guy off the street.
Give me an example of...
A complex and a complicated problem.
Yes, because in math, the only thing
I can think of,
because I am wildly ignorant, I would
like to be abundantly clear.
But from my just not knowing math
at all perspective,
the only category of thing in math
that I know as being complex
would be something like the pi.
So pi is, if Yosha Bach is correct,
better understood as a function rather
than a number
because you can never know the final
digit of pi.
It's a relationship.
Interesting.
Yeah, it's a relationship.
So I'll give you an example of two.
Is that complex?
Yeah, well, it's a good question whether
or not it's complex.
I think about it in a slightly
different way.
So I'll give you an example that
might make it clearer.
So a complicated problem is one that
has 75 equations and 75 unknowns.
It's a highly dimensional mathematical problem
that it would just take tons of
computational horsepower to figure out.
But there is a solution.
Designing a jet engine is an incredibly
complicated problem.
Making a toaster is a complicated problem.
You know, if you try to do
one out in your garage with, you know,
stuff that's sitting around your house,
you'll probably burn your house down
if you try to make toast with it.
It's a very complicated thing to do.
But once you do it, you can
do it over and over and over again
with almost complete accuracy.
That's these are complex, complicated problems.
A complex problem is a football game.
A football game is a complicated problem
where I don't care how good your
computer is.
You're not going to be able to
tell me the outcome because it's complex.
It's complex.
It's I think I misspoke.
You said complicated ones and complex ones.
But yeah, it's a complex problem.
A complex problem is incredibly simple
to understand the outcome.
You know, the Patriots score higher
than the Broncos.
That's, you know, the natural order
of things that they that is just
one team has a higher score than
the other and wins.
Very simple.
Incredibly simple.
But it's unbelievably, the permutations
are so vast that you can't simulate it.
And you don't think that's knowable
with enough computation?
It's not knowable with enough computation.
But actually, and even if that one
turns out to be,
that turns out to be not a
complex problem, but a complicated problem.
There are complex problems like the
problem of love.
The problem of love is very simple.
And yet it's not something that you
can simulate in any real way.
Some people will say, well, you have
your AI girlfriend.
You've cracked the code of love.
No, you haven't.
There's nobody watching us right now.
It's like, yeah, AI girlfriend just
as good.
No, no, AI girlfriend, a substitute
because I can't get the real thing
is what it would come down to.
That's the difference between pornography
and sex with your wife.
All right.
When two smart people who are well
-meaning think the other person is crazy,
you know, they have different based assumptions.
So to me, that sounds crazy.
And the reason is that I believe
we're in a deterministic universe.
I'm guessing you do not.
I don't believe we're in a deterministic universe.
I believe we're in a stochastic universe.
Okay, define stochastic.
Stochastic means there's randomness
in the universe.
My father was a biostatistician, a
PhD biostatistician,
and he was a devout Christian.
I said, what gives dad?
You know, I'm an adolescent, what gives?
And he said, you don't understand.
He said, you know what miracles are?
And I said, what?
He said, events that are five standard
deviations away from the mean.
They're way out of the tails of
the curves.
You know, the greatest gift that God
ever gave the world was a distribution,
a random distribution of events.
He believed, and I think it's actually
more than plausible,
I think it's most likely that the
universe is actually has randomness
in it,
which means it cannot be, you can't
get to a single point on most
of the,
or any of the complex problems.
You can't, and so you can simulate
a kind of a version of a
curve fit,
but you can't actually get underneath
them and simulate them properly
because we have a stochastic universe
and we live with deterministic brains.
Our brains say that this happens to
this and this happens to this.
We have a supercomputer that's good enough.
We can figure out how it all
hangs together.
And that's the supposition behind
Einsteinian physics or Newtonian physics,
that there's a deterministic structure
underneath that we're simulating.
We're doing the best that we can
to put a model on top.
It's a map, but that's actually probably
not the way that the universe works.
And if that's the case, and if
we have a craving for the source
of that,
then it's something, someone, some entity
that can be the origin of that
complexity per se.
What is it?
You know, it's like maybe my model,
which is,
yeah, I got the Bible and I
got God and I got that whole thing.
Maybe that's nuts.
Maybe it's nuts, but it's a hypothesis.
And it says that we can't get
it from the stuff.
We can't get it from the stuff.
You can only get it by looking
for it, looking for the true thing.
And that's the reason I think that
really great intellectual life
requires that we have both an intellectual
pursuit and a spiritual pursuit
and that we need to undertake these
things in parallel.
I think that's the only responsible
course of action.
What's happening when you're looking
for it?
I can give you, I don't know
that Buddhists would agree with this,
but I think they would.
What you're getting by looking at
it in a Buddhist
or looking for it in a Buddhist tradition
is you're getting out from under the
illusion of perception.
That's definitely a Western look at
it, but that feels pretty accurate.
That's a good way of explaining it.
That's a good way of explaining Buddhist
thinking on it,
that you're no longer bound by the illusions.
What, in the language that we're developing here,
you're no longer bound by your models.
You're actually able to see the road
as opposed to staring at the map
all the time.
It's like, you know, we're looking
at, we got our devices and we're
looking at the GPS.
If you just stare at the GPS,
you're going to crash in your car.
You're actually driving on a road
in real physical life,
but you're more and more and more
divorced from that
when you're stuck with the models.
And those are the illusions that I
would say that you're trying to free
yourself from
by actually imbibing some of the oxygen
in real life around you.
Okay, so if that's the Buddhist take
on it, what is the Catholic take
on it?
The Catholic take on it is very
similar, which is that there is underlying reality,
but that underlying reality is not
always apparent and for all sorts
of reasons.
And that the underlying reality is
made by God and-
Yeah, it is the realm of God.
We just don't have the capacity or
the preparation to be able to experience.
Now, Plato talked about this.
He was pre-Christian.
Plato talked about this, about his
analogy of the shadows on the cave wall.
The closest that we can get to
actually seeing what's going on
is the shadows of what's going on
behind the fire in the cave wall.
A lot of the German philosophers from
the 17th and 18th centuries
and 19th centuries would talk about
this too.
So that Schopenhauer, for example,
Arthur Schopenhauer,
obviously one of the greatest early
19th century,
mid-19th century philosophers would
talk about villa,
which was the sense of will that
the reality exists,
but we can't see it because we're
just not competent.
And we're trying to put one foot
in front of another.
And so we create an edifice that
allows us to live,
but we can't actually see the reality,
that the complex reality is happening
behind it all the time.
What do you think these guys were
struggling with?
And maybe you're from your perspective,
the obvious answer is just God, but-
I don't know if it's just God,
but that's a word for it.
They were struggling for something.
They had a craving.
Because here is the modern take on that.
You're in a simulation.
Now, some people believe you're in
a literal computer simulation
and other people like me,
I don't necessarily have evidence
that you're in an actual computer simulation,
but I do have evidence that your
brain is simulating reality
as a way so that you can
grapple with it.
Because instead of seeing blue,
if you just saw the number of
photons in a given wavelength
that are reflecting off that surface
and into your eye,
it's so complicated.
So your brain is just taking this
incredibly complex universe,
which by the way, for people that
don't know,
the human, our ability to perceive
the actual electromagnetic spectrum
is 0.0035%.
So you're like way, way less than
half a percent-
Tons of dimensionality doesn't exist.
There's tons of things we can't see.
So we've taken this gigantically complex
thing-
We know the things we can't see.
Yeah, for sure.
Yeah.
And we boil it down into something
that is just an absolute sliver of
the reality.
So, okay, in a modern context, I
get it.
But like, what were they coming up
against in whatever 2,000 years ago
when Plato's describing the shadows
on the cave wall?
What is he grappling with?
Like it's, as far as I can tell,
he's getting underneath, like realizing,
oh, my perceptions do not equate to reality.
And once you accept that, like everything
begins to unwind.
Well, it doesn't begin to unwind.
It begins to free you to this
understanding that you're-
You begin to see its illusions.
You begin to see that you are
living in a world of illusion.
Now, how is this that we can
militate against that by saying it's
all in a simulation?
And part of the simulation is that
we're simulated.
The simulation creates the illusion
that there is something bigger,
even though there isn't.
But that's just explaining something away.
So, in a philosophical basis, the
way I talk about this with my students,
I say, okay, we got three choices,
three doors to go through Monty.
This is for those of us, that's
the Monty Hall game in economics
is based on Let's Make a Deal,
this old game show that was on
when I was a kid, right?
And you get the contestants would
have to choose
one of these three doors and then
the door would open up
and it would turn out you either
got a car,
you got a living room set or
you got a goat or something like that.
So, there's basically three choices
about that,
about how you're gonna see the existence
of an underlying reality
that you can or cannot perceive
and you can or cannot get closer
to and make progress toward.
It has to do with the two
concepts of essence and existence.
We believe, we all believe that we exist.
I mean, you can relax that by
saying it's a simulation,
we don't actually exist, I don't know,
but let's leave that for a moment.
And let's just say that we all
agree that there's existence.
What we don't agree on is the
nature of essence.
Essence is meaning.
So, I'm alive and my life has meaning.
Okay, now the traditional philosophical understanding,
the platonic understanding of this,
the ancient Greek understanding of this,
the Christian, Jewish, Hindu,
Muslim, for sure, understanding of this
is that essence precedes existence.
Let's think about that for a second.
The meaning of your life existed before
you were born.
Your job is to live up to
that meaning,
to find that meaning and live up
to that meaning.
It existed, it's a cosmic thing.
That's what comes from the cosmic oneness.
The modern existentialist view, modern philosophy,
a lot of it would say that
existence precedes essence.
You're born without any meaning.
You have to invent meaning the best
you can.
Good luck, that's Sartre.
Like, go sit in a French cafe
and smoke filterless cigarettes
and feel depressed.
As existence precedes essence.
Now, the third, the middle way, the
most depressing way
is the Nietzschean way, which is the
nihilistic way
that says existence exists and essence doesn't.
There is no meaning.
The only responsible course of action
in a life
is to give up on essence.
There is no meaning.
Stop looking for God, stop looking
for enlightenment,
stop looking for all of it.
That created-
He said you couldn't apply meaning?
He said there is no meaning.
There is no meaning.
Life has no meaning.
So you can't apply, because the first
one is,
there is no meaning, but you can
apply meaning.
That there, the first one is that
there is meaning.
You need to find it and live
up to it.
I see.
So the second is that there is
no meaning
until you create it.
And the last is that there is
no meaning.
Got it.
And you can keep looking for it
and you can keep trying to create it.
But that's childish.
Let it go, let it go.
That's nihilism.
That's why we call somebody who's nihilistic
somebody who believes that there is
no meaning
and nothing matters.
That's the reason we call it that
in the popular vernacular.
So these are the kind of the
three choices
that we have to walk through.
For most of all of existence of humanity,
it's been door number one,
which is that there is essence.
And then we experience existence.
And the whole point of life
is to figure out and pursue essence
and responsible in a way that's generative
and meaningful.
And that's what we're trying to do.
That's what I think is most compelling.
I think that's the most compelling view.
I don't know the truth.
You know, and by the way,
when I've talked to Sam Harris about this,
he agrees with me that there's things
that we don't see,
that there is essence
that we can only barely perceive.
And all of the things that I
talk about
from Catholicism to the stochastic nature
of the statistical set of circumstances
in which we find ourselves,
from the science to the religion
is my understanding,
my best understanding,
my fumbling around in the dark
and looking at shadows on the cave wall
for what I'm trying to do
to find the essence
that will give meaning to my existence.
That's the point of my life.
It's very interesting.
So it goes back to
what are we grappling with here?
So I'm going to define my version
of what I think the God-shaped
hole is.
Yeah.
And I'm going to put it in
the context
of the language we've been using here.
Because I come at everything
from an evolutionary lens.
Right.
And I'm very much of-
It's a good lens, by the way.
Thank you.
It really helps you understand a lot.
It has been very helpful.
Evolutionary psychology is just the best.
It's bizarrely controversial,
which I will never understand.
But nonetheless,
it has been extremely useful in my life.
So I come at it from that.
So I'm like, okay,
if we do have this hole
and it is a yearning
and that yearning is evidence
that there is something,
what is the nature of the yearning
and what is the thing that I'm
yearning for?
And again, using the language
of this conversation,
I have a feeling
that humans have
a very intrinsic,
evolutionarily derived desire
to kneel before something.
And now the question becomes,
okay, if you have this push
to kneel before something,
why?
What is the evolutionary advantage
to those that kneel before the thing?
And the best answer
that I can come up with
is that you need to get out
of the me self
and you need to get into the
I self
and you need to create that distance.
And by kneeling before something,
by making something bigger than you,
now, one, you're just,
you are in the habit
of living your life in service
of something beyond yourself.
Right.
I don't think,
this is definitely just ignorance,
so you will help me here.
I don't think that any of the world's
lasting religions
would compel you to serve
anything other than,
ah, this will be interesting.
I actually don't know the answer to
this question.
I will be very shocked if you
tell me
that any lasting religion
has asked people to serve
anything other than either humanity itself
or a God that loves humanity.
Is there?
No doubt there are.
No doubt there are religions that,
but they're, I guess,
but you stipulated to lasting religions.
Yeah, because I don't see
how that would be beneficial.
Because ultimately what I'm saying
is the proxy,
the God-shaped hole
is actually a desire
to serve your fellow man,
because that's going to be the thing
that keeps you alive.
Because you're way better off
coming together as a group.
Evolutionary.
Yes, is my gut.
And then religion,
like the specific,
whether oral or written tradition,
is the thing that allowed humans
to come together in gigantic swaths
in a way that no other species,
no other creature,
not ants,
nothing can come together
in the flexible fashion that we can
by using ideas of religion.
Like those just give you an instant bond.
And I'm willing to kill for
and die for this thing
that we have in common.
Yeah, yeah.
I also have a huge amount of
time and admiration
for evolutionary psychology,
but it's totally descriptive.
And it's neither prescriptive
nor deterministic.
So I don't believe
that the evolutionary psychology
of the things that actually set out
our impulses and imperatives,
that they prescribe
nor proscribe particular behavior.
I think that we have choices
way beyond our evolution.
So let me get an example.
We talked about Mother Nature.
She has really two goals for you.
And all of evolutionary psychology
comes down to survival
and gene propagation.
That's what all of, you know,
the evolutionary psychologists
and evolutionary biologists,
they say that all that
any organism exists for
is to survive long enough
to pass on its genes.
And so it all comes down to that.
But virtually everybody believes
that we can short circuit that
and make decisions
that go beyond that.
We can do all.
And so people will say,
OK, well, you laid down
your life for a stranger,
but that was because you had
some evolutionary impulse
to behave in an altruistic way
that dates back to a time
when that would have been better
for your tribe, etc., etc., etc.
I think that the better explanation
for that is the animal path
versus the divine path.
The animal path is incredibly powerful.
It's a wonderful model
for understanding
why most things happen
and why we have the impulses
that we do.
But the most interesting questions
of the divine path
where we actually make decisions
that go beyond
what our evolutionary evolution
would suggest is the best path for us,
that go beyond the things
that we want to do,
that help us to understand
that there could actually
be something bigger.
And this is the really unique thing
about the human species
is that we can make this election
between divine and animal,
divine and animal.
And every day is this election
between divine and animal.
And in fact, to look
for the source of the complex oneness
in a world of complex ingenuity,
a complicated ingenuity,
that's to choose the divine path.
Ultimately, the divine path
or the animal path in the biggest way.
So not everybody agrees with me.
A lot of really smart people
disagree with me and say
all the things that we actually do,
they still come back to evolution,
even if they don't look like
this is an evolutionarily
adaptive thing to do.
It sort of is.
You just need a more complicated
understanding of the evolutionary impulse.
I disagree.
I think that there's,
man, evolutionary biology,
it just puts us on this track
and makes us act in particular ways.
Yeah, we got all these habits
and things that we want to do.
And then we can decide not to
do them
because we want something higher,
because we're called to something higher,
because we have a dim perception
of something that's bigger,
that's something that's better
that we're drawn toward.
And that's the oneness
that we're distracted from
when we're basically
just sitting on the animal path
and doing money, power, pleasure, fame,
money, power, pleasure, fame.
And so instead of getting on our knees
and contemplating the nature of enlightenment,
we'll scroll Instagram.
That's interesting.
So as somebody who believes
that you can't be enlightened
prior to death,
what is it about the contemplation
of that,
knowing you will never be able
to actually understand it?
What is it about the contemplation
that makes your life better, I presume?
Progress.
The progress principle.
You're getting closer.
And why not?
Why would God want it such
that you can't attain enlightenment?
Because, well, according to Christian theology,
I mean, so this becomes a theological question.
It's because ultimately it's the relationship,
the beatific vision is the relationship
with God, him or herself.
And the way that the Hindus talk
about this,
by the way,
is that the transmigration of the soul
occurs as people are getting closer
and closer to enlightenment,
at which point the soul will be reabsorbed
into the Godhead.
So the idea of the soul for Hindus
is that your soul,
Tom's soul, is a little chip of God.
Comes down, enters a human being,
corrupted by circumstance, et cetera,
becomes perfected over a hundred
or a thousand lifetimes,
and this is reabsorbed into the Godhead.
And the ultimate goal of to stop samsara,
the endless cycle of birth and rebirth,
is to be reabsorbed into God.
So their understanding of this
is actually easier to understand,
weirdly, than just,
I got to see God.
Awesome.
You know, I don't know.
But it's all basically saying the
same thing,
getting closer, getting closer,
making progress.
This is the goal in life.
This is the impulse.
And how do we do that?
All kinds of ways that our lives
are generative and help us do that.
You know, as silly as, you know,
doing a podcast, starting a business,
all these things, they help other people.
They help us understand ourselves.
They make life,
they lessen the burden
for our brothers and sisters
in particular ways.
This is the reason that
it's so profoundly unsatisfying for you
to do something,
it's all me, me, me, me, me,
as opposed to others, others, others.
And ultimately you get the juice
of these generative things,
of these creative things that you're doing
when it really does lighten the load
and improve the lives of other people,
because that's the process of getting closer,
the process of getting closer.
And the physical manifestations
of the things that we do every day,
and it gets better.
And we hope, and again,
this is one theory.
I mean, my whole religion,
I might be completely off base.
I mean, I can't say,
because I have no data.
I can only hypothesize at this point,
faith is belief without data,
is belief without evidence.
It's a set of non-testable hypotheses
is what it comes down to.
And it's just that the progress per se
is the point of what we're trying
to do on earth.
That's what the,
certainly the Dalai Lama would say.
From life to life, toward enlightenment.
That's what the Hindus would say
about the transmigration of the soul
for the reabsorption of the Godhead.
That's what Hindus,
or that's what Buddhists, sorry,
Muslims and Christians would say
about trying to actually go to live
in heaven with God.
But it's all saying the same thing fundamentally
about the progress.
The progress is the point of life.
Yeah, I don't know why at this
point in my life,
this has become such a fascinating question.
You're right on schedule, by the way.
No, no, seriously,
because what you throw off superstition
and you look for the pure oxygen
of enlightenment
and what looks like Jesus and Santa Claus,
what's the difference?
You know, when you're 20,
when you're 50, you're going,
ah, big difference.
Yeah, it's interesting.
There is something about the way
that the world is moving.
So my goal in life is to,
in a really practical way,
help people live a life of fulfillment.
And I never quite know how to
put words to it.
Fulfillment survives grief.
And so I'm trying to,
I have thought a lot about in
my own life
and have found tremendous easing of suffering
in recognizing what I call
that there is an evolutionary impulse
to get me to do the things
that will align myself with having kids
that survive long enough to have kids, right?
And so while I don't have to
do that literally,
I have to understand what the algorithms are
that are running in my mind to
make that happen.
And the more I explore this space
of like how one clicks into fulfillment,
I do find myself grappling with,
as you get under perception
and you really start to say,
okay, what is the bedrock here?
It does become, I'll say quasi-religious
because I don't find myself going,
oh, I'm getting closer and closer
to God.
That isn't what it feels like from
my perspective.
From my perspective,
it feels like there is ground truth
and you can get closer to it.
And the more you understand how the
illusion is created,
the less you are trapped by it.
And the less you are trapped by
the matrix
to use a very fun word,
evocative way of thinking about it.
It's one of the most profound movies
for the past 30 years,
notwithstanding the cinematography.
It has to do with the concepts
underneath it.
A hundred percent.
For me, it is the most useful metaphor
for the human existence.
And so once I understand how the
matrix works,
then I start seeing it in everything.
I start seeing it in politics,
which is not something I thought I
would ever engage with.
I start seeing it in the culture war,
another thing I never thought I would
engage with.
But as I, I forget what this
is a reference to.
This is an allusion to something.
As I set aside childish things,
I really come to realize that.
You just quoted St. Paul.
Is that what it is?
That's hilarious.
I can't even tell you where from,
but that you begin to realize,
oh, this is one problem.
And once you understand it's one problem
that manifests in all these weird ways,
helping people get deeper on that ladder,
because helping people get deeper
on that ladder
becomes, is very meaningful to me.
It's obviously also self-serving
in that the deeper on the ladder
I go,
the more grounded I feel,
the more I feel resilient to the
slings and arrows of life,
the more I feel like facing death
isn't scary.
Just all the things, all the things.
But I am,
I don't know what to make of
the fact that
when I started all of this,
it was a lot easier to have conversations
about think like this, act like this,
and then finding people wouldn't do it.
And every time I tried to scratch
as to,
okay, where were all my own hangups,
that it has led to me circling
around this problem
of the God-shaped hole over and
over and over.
It's very fascinating.
Yeah, no, it is.
And this is, I mean, psychologists
and sociologists
have found that pattern that it tends
to occur,
particularly with people who live
in their heads,
people who are questioners,
that they start asking bigger and
deeper questions
and the answers that typically come
to them,
even with the greatest horsepower
that the world can provide,
doesn't give them the truth that they seek.
It just doesn't give you full flavor.
It doesn't give you,
you get lots of interesting solutions.
Like, yeah, I got a good morning routine.
It's really good.
I have to ice bath, workout, whatever happens.
It's just not good.
But it's not the thing that I'm seeking.
You keep finding answers to questions
that you weren't asking
and you're not finding the solutions
to the questions that you really were asking
that are inchoate.
You know, you don't even know quite
how to put words to these questions
because the complex is so hard to apprehend
that you don't even, you can't even,
you don't even know the questions,
let alone the answers.
But that's what you're grappling toward.
And that's, I believe that's what humans
are grappling toward.
That's what Aquinas was saying,
that we all want the thing,
but we'll like, all right, I'll take
the substitute.
All right, I'll take the substitute.
And people start to freak out about dying
if they've been taking the substitute,
the counterfeit, money, power, pleasure, fame
their whole life
because they're running out of time
and they haven't made any progress
because they've been, you know,
eating non-nutritious food and not getting,
and they're starving to death.
And it's just, they get,
people get into a panic in their life.
And they realize they get into this deep,
existential dread, this ennui
that comes from, you know,
the depression of the world
that comes because there aren't any answers.
And maybe Nietzsche was right
and they were just looking in the
wrong place.
So that's what I see.
I mean, I'm endlessly interested
and enthusiastic about the promise
of AI,
but I'm not kidding myself for a second
to think that it's gonna answer
the real questions that I have
and that real people have.
And the real things that people want.
It's funny because, you know,
the one thing that we really all want,
we don't have the technology for,
and we're not getting closer to it.
You know, the happiness
that everybody really wants,
it's not sold on the internet.
It's not provided by the government.
You know, we've got lunar landers
and TikTok videos and you name it.
We can invent anything.
The ingenuity is almost boundless,
but we're not getting closer
to the thing that we want
because the ingenuity is being deployed
toward complicated ends
as opposed to the answers to complex problems.
We're answering the wrong set of questions.
It's what it comes down to.
And that's why you can find people
who have everything in the world
and are still miserable.
They couldn't get it there.
They couldn't buy what they wanted
in that store.
It's the way that it works.
Interesting, the Dalai Lama
and I had a conversation about this
because he and I have worked together
in various projects for the last 11 years.
And we had this conversation about it.
He says, you know, he's musing.
That's one point.
When the Dalai Lama muses, you listen.
And it's like, it's funny
because, you know, you Westerners,
you know, you've done everything
to create economic value
and tremendous businesses
and incredible wealth.
And it's so wonderful
to give people all this opportunity
so they don't starve to death.
And, you know, the world is richer
and all that.
But you spent no time
actually trying to understand the nature
of what really matters the most.
He says, we're poorer.
Yeah, our societies are poorer in
the East,
but we spent all our time
and all our ingenuity
trying to get the source of pure truth.
Did they make any more progress than
we did?
I'm not sure.
But also it's interesting
because a lot of Buddhists
will look at Christianity
and they'll be like, yeah, yeah,
we used to believe that 4,000
years ago.
That's a rudimentary theological technology.
You're on the right road,
but you're way, way back
compared to where we were.
Yeah, we used to have a guy.
Yeah, we used to have a guy,
you know.
And the whole thing,
as opposed to,
these are different religions
trying to get at the same ideas
in different ways.
They think there's a natural progression
of enlightenment
that happens to people and societies.
And we're thousands of years behind
where they are,
despite the fact that we're hundreds
of years ahead,
economically.
We're thousands of years behind
in terms of spiritual enlightenment,
complex versus complicated.
Same idea.
I don't know if it's true.
That is the question.
All right, let's re-ground this for
a second.
This has gotten pretty heavy, man.
I've never had a conversation like
this before.
Yeah, this is-
In media, this is amazing.
Oh, thank you.
Assuming that the audience is still
with us,
let's re-ground this.
So in the book, you talk about
what it is exactly that people need
to come back together.
So you talk about the four pillars
to build the life you want.
Right.
What are those four pillars?
And if I can contextualize this,
why does modern technology seem to
move us
in the exact opposite direction?
Yeah, so what we want is love.
That's what we want.
And once again, the world gives us
complicated things.
We want complex things.
Love is complex.
How do you get love?
Love of the divine or love of truth,
love of your family, love with friendship.
The point of intersection between family
and friendship is romantic love.
So that crosses both those categories.
And love of everybody is instantiated
in the way you earn your daily bread,
which is work.
So the way that we needed the portfolio,
the pillars or the investment portfolio
for happiness that we all need
is to spend every day thinking
about the way that we're going to
make progress
in our faith or philosophy,
whether it's religious or not,
family life, friendship,
real friends, not deal friends.
And the modern world gives us lots
of deal friends,
but not very many real friends,
which are real friends,
deal friends are useful to us.
Real friends are useless.
And that's why we don't spend a
lot of time on them.
And then work that serves is what
it comes down to.
So those are the silos.
Those are the deposits.
Those are the accounts that we need
to put investment in every single day.
And if we don't, we're going to
be missing things.
We're not going to be as happy
as we could be.
And we're not going to be building
a stable and steady happiness
that will improve our lives
and help us make progress as we
go through life.
So those are the four things.
It's just a very practical matter.
I set people on,
I can actually set up a course
of action.
Most people watching us are very good
at working.
You know, nobody's watching impact theory
who's a total slacker.
It's like, yeah, I don't think
I'm going to sit around all day,
but I'm going to watch impact theory.
No, you want to be better at
what you do.
So everybody watching us has got,
his work is pretty on point.
And okay, and it's creating value
and it's cool stuff.
Generally speaking, it's going to
be cool stuff.
You've got a cool stuff audience, good.
But are you working on your philosophical life?
Are you reading the Stoics?
Are you walking in nature without devices?
Are you studying the work of Johann
Sebastian Bach?
Are you engaged in meditation practice?
Are you practicing the religion of
your youth?
You need to do something like that
every day.
I recommend at least 15 minutes
of wisdom reading every day.
Stuff you don't need to read,
but your soul needs it.
15 minutes a day.
And I have a whole, you know,
list of books that I recommend.
Toss out a couple.
Well, I'll toss out a couple,
depending on what tradition
you want to start in.
You know, somebody who is interested
in all Eastern and Western
and very questioning and open
to all different ideas.
I would recommend The Way of a Pilgrim,
which is written by an anonymous
Russian Orthodox monk in the 19th century.
Way of a Pilgrim?
The Way of a Pilgrim.
And what he is, he's just walking
around Russia,
having adventures,
saying one prayer over and over and
over again.
It's a meditative book.
You're reading it.
It's just like the more you read,
it turns into a page turner.
It's the most boring book ever.
It turns into a page turner.
Zen and the Art of Archery,
which actually explains Zen
through the activity of archery
through the eyes of a Westerner.
So that's a very good way
to begin to understand Zen thinking.
Zen is the most I-self thing ever
because it's nothing more
than an attitude of observation.
That's what Zen really is.
It's a stripped thing
compared to Tibetan Buddhism.
All the Buddhists are going to,
you know, put in the comment section
how crazy and wrong
and wrongheaded I am on that.
I would recommend
The Miracle of Mindfulness by Thich
Nhat Hanh,
which talks about what is mindfulness?
It's being alive right now
and how you can actually do that.
And there's countless numbers of these things.
And there's any number that we could,
if you want fiction
that falls into this category,
it's Dostoevsky's Brothers Karamazov.
That is the most spiritual
and intellectually,
psychologically rich book I've ever read.
Dostoevsky is philosophy, right?
So it's kind of like
people were reading Atlas Shrugged
because they wanted objectivist philosophy
in the form of a novel.
If you want the essence of the search
for the complex oneness
in the form of a novel,
Brothers Karamazov by Fyodor Dostoevsky,
it's great.
And so there's reading.
Second thing is family life.
Again, we talked about that before.
There's one reason to have schism
in your family,
and that's abuse.
Everything else requires work.
The big reason that people drift away
from their families
is because they're just lazy.
They're just lazy.
They're just like,
I ain't got to call mom.
When was the last time I saw mom?
Do the work.
But it takes two to tango.
Like if the person is just not investing,
like you're trying to engage with
your mom
and oh my God.
Yeah, I know.
But the point is that generally speaking,
it's an iterative process
where you don't and she doesn't
and you don't and she doesn't
and you don't and she doesn't.
It's got to get restarted.
And doing the work,
actually, even unilateral work,
even one-sided work
is incredibly enriching for your happiness.
Because the part about relationships
that's best
is the giving.
It's not the getting.
It's better if you're giving and getting.
I get it.
I mean, there's an equation.
It's a dynamic situation.
But even if you don't,
it's better to do it than not
to do it.
Friendship is critically important.
Real friends, not deal friends.
And that means the work that you
have to do
is not pecuniary.
I have people I work with who
are real friends,
but they started as real friends
and we just look for an excuse
to spend more time together
and that's how they became deal friends too.
But the whole point is,
you know, the people that you grew
up with,
often people they went to college with
if they went to college.
And, you know, I have a son
in the military
and his buddy's in the military.
They're his real friends.
I mean, they've literally saved his life.
And he can't lose touch with those people.
I guess that's the ultimate deal, right?
In saving your life.
And then last but not least,
making sure that your work serves others
and you earn your success.
And that you're working to make sure
if you're an entrepreneur or a CEO
like you or me,
that the people who work for you
can earn their success and serve others.
Because they deserve to earn their success
and serve others.
And that's in the hands of the boss
to a very large extent.
That's the portfolio.
And either you're doing those things
every day
or you're not.
Either you did your reading
and called mom and your best friend
or you didn't, right?
And every day that you don't,
you're just, you're weakening the pillars
of your happiness.
You're getting less competent
in the serious business of building
your life.
I think you may have even said
it in this episode,
but life is an entrepreneurial game.
It's a startup.
So when I think about those different pillars,
they're not necessarily,
like they don't seem like big, scary things.
So how do we approach those
from an entrepreneurial standpoint?
Like how do we make these more
than just,
oh, I checked in with my friend.
I touched base with mom.
I read a passage in the Bible.
Like how do we go beyond going
through the motions
and really do something meaningful?
Yeah, well, to be more entrepreneurial
about it,
you have to actually induce risk.
You have to inject risk into the proposition.
So one of the things about willingness
and ability to take risk for outsized return,
you can tell I've written a textbook
on entrepreneurship and it's like,
this is what they all have in common
is this willingness and ability to
take risk
in exchange for outsized returns.
Now, usually for entrepreneurs,
the way they'll denominate it
is green pieces of paper.
But the truth is for the startup
of your life,
it's usually the denomination is love.
Is you're willing to take risk for love.
You said either in the book or
the interview,
I wouldn't invest in an entrepreneur
that was afraid to fall in love.
That's exactly right.
So that's one of the greatest examples
for a lot of people who are
watching us.
Disproportionately, people who are
watching us
are gonna be people in their 20s,
a lot of guys in their 20s,
the audience.
Unless I dreadfully misperceived the audience.
No, no, you're close, yeah.
And I know a lot of guys,
my students,
my graduate students at Harvard
who are willing to put $10 million
of other people's capital at risk
or even their own if they've got it.
They're willing to take a big scary job,
but they're not willing to ask a
girl out on a date.
Like what?
And the answer is to that conundrum,
to that mystery, that riddle
is that they're not entrepreneurial
in the part of the life that
matters the most,
which is their heart.
You know, this is like,
if you're willing to put money at risk,
but not love at risk and self
-esteem at risk,
you're not an entrepreneur
and you're not gonna have an exciting life.
You're just not.
And here's the interesting thing.
I had this, I was talking to
this guy.
Here's how it worked.
I was giving a talk and I
gave the analogy
of entrepreneurship in the business
of romantic love.
And I said, I gave him a,
it was a group of, a big
group of 20 somethings
in Washington, DC.
And I remember the day distinctly.
And I said, here's your assignment.
You got two weeks to tell somebody
you love that person
who doesn't know it.
And if it's not scary,
it's not the right person.
And maybe, by the way, maybe it's
your dad.
Maybe it's your dad.
Unfortunately, I love my dad to death.
Yeah, I know.
It sounds easy.
Yeah, yeah.
But for a lot of people,
they have relationships with their families.
Like, I've never told you this, but
I love you.
And that's like scary and weird and
awkward and et cetera.
So it doesn't have to be a
romantic love.
But the whole point is,
if it's not scary, it's not entrepreneurial enough.
Okay.
So this kid, kid in his twenties,
finds me on an airplane a couple
of weeks later.
He says, I was at that speech
in Washington, DC
and I can't get it out of
my head.
And I'm like, yeah.
He says, so I'm literally on my
way right now to Philadelphia
to confess my love to a woman
I've been secretly in love with
for two weeks.
Wow.
For two months.
No, two years, two years.
I've been in love with this woman.
I've never told her because I'm too afraid.
And I'm going there right now because
of your speech.
And I'm like, it's only a speech, man.
Bro, be careful.
I don't want to ruin his life.
And I said-
Did you get a follow-up on this?
I did.
Okay.
Because now I'm already engaged.
I did, I know.
But not immediately.
I gave him my email and I
said a prayer for him and the girl.
And I said-
And the girl.
And yeah, I said, let me know.
And then I didn't hear from him.
So I thought that was a bad sign.
I run into him at a holiday
party a few months later.
And I say, remember me?
He's like, yep.
And I said, how did it go?
And she said, she shot me down.
And she introduced me to the man
she was in love with.
And it was awful.
It was awful.
I said, I was very contrite.
I said, I'm sorry.
I didn't mean to mess you up,
you know, the whole thing.
He says, no, you understand.
I've been meaning to email you to
thank you.
I said, why?
He said, because that was the thing
I was most afraid of in my life.
And it happened.
And I didn't die.
And I'm never going to be afraid again.
Wow.
How did you get-
He's also not going to waste time
on her.
How, I mean, you're a very successful entrepreneur.
Not on your first venture.
You know, I don't, you need it.
It's like the, there's work out of
Northwestern, Kellogg, the, you know,
the management school in Northwestern.
It's a, you know, Lester University.
And they, the work shows that the
average entrepreneur has about four failures
before their first success.
And they learn from each one of
these failures.
And that's the basis of the success.
You need to have at least four
substantial heartbreaking rejections.
I mean, on average, if that, if
startup data or any indication of
the startup of life,
and that's an entrepreneurial life,
man, put your heart on the line,
get it stomped on,
get rejected.
You need it.
You need to learn.
It's what it comes down to.
And by the way, life is more
exciting when it actually does work out.
If you took a risk?
If you took a risk and you've
failed in the past.
You know, it's like, it's not that good.
If you didn't take a risk and
got rich and you never tried anything
hard before that,
that didn't work.
You know, part of the process is
the adventure.
And part of the adventure is the pain.
That's life.
And we need to understand that and
love, which is the way, way, way
more important than business.
That's well said.
Yeah.
I think a lot of people these days.
So going back to the framing of
the question where you've got modern
technology is pulling
us away.
You've got the celebration of business.
You've got money, money, money as
a metric of success.
And the thing I try to convince
everybody is, look, somebody that's
had the kind of
success that most people only dream of.
Nothing has come close to giving me
as much joy, fulfillment, anything,
protection from
the downside, all of it, other than
my marriage.
My marriage is the thing that I
protect most fiercely.
I am not worried about losing my money.
I'm not worried about losing accolades.
I am terrified of losing my wife.
Yeah.
And the market can have a horrible
day and you don't like it, but
your wife is really
mad at you and you're bummed.
Yeah.
Even if you know she's not going
to divorce you, you're bummed because
you don't want
the person you love the most to
be upset with you.
You want her to be happy with you.
Because what's happened, it's basically
like your stock market radically tanking.
The stock market of what really matters
in your life is the way that
that works out.
It's actually a really interesting
way to think about it.
Okay.
So if that is the thing, if
that's the thing that's going to really,
the thing that we're
pursuing is love in a bunch of
different guises, but the relationship
that's going
to be most important to us is
the relationship with our spouse.
How do we do that?
Well, and let's start at the beginning.
So one thing you've said is delete
your dating apps.
Yeah.
Or there are some people who wind
up meeting their partner and getting
married based on
dating apps, but dating apps, the
evidence suggests that it's making
dating harder.
It's actually true because it's making
it harder to find somebody with you,
with whom
you can have the complex connection.
That's appropriate for a couple of
different reasons.
Number one is the paradox of choice.
So dating apps give you too much choice.
And so what that means is that
there's always something better.
So are you saying settle?
Yeah.
Well, part of the reason is because
you're not going to find the perfect person.
You're going to make the perfect relationship.
Oof.
That's the way relationships really work.
You know, people think I'm going to
find, I mean, magical thinking is
a huge problem.
Love at first sight doesn't exist
and soulmates don't exist.
Facts.
Right?
I mean, I believe that God wants
me to be with my wife, but
that's an entirely different
thing than saying that there was this,
there was one woman in the world
and she lived
in Barcelona and she was a little
girl and I was growing up in
Seattle and the whole,
no, no, no.
Circumstances were such that I met
the person that was going, one of
the people that could
have been perfect for me if I
worked to make it perfect.
And your wife is cool with that framing?
Yeah, because she knows that that's
what God wants us to do.
You know, we believe that this is
God puts people together and then
puts a lot in our hands.
We have free will and we have
to, you know, a part of making
cosmic love-based progress
is the things that we do in
our relationship.
This is the way that we work
out the stuff of love in life
is not, it's all perfect.
Then you're in heaven automatically.
Well, boring.
That's boring.
No, no, no.
Progress, man.
And you got to make progress.
One of the ways you make progress
is the imperfect that you make as
perfect as you can using
your imperfect tools.
And that's the exciting adventure
that is a romantic relationship.
And if you start off with the
idea that there's always something
better because of magical
thinking, and I'm going to find the
perfect one if I keep swiping right
or left or whatever
it is.
What is it, left or right?
I don't know.
I've never used them.
That's right.
Because you and I have been married
men for a long time.
I'm 21.
You're how many years?
32.
Man, it's impressive.
32, yeah.
Congratulations.
I am in awe of that.
My wife's like, it's like 10 minutes underwater.
That's good.
It's like being married to an old
time comedian from the Catskills.
It's nice.
Except she's Spanish.
Spanish Jackie Mason.
It's a good reference that no one
in the audience got, but that's okay.
Google him.
Anyway, so he's probably on YouTube.
Yeah.
Black and white.
Maybe.
Yeah.
Yes.
Jesus.
So that's number one.
The second reason, however, is that,
and again, I'm not down on dating apps.
I'm just not, I'm not down.
I'm not down with how people use
them typically.
Interesting.
People use them for-
This feels like you're caveating.
I am caveating for sure, because there's
nothing that's good or bad, but that-
Thinking makes it so.
Exactly right.
And so the big thinking error in
apps is finding somebody who's completely
compatible with us.
The technology enables compatibility.
The technology is-
Enables you to find compatibility?
To find people who are more and
more and more compatible that you
couldn't on the human market.
And so that matchmakers your parents
wouldn't find for you or certainly
blind dates or somebody
you meet in a bar, you just,
you know, it's a crapshoot for compatibility,
which is actually
what you need.
We're too compatible.
This is something that most people
don't understand.
That sounds crazy.
Yeah, I know.
And so, but people will sort on
their political views and their likes
and their dislikes and,
physical characteristics.
What you find is that people that
match up on compatibility,
ex ante, a priori in the dating
market, they even look alike, right?
And that's a problem.
You know, it's basically you wind
up looking for somebody who's effectively
your sibling,
which is my adult kids say is
not hot.
That's not hot.
Not hot.
And so when people are looking for
excess compatibility, they like the
person less,
they find them less attractive.
What you need is a base of
compatibility, which is lower than
you think.
And then tons of complementarity,
which is interesting and sexy.
You want difference.
Yes.
Agreed.
Not opposites.
Opposites don't attract.
Where do you want, you're now confusing me.
Where do you want things to be?
Where do you want to be compatible?
You need basics on non-negotiable values.
Preach.
Right.
Non-negotiable values.
Negotiable values doesn't matter.
People think that too many values
are non-negotiable that are actually negotiable.
Politics shouldn't be in there.
You should not sort on politics.
Now, 71% of political liberals say
they won't date a conservative.
41% of conservatives say they won't
date a liberal, which just shows that conservatives
have lower standards politically than liberals.
And maybe it's men versus women or
something like that.
I'm not going to look into the
data more.
But the whole point is that that's
a ridiculous barrier.
That's a ridiculous barrier.
That's basically like classifying
being a Democrat or Republican,
like being Jewish or Catholic or atheist.
It's interesting, man.
Like this is one area where I'm
with you in the abstract, but political
stuff's gotten so weird.
People are so devout about it that
that isn't interesting.
In the moment, I don't want to
be like, even I try not to
be dogmatic.
But even if I were, I'm not
being dogmatic.
If they're dogmatic, that's not interesting
to me.
Yeah, I get it.
And one of the best ways, actually,
is what I recommend to my students,
for example,
is that they don't talk at all
about politics for four dates.
To see if I really am into
you, it's not until we get into
that thing.
Exactly right.
So you don't actually, so the dogma
or something, and if you can start
to fall in love,
suddenly you're less dogmatic.
You're less dogmatic about politics.
And the person you're falling in love
with, when they say something that
you would have
previously thought was a non-starter,
was a deal breaker, it no longer is.
Are you and your wife politically aligned?
Kind of now, just because we've been
together for so long.
But you weren't in the beginning.
No, she was Spanish.
I mean, she was brought up in
a hard-red, atheist family.
It's like complete socialists.
They were on the losing side of
the Spanish Civil War, and they were
all atheists.
She hadn't been to church since her
first communion.
Interesting.
I quietly assumed that was the first
thing you guys bonded over was religion.
Oh, no way.
That was just like, that was a
10-year project for me.
Wow.
Totally.
10-year project for me.
But, you know, when I met her,
she's like, no, I don't believe in marriage.
That's an antiquated institution.
Doesn't make sense.
We'll see.
I mean, I moved to Barcelona to
try to convince her to marry me.
How long were you guys together before
you got married?
Well, I hoped that it would be
very short, but it took me two
years to close the deal.
Okay.
From meet to married?
No, from moving to marriage.
Okay.
How long from meet to marry?
Three.
So we were apart for a year
and I was, you know, right.
And she didn't speak any English.
I didn't speak any Spanish or Catalan.
And so I thought I'm gonna...
The only...
I had a premonition.
I mean, I met her for a week.
And I told my dad, I think
I'm gonna marry this girl.
Whoa.
He's like, can't wait to meet her.
Like, I got some problems.
She doesn't speak English.
She doesn't live in the United States
and she doesn't believe in marriage.
But I think it's surmountable.
Other than that.
Yeah.
And so, you know, we kind of
stayed in touch for a year.
And then I quit my job and
I moved to Barcelona.
I took a job in the Barcelona
Symphony because I had this very strong sense.
And by the way, maybe it didn't
work out.
It was an entrepreneurial thing to do.
And I was 24 and it was okay.
And I worked on it and worked
on it, learned the language.
And we were in love.
And when I was 26 and I
said, we have to get married.
You have to marry me.
She said, yes.
And, you know, and then little by
little by little, you come together.
See, the couples change, people change
over the course of their lives.
For sure.
And couples change together.
And the couples that don't do well
change apart because of the hubris.
Don't change together.
There's too much pride is what comes
from it.
So what will happen is tons of
difference at the very beginning.
Lots of love glues you together and
then you start to change together.
The ultimate goal, by the way, for
a marriage relationship that lasts,
tons of passion.
We talked about the neurochemical
cascade of falling in love, of love addiction.
But within five years, what you need
to be left with is what we
call companionate love.
Your goal within five years is to
be best friends with the person.
That's your goal.
There's lots of passion and companionate
love that also sounds not hot.
You know, here's my companion, Mrs. Brooks.
You know, no.
Companionate love is this is the person
that you'll be looking into her eyes
on your dying day.
And then who knows all your secrets
with whom you can be truly yourself,
who really has your best interests
at heart.
That's what companionate love is.
And not every relationship can get
to that.
But that's the goal.
What do you think though?
What's the importance of keeping sex alive?
Because that's a physical bond that
is the most intimate understanding
of your relationships.
It's an expression of your greatest intimacy.
It's also super fun.
Yeah.
A and B.
So I want to make sure that
people hear that.
You can have sex with people you're
not in love with.
You know, people do that all the
time too.
Carfax.
It's way, way, way more satisfying
when it's in the expression of your
greatest intimacy.
That's why the happiest people have
one sexual partner in a given year.
It doesn't mean one in your whole life.
It means one in a given year.
There's actually been a study on that?
There's a study on that using the
general social survey at the University
of Chicago.
Yep.
Is that, to me, that just sounds
like a proxy for committed relationship.
Yeah, it is.
And the greatest expression of the
deep, deep, deep intimacy and commitment
is usually sex.
Because when people ask Lisa and I,
like, what's the secret to a long marriage?
We always say, like, one of our
top things,
obviously communicate, but have a
lot of sex.
Like, you don't want to become roommates.
And there is something also, and I
don't know what you think about this,
but there's something about, there's
an electricity to crossing that line.
And there's one person that you cross
that line with.
And not having that, like, one for that,
just entire part of your life to
die and for you to never have
that thing.
Well, there's tons of oxytocin that
happens during sexual activity
that you don't get otherwise as well.
And that bonds you together again
and again.
Look, there are other ways to get
it too, by the way.
So sex is not the only way.
People often ask, is it bad that
couples fight?
And the answer is it's bad when
they don't.
And I mean, some people fight a lot.
Some people fight a little.
My wife and I fight a lot.
We fight a lot.
We have a lot of arguments.
Because she's Spanish?
Because yeah, I mean, for them, it's
just a form of communication, you know?
And there's nothing that's not on
the surface.
And so that was hard.
The first five or 10 years, I
was very aggrieved.
Because you're not built like that.
I'm American.
You know, we didn't do that growing
up in the Pacific Northwest, did we?
I mean, it was like...
Ah, yeah.
That was not...
Learning to fight well was a big
thing I had to learn.
But the key is about that couples
that never, never, never fight,
they're missing out on some of the
greatest source of intimacy.
Because the friction is there.
Yeah, you're saying things that you
think that you weren't saying before.
That's interesting.
I heard you say this before.
Take a second to say that very clearly.
The idea of...
Of intimacy through fighting.
Yeah.
People often say, it's so weird, you know,
after we have a big fight, then
we make love.
As if it were make up sex.
I've never once done that.
I never do that.
Are you in the mood for sex
after you've been in a fight?
Well, it depends on how the fight resolves.
But the point is that a lot
of people do that.
And the reason is because they're
raw and intimate in their communication.
Sometimes for the first time in a
long time.
Okay.
For the first time in a long time.
So if you're the kind of couple
that has,
you're not seeing each other very
much because you're working really hard
and you're on the road and you're
not talking about things
and a lot of tension is building up.
And then finally you have a knockdown
drag out fight.
And you're saying things that you
think that are deeply intimate,
that are your deepest feelings.
That you would never say at work
because you don't have the kind of
relationship with other people.
You don't want to demoralize them.
You don't have trust.
You have enough trust.
And you say things that might be,
they might be cutting.
They might be wounding, but they're
deeply intimate.
You have an intimate bond.
You have a spiritual bond with that
other person
because of the intimacy of the communication,
even though it was wounding.
That's really interesting.
So I will say this.
I have had moments where I was
completely uninterested in sex
until we had, I wouldn't even necessarily
say fight
because fight implies that it's like
really fiery.
There was one big disagreement that
my wife and I got into
and it was really interesting.
When I brought up the thing,
we happened to be in a swimming pool.
And so my wife likes me to
hold her
and walk her around the pool.
And it ended up being this amazing way
to have this argument because it was
really like,
hey, I've been meaning to say this
thing for a few days now.
Here's how this thing made me feel.
Like, let's really get into it.
And we couldn't see each other's eyes
and it made it way easier to
have the conversation.
So we were like cheek to cheek,
but we couldn't see each other's eyes.
So there, it just became easier
to like get those things off of
our chest.
It was really wonderful.
But I, and so I didn't want
to have sex
until we had that conversation,
but it wasn't like, oh, I'm going
to run you upstairs.
And like, I've never had that response.
Like I don't-
People are different for sure.
But it's important that you have those
relationship moments
and those might be as bonding.
Your fights might be as bonding for
you as-
When done well.
Are you-
Yeah, for sure.
And there's technique.
Yeah. Talk to me about, so-
My guess is that you're in a
21 year marriage
and you're going to be married until
you die.
Yes.
You're going to die.
I mean, until the death of you part.
For sure.
And so my guess is I could
probably write a script
for your fights based on that.
And when something's not right,
the accusation is that we are having
a problem.
Now, when you look at a couple
that's tenuous
and really having trouble and really
in danger,
it's like you're doing something
and it makes me feel a particular way.
So important.
Super important.
And just changing the language
because language change has very strong
cognitive impact.
So if you want your fights to
be-
You're going to fight
and it's important that you relate
to each other
and you're honest with each other.
But you want it to stop actually creating
so much brain damage.
Just change the pronouns.
That's the first thing to do
is to change the pronouns in the fights.
Don't say I and you.
Start saying we and us.
We and us.
We have to do this thing.
Whenever we do this thing, we have
a problem.
And you'll find you're stumbling across it
at the very beginning.
You'll find it because it's because-
And you did this-
We had this problem.
We had this breakdown in communication
because then you're trying to solve
a problem together
and it's a joint problem you're trying
to solve.
And when you solve it, you've made
progress together
as opposed to I won and you lost.
That's really-
Super important.
And just using different pronouns
it can actually repair a multitude
of problems.
And something my wife and I do,
and this has been really powerful
for us,
is we talk in insecurities when we
get into an argument.
So if one of us is getting angry,
it's like we have a shared understanding.
If you're angry, it's because your insecurity
has been tripped.
So confess.
Like what's the insecurity?
What's the thing that's bothering you?
So that you can get off of
the surface level argument,
which is usually very fruitless
and you can get down into-
It's something stupid.
It's like you finished the milk or
something stupid.
Right. And you finished the milk without
talking to me
and it makes me feel unseen, whatever.
And once you get down there, like,
ooh, whoa, why is that making you
feel unseen?
And also that the person isn't just,
I have an insecurity, you triggered
it, shame on you.
It's like, okay, I have an obligation
to work on my insecurities.
You have an obligation to care enough
about me
that you want to know,
but I can't just be like, you
have to deal with it.
I have an insecurity and you better
tread around it forever.
You're doing a lot right.
I can tell you that.
And this was one of the reasons
that you stayed so openly
that your marriage is the most important
thing in your life.
It's the central institution of your life.
I mean, like this goes all bust.
And by the way, this is going
to go bust.
It's all going to go bust.
Yeah.
Right?
But the one thing on your deathbed
is Lisa.
I mean, here's the problem.
One of you is going to die first.
Yes.
Although if you ask my wife, she
really wants us to die.
Simultaneously.
That would be like, she's like,
I don't care if I die in
a plane crash
as long as you're next to me.
And I'm like, what?
What are you talking about?
Why are we both going down?
Like, if I have to die in
a plane crash,
I want you to be safe on
the ground.
She's like, no way.
I'd want to be with you.
So yeah, that's my wife.
She says it out of love though.
So you actually laugh about it.
Yeah, I totally get where she's coming from.
I sure hope you die in a
plane crash with me.
Yeah, no, I get it.
But that's, you know, this is an
issue, right?
Because that you will be separated.
Yeah.
The data say that except under the
oddest of circumstances,
you'll be separated.
But what typically happens is really,
really happy couples,
except under conditions of bad luck,
they tend to live a long time,
have a long marriage.
And one of them dies and then
the other dies.
It's crazy, man.
Because you have a joint life.
You have a joint life together.
The enterprise.
It's the startup.
It's your co-founders.
The other thing that's really interesting too
is that a lot of the relationships
that do best
are startups, not mergers.
That's interesting.
Tell me more, meaning second marriage?
No, well, I mean, second marriages are,
sometimes they're really great,
but the marriages that have the greatest
likelihood of success,
they're entered into earlier
when you're both in life startup mode,
as opposed to I got my law degree
and you got your PhD and you
got your startup
and I got my startup and I
think we're,
and we have separate bank accounts
and now let's have a merger.
Startups are more successful than mergers.
There's data on that.
Oh yeah.
And the worst, of course,
are hostile takeovers or acquisitions,
but you know.
Wow.
Okay.
So you can have a merger that works,
but you got to go into it
with your eyes open
and make it as much of a
startup as you can make.
And that was, I don't recommend separate
bank accounts.
I don't recommend it.
Really?
Yeah.
There's huge data showing that couples
are more successful
when they have joint bank accounts.
Interesting.
Let me run something by you.
So when Lisa and I first got together,
um, we had enough difference in values
that it was,
I looked at the things that she
spent money on
and I thought they were dumb.
She looked at the things I spent
money on.
She thought they were dumb.
So what we did was we said,
bills are joint,
but spending is separate.
And so we put our money together
and then we each had the exact
same amount to spend.
Yeah.
And at the time, so when we
got married,
she certainly had more money than me
because I was just absolutely broken
in debt.
But then when we got married, I
was the only one with a job.
And the one insight,
and I wish I could track back
to where I got this,
but I was like this,
cause this is all pre-functional internet.
The internet existed, but nobody was
really using it for much.
And I said, okay, look, we're going
to come together,
but the, we're in this together.
So whatever money I earn, it really
is half yours.
Right.
And so we're going to take care
of all the bills together.
We'll have the separate spending accounts
and really have looked at everything
in that way.
Like when we started Impact Theory,
the lawyers were like, who's going
to own 51%.
And I was like, what are you
talking about?
And they said, you can't be 50-50.
That's the ultimate divorce nightmare.
And so my wife was like,
you're obviously going to work more
than me.
Like you take the 51%.
She's like, I don't have any problem
with that whatsoever.
And I was like, over my dead body,
I was like, I need you to
know to the core of your existence,
this company, whatever.
If something goes wrong with us, I
have a problem.
If we're in a position where I'm like,
thank God I have 51%.
I've already lost everything.
So 50-50.
Well, all you're saying is Impact Theory
is an extension of Tom.
And so therefore my life is 50
-50 with you.
So axiomatically Impact Theory is
50-50.
Nice.
And really what I wanted to say was
Impact Theory is an extension of Tom
and Lisa.
Like this is a thing we are
doing together.
And even if we weren't,
I mean, I suppose at that point
I wouldn't have thought about it.
But like if my wife betrayed me,
I'd still give her half my shit.
I'd just be like, you earned it.
Yeah, because you love her.
Yeah, yeah.
Not only that, I don't know who
I would have become
had I not been a startup with her.
You're not pre-nuppy at all.
And all you were doing is avoiding fights
by having separate allowances.
Yes.
It's not the same thing.
I mean, that's just prudent is the
way that it works out.
It's like, yeah, we're going to tend
to fight over this.
And we don't want me to accidentally
take all the spending on giant chess pieces
or Batman statues or something.
Video games.
Video games, whatever the thing happens
to be.
And so let's make it so we
just avoid a fight.
Let's just simply avoid a fight.
And that way I can laugh at
the way you spend your money.
You can laugh at the way I
spend my money
instead of feeling a source of resentment.
But basically saying, my money, your money.
My account, your account.
My property, your property.
That's problematic from the very beginning.
Because what you're basically is you're
planning for
is the dissolution.
You're planning for the, I mean, it's
a union.
And the union of this is to
say that we're,
I mean, biblically it's a man shall
leave his parents
and cleave to his wife.
It's one flesh.
I mean, the whole, in religious traditions,
divorce is supposed to be like cutting
off your arm.
It's supposed to be that kind of,
I mean, I get it.
It happens sometimes.
I get it.
You know, I live in the real world.
It happens sometimes.
But when you're doing it from a startup,
you don't really understand yourself
without Lisa.
It's like, who's Tom?
I don't know.
Alone?
Yeah, that's the thing.
Now, not everybody can have that.
You know, and I'm not saying people shouldn't,
not everybody can be held to these standards
because of the reality of things that
have happened
in their lives.
And, you know, I talk to people
who've been the victims
of abuse and addiction and criminal behavior
and all of this.
And they have a need for love
in their life
and they get married again
and they have an established life.
And it doesn't have these perfect standards.
Social science gives you the ideal circumstances,
but not the only circumstances.
And so here's the key.
When the circumstances are not ideal,
you have to work consciously with
your eyes open
to make them as ideal as you can.
So if you've got a merger on
your hands,
got a merger on your hands, good.
You can make that work too,
but make it as startupy as you can.
Yeah, the thing I would encourage people
is to understand that the reason a
startup works
is for a set of principles.
If you understand the principles
and can apply them later in life,
so be it.
One of them is going to be
being open
to being changed by the relationship,
going into it and knowing we are
creating a union.
And in doing that, like what are
the ways
that we have to move and to
dance in this thing
in order to make it work?
And then a big part of it,
especially if you're older
is understanding that selection is
80% of the battle.
Like if you select poorly,
you're going to be in dire circumstances.
There are.
I mean, again, without magical thinking,
without thinking there is one soulmate.
So choose wisely.
I don't believe in soulmates.
I don't believe in love at first sight.
I'm just saying that if, for instance,
you said earlier, you have to grow
together as a couple.
Now the amount of all the things
that we talked about here, emotional stability,
getting that right, knowing how to
fight well.
Like, I mean, there's just a laundry list
of happiness things that if you get right,
you will be way prime for a marriage.
Knowledge is power in your relationships,
in your work, in your spiritual life.
Knowledge is power.
And again, it all goes back to,
I know people who say, yeah, we
knew each other for a week
and we got married in Vegas.
It's like, that's folly.
That's just serendipity.
That just doesn't make sense.
On the other hand, when somebody says,
I say,
how long have you been dating that girl?
It's like eight years.
It's like, no, no, no.
And what's the right amount of time?
This is a question of prudential judgment too.
My oldest son met his wife, now wife,
when he was 24, early 24.
They dated for six months.
They were engaged for six months.
They got married a year after they
started dating.
Their first child was born nine months later.
I mean, that's called the 6-6
-9 cadence
in Catholic life, by the way.
Six, really?
That's a thing?
That's a thing.
Six months dating, six months engaged,
nine months till the first baby.
I mean, it's not that we recommend this.
But it worked out really, really well
because that was enough time, but
it wasn't too much.
You know, it wasn't the kind of
thing where, I don't know,
why don't we live together for, you know,
50 years before we decide whether
or not to get married.
That's not the right thing either.
So, you know, prudential judgment is,
and it's the same thing with a
startup, by the way.
I don't know, I think I need
a little bit more experience.
So when I was writing my dissertation,
I would see these guys and, you know,
I was doing my PhD with like,
I got to read a couple more books.
Write your dissertation, pop the question
after a certain point, but not on
the first date.
Yeah, I didn't have any trouble with that.
So for me, when I met Lisa,
I did not think I was going
to get married.
And then I was 24.
And when we started dating,
probably about three months in something,
three, four months in something like that,
I realized, oh shit, like I'm in
love with her.
And then I was like, okay, well,
I'm either never getting married
or I'm marrying this woman.
And so I proposed at eight months
and we had spent some of those
eight months apart.
So it wasn't even like we were
living together
for eight months or anything
because she was in England.
And then I was ready to get
married right away.
I was like, what's it take to
get married
about three months?
And she's like, you are having a laugh.
She's like, no way, this is going
to take
like a year to plan this wedding.
So we ended up being together for
about 18 months,
by the time we got married.
But it was-
Good and fast, that's good.
By today's standards, that's fast.
And by today's standards, you were young.
Yeah.
And again, society changes in different ways,
but some of these principles don't change.
I don't know if any of the
principles change.
That's the thing, like-
Circumstances do, but principles don't.
Yeah.
So how do people grow together?
Like what is the key there?
Part of it is understanding that you
are stronger
when you are together.
And that one of the cues for
you to change
is the other person changing.
So not, people who struggle,
they think the cue for me to
do something different
in my life is I feel differently
about something.
One of the cues for you to
do something differently
in your life is that your spouse
starts to think,
feel differently about that.
You have to take on the characteristics
of the other person as if they
were inside you.
You know, so you find, for example,
that your spouse is on a spiritual journey,
starts to find stirrings of spirituality.
That's a cue for you to do
that too.
And to do that sincerely as well.
And again, people say, well, you're losing
your individuality and the whole thing.
Yep, that's exactly right.
Yep.
Yeah, you're sublimating the individuality
on these things to have greater strength
in the union, right?
So that you can have a greater multiplicity
of experiences across the two of you.
Greater adventure and excitement across
the two of you
is a way that that works.
And sometimes it's hard for people
because they feel that they're the
senior partner
in the relationship.
That's not the secret to a successful marriage.
Now, there are social scientists
that have very heterodox views on this.
There's a guy named Eli Finkel at Northwestern,
a psychologist who's written about marriage.
And he says that one of the reasons
that marriage is so hard today
is because we expect too much from it.
He says, you know, we expect your
best friend
and your one and only lover
and your business partner
and the person who helps you raise
your kids.
The only person who knows your secrets.
And it's like, it's too much pressure
for one relationship
that was distributed across 10 people
until about the 19th century or the
20th century.
But in the time of the romantic era,
where when romance took on its modern connotations,
which is it's everything, it's magic.
It's, you know, it simulates the relationship
with God.
Even some of the language
that we've used in this conversation,
that then it took on too much pressure.
And he recommends in his book about this,
that and in his work and his
very interesting research,
that you ease off on the throttle
a little bit.
That you don't expect your wife
to be your best friend necessarily.
He even suggests that some couples
do better
when they're not the only exclusive
sexual partner.
I disagree with that.
I don't think the data support that.
I mean, again, as they say in finance,
your results may differ.
But they certainly don't in my case
or yours.
Yeah, that one I can't imagine.
Having unshared sexual experience.
The only thing that I can imagine
is if, yay,
if you're like sharing something by
all means.
But when people go off, I just
don't see how that works.
And I certainly don't see how it works
if you invite another person into
the stable pair bond.
Like, whoa.
I know.
And there's actually, you as an evolution guy,
you'll really, really like this literature
that talks about why it screws up relationships.
So there's a guy at University of Texas
that does work on jealousy,
on the evolutionary basis of jealousy.
And he had this hypothesis
that men are more jealous of sexual infidelity.
And women are more jealous of emotional infidelity.
And so what he does is he
finds that women in relationships,
they will forgive their husbands for
sexual discretions,
but not for falling in love with
another woman.
And a man, if your wife says,
I mean, yeah, I had an affair,
all that.
But it was only because I felt
like I was falling in love.
The sex was terrible.
You'd be like, I forgive you.
Yeah, yeah.
I forgive you.
It's so asymmetrically weird.
And the reason for this from an
evolutionary basis
is that males have to be really vigilant
about making sure they're not inadvertently
raising the offspring of another male.
Yeah.
And women have to be very vigilant
to make sure
that the provider and defender of
the family
doesn't stray and take and defend
and provide for another family
and another female's offspring.
And so that's why the jealousy
is gonna work in that particular way.
But no matter what, I'm telling you,
if you have an open marriage,
somebody's gonna fall in love, you know?
And there's all kinds of stuff that
can go wrong on that.
So that's not, I mean, again,
it's like different social scientists
disagree on that.
But I think my reading of the data
and my prudential judgment,
not just my Catholicism suggests
that that's not a wise course of
action for most.
I'm a big believer.
I think you're right about that.
I'm a big believer in what I
call frame of reference.
So your frame of reference
or your set of beliefs and your values.
Right.
There's other things at the fringes,
but that's the core of it.
And it will make all the difference.
It's not what happens,
it's how you perceive what happens,
just going back to Viktor Frankl.
So to that point,
you said guys have to be really
hyper protective
that they're not raising somebody
else's kid,
but you adopted a kid.
Right.
And so that to me speaks to
frame of reference.
And I've heard you say that you
have every bit of love
for your adopted daughter
that you have for your biological kids,
which I have no reason to believe
is not true.
So what did you do to your
frame of reference
in order to be able to welcome her?
And even though we would both agree
that from an evolutionary standpoint,
that doesn't make sense.
Yeah.
It will.
From an evolutionary standpoint,
it actually might make sense
from an evolutionary standpoint,
because if there's an orphan,
even in nature will be adopted
by non-human mammals,
will adopt orphans.
As their own.
And sometimes it will be even a mistake.
So you see the cuckoo bird
will actually lay its eggs
in the nest of other birds.
And then the egg,
knock the eggs out of the nest
of the other of the birds
that have the nest.
And then the cuckoo will hatch
and be taken care of by the
surrogate mother.
That's where the name cuckold comes from.
Yeah, exactly right.
And then of course,
the cuckoo is twice the size,
the regular bird.
So it's hilarious because,
you know,
the baby bird is the funniest thing.
So there is some evolutionary basis
for that
in the case of not raising
somebody else's offspring per se,
but raising an orphan
and bringing the child into your own family.
And one of the things that you find
is that my experience,
but also the research shows
that the oxytocin release
for an adopted child
is just as high as it is
for a biological child.
So you basically know
that this is my child.
You lay eyes on that child
and it's 4th of July all over.
There's Roman candles in your head.
And it is forever.
And so it's funny
because you don't actually know
till you do it.
It's all a theory.
Oh yeah, no, you know,
the bond with the adopted child
will be just as much
as with the biological child.
It's weird because intellectually,
it's a stronger bond in some ways
because it's this election,
it's this human will
on top of the neurophysiology
of human connection on top of it.
It's really something.
I have to say it's funny.
It's funny, but it's just deep, deep,
deep, deep love.
And for both kinds of kids.
It's really interesting.
Speaking of kids,
how does a good Catholic
end up with a son
who becomes a sniper?
Yeah, there've been a lot of good,
good service members in the Marine Corps,
but my son, Carlos, it's interesting.
So I used to,
my approach with my kids
has been given that life is a startup,
they need a business plan.
And I need a business plan from them
because I'm VC, right?
And I deserve a good business plan.
And so I had my kids write
business plans in high school.
And when they were not original
or no good, I'd send it back
for revisions.
And Carlos's business plan
had like six rounds of revisions.
The first one was very unoriginal.
He was not a motivated student
in high school.
It was always like,
you know, he's getting a C in history.
He's getting a D in Latin.
And he's clear.
He was not cut out for college.
And when it came time,
he got a big athletic scholarship.
He's a great, big, healthy, strapping,
coordinated athletic boy.
But I said, in this business plan,
you need something more original than that.
I'm an academic,
so this isn't breaking my heart.
But, you know,
so finally he comes back and he says,
part of it is because your business plan
as a kid has to answer two questions,
by the way, as an adult too.
The meaning requires that you have
answers to two questions.
This is the diagnostic test.
Why are you alive?
And for what are you willing to
die today?
If you don't have answers to those questions,
you have a meaning crisis.
I don't know what your answers are,
but you have to have real answers,
not BS answers, not nonsense answers.
How old were they when you started
asking this question?
High school.
So like junior year in high school.
And he didn't have answers.
So where are you going to go
find the answers?
And he had a very good answer
to the question of how to find
the answers,
which was, I want to go work hard
with my hands outdoors.
Why do you think that was a
good answer?
Because I believe that that was the
case for him.
He's a very kinetic boy.
You know, he was a kid who,
he had a strong,
an affinity for the outdoors,
fishing, hunting,
which is not in our family.
You know, I didn't grow up.
I used to go fishing every year
in Lincoln City
on the Oregon coast when I was
a kid.
And, you know, that kind of thing.
Outdoorsman.
My dad was a professor, right?
And so, but he was really into it.
He's good at that whole thing.
So he took a job as a
dry land wheat farmer
up in Idaho in Grangeville
and worked two harvests, made a bunch
of money.
He was alone all the time with
his thoughts.
He was digging rocks out of the soil
and mending fences and driving.
Was he making it spiritual for himself
or did just the nature of it?
He was going to church.
I mean, he was always kind of
half-heartedly,
you know, but it wasn't spiritual
so much
as he was looking for these answers
to meaning.
You know, why am I alive?
What does it mean for me to
be alive?
For what would I be willing to die?
And at the end of that,
this was kind of vaguely part of
the business plan,
but it became clear as time went on.
He said, I want to join the Marines.
I want to see what I'm made of.
And so he did and it was hard.
You know, bootcamp was hard.
He broke his foot a couple of times.
A couple of times?
Twice.
Jesus.
Yeah.
And then he went into the infantry
training battalion
because he was a war fighter,
which is 15% of the Marine
Corps are combat Marines.
What does that mean?
I thought they were all war fighters.
Yeah, but 85% are in support roles.
15% of the war fighters,
the door kickers and the riflemen.
Wow, I didn't realize it was that lopsided.
Yes, he was in the infantry.
Yeah, for sure.
I mean, there's logistics and mechanics.
And I mean, there's so many jobs
to support the 15%.
And then from there, he became a mortarman.
And from there, he went into the
elite sniper corps,
which is a really, really hard-
Were you freaked out during any of this?
Kind of, except that,
what do you want as a dad?
You want a kid who has the
answers to these questions.
Because this is what it means to
be fully alive.
This is a saint in the fourth
century named Saint Irenaeus.
And he's most famous for saying,
the glory of God is a man
fully alive.
Like, don't give me half dead.
Don't give me half dead.
And half dead is I don't know
why I'm alive
and I don't know what for what
I'm willing to die.
I want my kids, I want the
people in my life
and my friends to be able to
have answers
to these particular questions.
So, I was scared, but I was energized
by his particular energy.
And it's so interesting because the
sniper corps,
the Scout Sniper Platoon,
which is a branch of the special forces,
they sit three hours behind the scope
of a rifle,
just sitting there.
And this is a kid who couldn't
concentrate in school.
I mean, he's like ADHD, whatever that is.
It's a funny diagnosis.
Their motto is suffer patiently, patiently suffer.
Ha, that's my son.
I'm super proud of him.
I'm scared, but I'm super proud of him.
Is he active duty?
Yeah, he's active duty down at Camp
Pendleton right now.
Yeah, for sure.
For sure.
He's 23 years old, he's married.
Wow.
He's, he, cause when he, when he
got that,
you know, when he got that,
then things became clear when he answered.
Cause you know, why are you alive?
Did you already say what he said?
Cause if he did, sorry, I missed it.
No, I didn't.
His answers are, I am alive cause
God made me.
For what am I willing to die today?
For my faith, for my family, for
my friends,
and for the United States of America.
And for our allies, for those of
you listening or, you know,
that he'd die for you too.
And those aren't everybody's answers.
Those might not be your answers,
but man, those are solid answers.
And when you have the answers, life proceeds.
Life proceeds, life becomes linear.
Life becomes clear.
That's why meaning is so critically important.
And boy, my son taught me a lot.
He's like, I got the theories.
I got the data.
But seeing it play out, it's thrilling.
So, you know, the phone rings at
2 a.m.
Don't like it.
Not looking forward to that.
When he's like, yeah, going on a
field trip.
Not great, not great, but I'll take it.
I'll take it all day.
Every time I get to spend time
with you,
I love it the most.
It's amazing.
Where can people follow you?
Where can they get the new book?
Thank you.
Arthurbrooks.com.
It has a sort of, it collects
all the stuff that I do.
My column on the science of happiness
is published.
It's called How to Build a Life
at the Atlantic,
every Thursday morning in the Atlantic,
theatlantic.com.
And my new book with Oprah Winfrey,
Build the Life You Want,
The Art and Science of Getting Happier,
September 12th from Penguin Random House.
I wrote it because I want people
to understand these ideas,
to change their habits and share these
ideas with others.
Thank you for having this conversation
with me.
Thank you for what you're doing.
Thank you for your heart.
Ah, thank you.
The book's amazing, everybody.
I highly encourage you to pick it up.
And speaking of things I highly encourage
you to do,
if you haven't already, be sure to subscribe.
And until next time, my friends,
be legendary.
Take care.
Peace.
To learn more about artificial intelligence,
check out this episode with Mo Ghaddad.