This is one I could probably do in my sleep because I've been doing it for so long,
but, and I probably take it for granted, but I see so many people struggling with this
that I just feel like I have to take a shot at trying to help people out here.
Let's talk about Linux permissions.
I know this is a tough one to get through, and this is going to be my attempt at making it easy for you.
Now, if you've used Linux before and you've tried doing the listing on files and directories,
you may have seen permissions notated like this through the ls command, and you're like,
oh, what does that stuff mean?
Well, I'm going to break this down because this is basically a table of access represented as characters,
and it's really ingenious because this one line, these few characters,
actually carries a lot of significance and can tell you everything you need to know about who can do what.
This is a number, but what most people may not quite get or doesn't quite make sense is this is a number in octal.
It's a representation of a numeric format.
This is a number.
It's just an octal rather than in the decimal format that we understand,
which means numbers that are permitted here only are from zero to seven.
Eight would actually make that an illegal permission.
We're going to skip that first character for now.
The first three characters after the first character, these first three right now, they represent the user permissions.
The next three characters represents the group permissions,
and the last three characters represents any other permissions.
If you're not this user, if you're not this group, you're other.
Now, the reason why I skipped that first character is because it requires special explanation.
This first character represents any special properties that may be attributed by what is listed here in the directory listing.
That first character could be mean or signified that it is a directory that it has a set UID bit or it may have a sticky bit set.
But we're just going to limit the scope here and say this is for any kind of special meaning.
So to give you a quick recap here, this notation can be broken down into these pieces here,
where the first character represents any kind of special significance around whatever this file is or directory.
The first three characters after that represent the user permissions.
The next three represent the group permissions, and the final three represent other permissions.
Now, this is where things get interesting and I begin to tie the two of them together.
If I have zero, then that means there are no permissions granted.
If I have one, then that means I have read access.
That's where the R comes from.
If I have two, then I have write access.
That's where a W may come from in that second piece right there.
And if I have three, then I have execute, which is denoted by the X.
Now, here's where I really start to tie things together.
If I have no permissions, that's going to be zero.
If I have execute permissions, I'm going to have one.
If I have write permissions, then I'm going to have a two.
If I have read permissions, then I'm going to have a four.
Why is this significant? It's because of bitwise operations.
A bitwise operator is basically a simple mathematical operation to the computer,
such that it can perform this calculation without having to think too much about it.
In this way, you can have read and write permissions.
If I have read and execute permissions, then I'm going to have a six.
A read and execute permission is going to be a five.
A write and execute permission is going to be a three.
And if you want to have read, write, and execute, you're going to have a seven.
And this is why octal is such a great representation for this permission schema,
is because you only have digits permissible from zero to seven.
And this is why it's so important to have a ten in octal.
So the reality of it is Linux only has at most 511 permission states
that represent something for what the current user has,
what somebody is part of this group has, and what other has,
with enough numbers left over to describe a few other things here and there.
And the permission schema, the way it's represented, the way you see it,
it just demeans for us to be able to see very clearly what those permissions are
once you understand what the mapping is.
So let's take a look at some examples here to see if we can help this to sink in.
If you have the permissions 644, then what does that give you?
It gives you read, write, access, but no execute for the current user.
If you are part of that user's group, then read before signifies that you get read access,
you get execute and not write permission.
And if you are part of the other, then you get read permission,
but no write and no execute permissions.
So whatever this was, be it a directory, a file, a socket, or whatever,
everything is a file in Linux.
So these permissions only persist to when you try to access something that has these permissions.
And then if you have the permissions 640, then that means the current user has read, write, access.
If you are part of the group, then they get read access.
And if you're anything else, you get no access.
If you have 755 permissions, then what does that mean?
Well, that means the current user gets read, write, and execute permissions.
They get it all.
5 and 5 means the group, and anyone else gets read and execute permissions.
And 750, respectively, means that the current user can access everything
if you are part of the group, you can read and execute it.
And if you're anything else, you get no access.
Did that click for you?
You know what to do.
Thank you.