Okay, so this is kind of cool.
I'm dipping my toes into AI again.
I managed to download
Stable Diffusion. (Excuse me for the
coughs, I'm kind of sick.) But I
downloaded Stable
Diffusion and you can find it on
the githubs at Automatic1111/stable-diffusion-webui
They created an interface that
we can use. You can just run
the entry point, configure
it to your desires, and boom, you
have yourself an agent running. I'm
actually using my gaming
box for this. I probably should stop
making gaming boxes because I end
up just,
turning them into other things. But
once you get that set up and
running and going, it'll
go ahead and get you set up
with this lovely interface where you
can pretty much type in
what it is you want. So we
can say something like a green forest
scene. A green forest
with an archer overlooking a city
with an elf tower in the background
of Middle Earth.
Ctrl+Enter to hit generate. And
that will go ahead and start generating
an image. Now
because my gaming system has more
GPU RAM or VRAM, whatever you want
to call it, for
that system, then what ends up happening
is this actually generates a lot faster than
my laptop. If you notice that, that
was in like mere seconds. You know,
it just creates
these lovely rich images after tinkering
around with it a little bit and
getting my
prompts right. I can show you how
to set up these things so you
can have your own internal
network so that I can, you know,
use my `/etc/hosts` and point it
over to another machine
within my local network. And then
stable diffusion just runs as a daemon
that starts
up a web interface and you can
download different models that allow
you to generate things
based on different stuff. So like
I can switch this over to like
a YamerAnime_UltraInfinity_V5+VAE
model that they created. It might
take a second for it to load
that into memory. And then
we can generate an image based on
the other model. I'll go ahead and
skip along so you
guys can see the finished result.
Alright, so once that's done and loaded
into memory,
you can use that to generate your
image and it will produce something
for you right now.
Actually, that's a lot faster so we
don't have to worry about it. But
yeah, you can
see how other models have maybe like
different artistic feels to how they
want to generate
some stuff. I thought this was really
cool. I just wanted to share this
and possibly could
do some videos on how I got
this set up as I learned about
it. I'd rather be a little
bit more versed in it. I don't
like talking about things I don't
know, but this was just
really cool. I had to share. It
was fun, man. It was fun, man.
It was kewl! 8)