So... like... to get me started with
stable diffusion, it wasn't really
that much to do.
Really the only thing that's important
is that you download the `webui.sh`,
and then you
can configure it.
But what I did was a little
bit extra because, you know, I'm in
Linux and I get to have fun
with that. =)
So, I created a user specifically
for this.
I'm not going to be running software
I don't trust as an unprivileged user
account on my
system, so that's going to reduce
its capacity of what it can do
to my system.
And then because this is a very
disk-heavy app, I just went ahead
and created a logical
volume for it.
I mean, I happen to be on
LVMs, you can just basically create
a disk, some kind of disk
space that you can use specifically
for this.
Just for the trial, I started with
20Gb, that quickly got up to
50Gb whenever I
realized if you want to test more
than one model, you're going to need
some disk space
for that, in addition to all the
libraries and everything else that's
involved with making
this happen.
And then once you get your file
system set up, you can use block
ID to figure out what
the UUID is if you want to
use that, or I could have, you
know, stuck with the path
to the LVMs, but in any case,
you're just going to try and make
sure that that's available
in your `/etc/fstab`, and then
you're going to mount your directory
for your new user
account.
This will jail them inside of their
own user account or their own file
system too, so that
all the space will be in that
partition and won't take up the rest
of your drive.
And then I went ahead and created
a `~/bin` directory, also you probably
want to set the permissions
because when you mount, that's going
to be set as root, so you're
going to chown that
to the user as well.
And I was also missing the tcmalloc
dependencies, so I just went ahead
and installed that,
and I created a bin directory, and
then I downloaded the web UI from
the GitHub account
for automatic one-on-one stable diffusion
web UI.
We download that bin directory and
set execution permissions on it, and
then I also installed
and modified `webui-user.sh`, so you're
just basically going to change those
as well in those two
places, and that's going to let you... --
that's it, I mean, and then you
just run it.
Now before you execute on it, you
probably want to take a look at
some of the configuration
itself. (This is kind of cool, we've
got some color output here). So if
you're wondering,
this is the directory where I set
it to install, and then I said
clone it to this directory,
and then this command line I discovered
after the fact to get it to
render images for the
amount of memory that my graphics
cards have, and the rest of it,
I mean, I pretty much
just left it as default, I ran
into some memory issues, so I increased
the split size
just a little bit, as it suggested,
and then when it executes, it's going
to kick off a
daemon, that's an error set before,
so let's execute a fresh one, so
yeah, when this thing
runs, it's basically going to kick
off a daemon that will listen on
a port, what's nice is
it only listens on localhost, so you
don't have to worry about it globbing
on all your
internet connections, and once you've
got that up and running, it's going
to load the
models into memory so that you can
start generating images, and basically,
yeah, that's it, you
go to that address, now if this
was running on my machine, you see
the x11 connection
rejected, that's because I already
have chrome running, and I haven't
permitted my remote
machine to be able to create apps,
or run apps on my laptop, because
you don't run this
thing, and this is actually installed
on a server in a different room,
yeah, so once
that's up and running, I was a
little bit extra, and I set it
up with, I put up a nginx
proxy, and then I did some fancy
dns stuff, so that I can access
it clean here in my browser
like this, and forwarded the connection
down to the remote machine that I've
got, that's
got more graphics, really it's my
gaming system in the living room,
I probably should stop
making gaming systems, because I end
up turning them into other things,
but yeah, the models
directory is going to let you have
access to all the different models
that you want to
try out, because apparently they can
all draw a different way, and when
I say models directory,
I mean like, you know, in the
install directory, slash models, you're
going to have this stable
diffusion directory, and inside of
that directory, you are going to find
your safe tensors, you
may only just have that one, the
v1.5-prunedemaonly.safetensors, like this is
the default that it
comes with, and the others I downloaded
off of Hugging Face Emoji, and when
I was talking
disk space, I was not kidding, these
things are huge, so be patient if
you're on a slow
connection, and be mindful if you
pay for the internet by the GB/MB.
What's nice
is once you do have your models
downloaded, you can use this to refresh
the listing here,
it'll check the file system, and anything
you may have downloaded to that directory
will then show up here, you can
select any one of these, it may
take a moment for the
rules to load into memory, because
these safe tensor models are basically
a bunch of
rules that define what it does with
the training data, based on my present
interpretation of
how this stuff works, you can then
take your prompt, and you can hit
generate, and it will
get to cranking at crafting an image
for you, as you can see, this
goes pretty quick, and
that's because, you know, I've got
some firepower on my graphics card
over there on my gaming
system, and so, you know, with that
prompt, attack on titan sharp 4k mikasa
anime beautiful
landscape scenery, yeah, from the
example before, we're able to craft
that, and that's
just based off of the default settings
that it comes with, I'm sure there's
more stuff
I can configure to get the image
to look more like what he did,
I thought this was pretty
cool, I wanted to share how this
works, and what you can do with
it, oh yeah, and by the
way, this folder, where these images
are stored, you can look in outputs,
that's going
to have a directory inside of it,
that's going to be all the different
tools that you may
be using, for now we're just doing
that, and there you have it, folks,
there's a directory
with all the dates and stuff, of
when this was invoked, when you, you
know, sort of by
date, which image, and it also looks
like the seed that was used to
generate the image,
that's kind of cool, and, you know,
in the download place location, wherever
it is, all
the images that you generate, this
is all local, this is on my
gaming box right now, now I'm
not an expert on this (yet), if you're
coming across me, and you're like,
holy crap, AI guy, well
you know, AI was part of my
original career path, as far as my
education is concerned,
and I'd like to continue to pursue
that, I really want to, I have
my associates in computer
science, I want to get my Bachelors
in InfoSec, I want my
Masters in Cloud Computing,
and I want my PhD in AI,
so, I mean, whatever the degrees are,
but anyways, this is me experimenting
with what I can get my hands
on, as far as stuff that's hanging
out there, and I can
understand it, I thought the install
was really easy, and pretty simple,
and I was able to
experiment with it in such a custom
way, that's, I mean, you know, this
is cool, you can just
have fun with it, and I'm learning
a lot about how images are generated,
you know,
how this stuff works under the hood,
I don't want to be one of
those guys that just talks
to the chatbot and thinks it's cute
and all that, no, actually, I'm a
techie guy, I'm
totally about how things work under
the hood, and this is just fascinating
to me.
I don't know, this is what I
do on a Saturday night, how about you? ;P