I'm going to show you what real-time
image generation looks like
with Stable Diffusion Turbo.
Attack on Titan, a 4K soldier.
Me: (I probably should just stitch it,
but oh well.)
Beautiful landscape scenery with vast
buildings sprawled out across the image.
Night standing on a cliff overlooking
the town.
So, I pretty much copied that prompt.
I managed to find the Turbo SDXL
version of the safe tensors.
Managed to copy the prompt.
I don't exactly know what he does
for all of his parameters, but hey,
I got it working.
And, uh.
See all of the different generations
that are possible with this prompt.
And it's just going to keep generating.
And now this was all done with
Comfy UI on GitHub using the latest
and greatest Stable Diffusion Turbo
that was released by Stability AI.
So, that's exactly what that is.
I mean, I don't exactly know what
I'm doing with all of this as
I dip into it and try to
figure it out.
But, I know I need to learn it.
And, this is, like, really cool.
I mean, you just download and go.
And, I mean, they give you such
incredible options that you can use
to, like, truly control and fine-tune
how you want any and everything to
show up in the results.
Oh yeah, and I haven't quite yet
figured out how he got it to
auto-generate.
I changed the seed.
This isn't moving as fast.
But, it did generate an image.
Man, that's kewl!
That's kewl, man!