Yeah, so what's really cool about
this is it is completely local. My
code is not sending anything
out to OpenAI. There's no authentication.
There's no APIs talking to some remote
libraries. This is
all completely local to my system.
Matter of fact, let's go ahead and
step into the code. I can show
you what's happening here since I've
had the chance to read it. One
thing about open source,
what's really cool is that it is
open source, so that means you get
to go read the code. You get
to see what it's doing under the
hood. What's also really amazing about
that is I saw some
people saying out there:
"oh, we don't know what Whisper's doing under the hood."
It's like...
Does nobody go and read the source
code anymore? No, it's totally local.
It uses PyTorch, Pandas,
and NumPy. We'll go ahead and take
a look. What's really cool about this
is I've got three
files that are sitting inside of a
directory. There is a fourth one there,
but that's some
experiments that I'm running on with
CUDA to see if I can get
Whisper to do translations on my
graphics card instead of my processor.
That is going to be fun. In
the meantime, we've got
Dockerfile, we've got index, and we've
got requirements.txt. Let's give a
quick highlight
on the top levels of the files.
Also, just a heads up, this is
out on my GitHub. If you check
out gist.github.com/markizano, you can go
and find Dockerfile. It's one of the
most recent.
It says voice to text based on
Whisper. You can go collect the same
files off of GitHub if you'd
like. You can download these and experiment
with them yourself.
The idea here is I just imported
some libraries. Import
Faster Whisper and some of its models
and stuff. What this will actually
do is it'll go out on
the internet and fetch the latest
model off of HuggingEmoji.com.
This is a place where
you can go to get HuggingFace.
This actually has models that people
have previously designed
and developed and have preloaded LLMs.
You basically download this PyTorch
LLM and that
is what is used to do the
translations. Faster Whisper is a
faster implementation of this.
I know I'm jumping around. This is
what teaching feels like from me whenever
I'm still learning
this stuff. If you guys notice my
web dev stuff, I've been doing that
for years. It's really easy.
It comes off the tongue quick. This
stuff, I'm still picking up and still
digesting all this
wonderful deliciousness. The cool
thing here is that they basically
just, let's see, transcribe,
I think is where I saw the
meat and potatoes of it. This guy's
importing CTranslate2.
It's also importing some text translator
libraries that basically go and take
the audio
and translate it directly into text.
This is all happening local to the
system. When you're
passing that stuff off to the APIs,
they're basically importing libraries
like these
that will go through and transcribe
the audio for you and place it
in a text file and send
that back to you in the API
response. This is transformational
for me. This is Google Assistant
right here. I don't have to pay
for some service or pay for somebody
else to handle it.
I've got everything I need right here.
What I've done is I've gone and
created my own CLI tool
that imports those same libraries
and gives me access to those same
godlike powers and
allows me to basically use FFmpeg
to strip the audio out of the
video file and then import it
into the Whisper library. Whisper
will then go and byte per byte
inspect the audio that comes out of
my video and translate it into text.
I get back a segment list. Actually,
yeah, this is a good way.
This is a good illustration right
here. I get a segment that gives
me an ID and tells me about
where the start and stop is for
the text that it identified and it
took a guess on. As such,
it also tells me there's temperature,
there's compression ratios, and there's
other fun details.
What is important is like the words.
I rewrote the SRT writer because at
first it was like
taking full 30 second segments, translating
that into text, and putting that as
part of a part of
the subtitle in the SRT files. I
didn't like that because then you'd
see this giant paragraph of
text on the video and it's like,
no, subtitles don't work that way.
I rewrote this part here to basically
go through and check to see, do
you have about five or six
words? Do you have about 32 characters?
Do you have about one or two
words or four characters
left in the buffer as I'm going
through and I'm stacking all the subtitles
up? If so, then stack
it so that I get about five
or six words because that's about
what fits in a video or about 32
characters. Or if you've got one or
two words left in the buffer, don't
make that its own
subtitle. Add that to the list. It's
fine if you've got six words in
there. Basically, organize the
subtitles so that they match just
right. Now, I have minimal effort.
I simply feed you a video
and this thing goes through and translates
it out and writes out subtitles perfect
for me.
I do have some minimal edits. There
are some things that are specific
like PV Create, LVM,
things that are industry specific.
If I have to go through, tinker
a few of those,
make sure I got those right. But
when I compare Whisper's ability to
do translations
versus CapCut, hands down, I'm going
with Whisper. They are so much more accurate.
The editing process is so much easier
because I don't have this kludgy,
weird, funky text box
with features. I just want a plain
text box. Let me edit my subtitles
and have a nice day.
I can inscribe them on the video.
I've got another command here called
Inscribe Subtitles.
What this is, it's just an FFmpeg
alias that lets me go through and
write the video,
write the subtitles to the video itself
in the font that I want, which
I happen to choose Impact.
With the styling and all that stuff
too. This is completely automated.
My process,
as far as creating videos is concerned,
and allows me to just hit the
record button,
pass it through the processor. Boom.
Have a nice day. That's wonderful, man.
(incoming b-line over text)
just kind of sort of speaking outside of
@WreckItMech,
if you're not getting into AI, if
you're not exploring this stuff, if
you're terrified of it
and you don't know what's coming,
research it. Get to know it. Understand
it. It's not the ferocious
beast that everybody fears it is,
at least not yet. We still have
a say in how we design and
develop our baby. As humanity, as
the parents of the next generation
that will be, it's our
responsibility to create something awesome.