So, let's talk about your career path.
Now, this is more directive rather than
prescriptive. So, take this with a
grain of salt. It's not a
one-size-fits-all
kind of thing. It's just a general
pattern that I've seen in the industry.
If you're new to IT, you typically
are going to go down one of three
different routes. Either you're going
to be social, you're going to be
design heavy,
or you're going to be functional.
I chose functional. Let me expand
on that just a
little bit further here. If you're
going down the social path, that's typically
going to be your business analyst,
your release manager, your project manager,
maybe even middle management. Social,
I tend to think of it as
like people
management or peopling because you
like to deal with people. Your helpdesk --
(let me hold on, pause before I
get there.) Your designs are going
to be more like
your Photoshop, your Illustrator,
your Adobe products. If you're getting into
gaming, that could be a thing too,
(but I have also learned from experience that
gaming can also be very function heavy
too with the whole geometry, graphics, and
trying to understand how to draw pixels
on the screen.) But there's also the user
experience or UX. Some people also
call this MX, which is like the membership
experience. The idea is to have flows
and designs that actually work and cohesive.
You know, first name, last name, email
address, password. What order do those go
in? How is this supposed to look?
It's supposed to ease and flow this
way to
make it simple to navigate and to
just intuitively figure things out. Designs
are good at that. Function is going
to be your DevOps, your cloud ops, your
information security, your operation
security, programming, things that deal
with the actual way things work, the
function of it. Is it aesthetic? Is
it not
only aesthetic? Does it meet the business
requirements and does the function match
with the social such that the things
do what they're supposed to do? And the
three of these together are all part
of a team. So there's somebody who's
going to
be dealing with the people, somebody
who's going to be making it look pretty,
and somebody who's going to be helping
to make it work. If you can
find somebody
who can do all three, they're unicorns.
You're a rarity. But most people
specialize in something. And if one
of these is calling to you, then certain
types and jobs that you are going
to want to apply for, that are
going to get
you to the places where you want
to go, and hopefully these give you enough
exposure so that you can glean off
of what people are doing related to these
fields, related to these areas, getting
these jobs. If you get a help
desk job, if
you get a reception job. When I
say receptionist, I mean there's somebody
that works in the front off in
the office, like when people go and actually
work in the office, and you notice
there's always somebody there to like
greet the guests, let them come in,
show them around, make sure to get their
badges, make sure their security is
in check, and all that fun stuff.
You know,
having this job can expose you to
various things. Having help desk can
expose you
to being able to work with people,
so that you can evolve into project
management, release management, and
get into those upper, I would say,
just past
entry-level jobs that are like just
a slight upgrade from this. If you're a
function guy, you're gonna want to
get into data entry jobs, working
with Excel,
working with CSV files. If you're
savvy enough and you want to try
your hand at
some things, you can get into API
development itself. You can get into being
a web dev. I highly recommend the
Linux Plus certification, and whatever
it takes
to get to understand and know Linux
better. If you know it inside and
out, I
promise you, function people, you
are going to succeed very well if you
learn how to use Linux. I'm not
gonna speak about things I don't know, because
I avoided design like a plague during
my early years, because I tried and
I was
just like, I'm not good at that.
I know I'm not good at that,
and I'm not gonna
put the efforts in it just yet,
trying to figure it out. So unfortunately,
I kind
of pigeonholed myself into a place
where I don't know the design space
as well as
I should or could; so if you could
drop a comment below and you know
something I
don't, I would appreciate that. And
then finally, we'll close this up
with some
points that you're gonna want to take
home. Don't let this be the end
of this
conversation, and don't let this be
the one video you watch and say,
oh I tried. If
there's one thing about IT and there's
one thing I learned, persistence is key.
Consistency is key, and if you have
a passion for it, it works all
the more to
your favor. You want to make sure
that your resume is on point. You
want to make
sure that it's got all the details
that are needed to be able to
contact with
you at the header, at the top,
need to be visible. You get one
of three things. You
either get to emphasize your experience,
your skills, or your education. Whatever
you value most goes at the top,
and sort in that order. And at
least that's how I
set up my resumes. I also kind
of sort out how I notice about
people whenever I
look at their resumes. Schedule interviews.
Be the active one. Be the one
that is putting yourself on people's
calendars. Follow up. Get on them. Make
sure that they know that you're here.
Make sure that they know that you are
ready and available for work, that
you're excited, that you want to know
about any
of the opportunities that possibly
could be to help you get going,
because you
want to work. In this economy, in
this current state where we're,
we're tipping on the verge of recession
and the tight monetary policy and
everything, people are kind of scared.
I don't know if they want to spend
their money. Guess what? That's when
you step in the door and you
say, look, I may
I know everything up in here, but
I'm willing to learn what I need to
learn. And as someone who is new
to this, I come with a fresh
perspective, and I'm
also willing to do what it takes
to get the job done. And I'm
willing to make
myself available in order to make
this happen. And for the duration
of time that
I'm here, I'm gonna make
sure that I do a good job.
Find others and
continue to network with wherever
you happen to be. So if you
are trying to get
into the programming space, go find
the programming chats. IRC is where you're
gonna find a bunch of them libera.chat
Not sponsored, but...
I hang out
there too as Markizano. You also,
you know, people who go and file
resumes on
LinkedIn and like just leave it at
that. There's a reason why they're
not getting
a job. Follow up. Find people that
work there. Bug them. Be like, hey,
I've been
looking at your company. I'm talking
with HR. I was wondering if you
could help me
out because like I'm wondering what
you guys are working on. You know,
I don't
want to be too creepy and all
that, but like I really would love
to work here.
I'm passionate about what you guys
got going on, and I want to
help you guys out.
And I've wanted to take that strategy.
I've wanted to explore the concept of
what if you get on the good
graces of the team rather than going
through the front door. You go and
you talk to the team, and you
get on their
good rapport, and now the team's talking
to HR. You're talking to HR...
I don't know for certain.
That's not a tried-and-true, but
I'm curious.
Would you be willing to try it
out and find out? And let me
know in the comments (I heard this from Alex Hormozi)
below. I'd be curious to know. And
the last thing I would leave you
with is
don't turn your brain off at night.
If you have time on your hands,
you have time
to read. Go to W3schools.com. Find
anything and everything you can about the
technologies you want to get into.
See if you can find yourself a
home lab. See if
you can find online free resources
that let you set up a terminal,
a console, a
server. Run on the free tier on
AWS... something to give you some
experience so
that you can actually go do the
things. Because there is no better
way to learn
how to do this stuff than to
do it. Than to set up your
own prototype.
That was one of the things that
I had to do in order to
learn the four major
softwares out there. Chef, Ansible,
Puppet, and SaltStack. I set up, I
used a test
lab and set up a mock interface
of an instance of what all of those
technologies would look like. How
would it work and function and and
and. It
takes a bit of work. It takes
some tenacity. But IT can be a
lot of fun, a
lot of rewarding. Mentally, emotionally,
financially. You're gonna love it.
Welcome.