Why yes, yes we can =)
Let's talk about business analysts. Now the good business
analysts that I've worked with in
the past have been the kind that
are the
ones that interface with engineering
and QA. They interface with the project
managers and they interface with the
customer. The business analyst's job
is to
go in with the project manager and
with the customer and to understand the
business need. They are the authority
on trying to decipher what it is
the CEO is
talking about. Whenever he says he
needs this product that's got these features
and we want the buttons this way,
we want this that way, the project
manager is
there to help structure the release
cycle so that the SDLC (Software
Development LifeCycle) processes like
it's supposed to. It is there for
efficiency and to help expedite things
and unblock blockers and such like that.
The project manager is kind of sort
of for the structure of the project itself
whereas the business analyst is going
to be the authority on if there are
features or business requirements
that we're working on within a particular
project. The business analyst is the
authority to go to on the decision if
there's anything that needs to be
made as far as what direction do
we go.
Do we really want something on the
home page that's going to trigger
a query in
the background for a statistic or
do we want to try and cache
that for later or
save that for later or something like
that you know something somebody has to
click on to initiate an action so
that it doesn't draw the servers down
as such.
The business analyst is technical
enough to be able to interface with the
engineering team kind of sort of on
a high level. A project manager typically is
the one who's going to be more
savvy because they interface with the
engineering and the QA teams more
and the project manager is kind of
sort of
there to kind of sort of tee
off and take care of some things
but the business
analyst is also that customer relations
style and type of role where
you're going to be making
sure the customer is comfortable and
okay and
happy and that their needs have been
serviced. If we present a product or
some kind of service to them that
they understand what it does how it can
benefit what happens and also possibly
even facilitate some sales because it's
some kind of a relationship that somebody
has to serve that is that customers
dedicated line to go talk to when
it comes to updates to a particular software
that you happen to be working for
within a company or an organization.