Greetings and welcome to Kisela's
Fintech channel where I take you
from zero to master and IT
and DevOps.
In today's video we're going to
be talking about some audio options
that I have been trying to
put together.
This is kind of sort of
an informal thing. I just have
a few audio options here available
to me
and I wanted to present those
to you here so that you
can have a better idea of
what some things may sound like
depending on what tools I have
available to me.
We have some AirPods here which
is kind of gloss over the
fact that on Linux there's additional
software and settings and configuration
that need to be made.
Just make these things available so
thank you Apple. I appreciate the
extra work.
It'd be great to just connect
to them Bluetooth and just plug
and play but you know, got
to do what you got to
do when it comes to Linux.
I also have these lavalier microphones.
I found these on Amazon. Go
ahead and pull up the product
detail page here.
I just found something that was
within a decent price range that
I could use and would allow
me to be able to get
wireless audio.
So sometimes I have my phone
set up here in the middle
of the room and it's just
not feasible for me to have
a wired headset streaming from the
phone.
I'm afraid my voice isn't well
enough to travel across the room
and catch with all the acoustics.
So having this connected also mumps
with my necklace somewhere.
And so sometimes you see me
go without it because it's incredibly
painful hearing that in the audio.
Trust me, I hear you. I'm
with you.
And well, when you're going with
what you've got and trying not
to dump thousands of dollars in
new hardware,
well, this is what I've had
available to me up until now
and I just want to kind
of sort of put this together
so that you could see in
real time
a screenshot of kind of sort
of what's going on here and
what's happening and see what's going
on here.
So I also have a webcam.
That's what you're watching me on
right now that is USB connected
into my laptop.
And I have to raise my
voice just a little bit just
to make sure that the webcam
is capable of hearing me.
Here on the screen share here,
I've got a Pabu control setup
so that you can see what
options there are available to me
as far as input devices are
concerned.
And I can also select what
kind of configuration I want. You'll
see that as I select those
over here.
In this other window, I've got
my Bluetooth connection here and I
guess I can go ahead and
start off with the AirPods.
We can connect those in very
quick.
And once those are connected, what
I can do is I can
shift the recording to actually watch
for the AirPods.
I need to configure them first.
Yeah, in AirPods, they actually have
two settings. You may not know
this, but there's the hands-free
headset and there's also just the
playback.
They do produce unique outputs and
I was going to demonstrate switching
over to the AirPods, but it
seems you've already been switched
over.
So that's just wonderful.
I could switch the audio back
to the webcam and now you
can hear back-to-back with
a little bit more intention of
what it looks like when I
switch to the AirPods.
And that audio can play out
for you right there.
I did experiment with the Kodak.
It looks like it doesn't have
any visible audio effect that I
could detect.
I'm guessing it's just a matter
of how this information gets transmitted
over Bluetooth.
I read something about that as
I was trying to understand how
audio works when it comes to
especially the Bluetooth devices because
I was trying to find the
best audio options.
But seeing as that is, I
can go ahead and switch over
to the next one, which is
this lot of their microphone here.
If I press the button and
that activates it, turns it on.
It's got a USB charger on
the side so that I can
keep it charged up.
I can use it as an
input device here. I'm going to
go ahead and also switch it
back to the webcam.
We're going to go ahead and
connect the microphone in. It's got
two pieces that connect here.
Press your button, they turn on,
they pair automatically. There's no
need for me to make any
connections there, which is great.
It's just connecting go. The input
is 3.5mm, so that means
there's no additional drivers that
are required.
If I switch the audio over
to this and say analog stereo,
and now you should be hearing
me out of the microphone.
With this, the distance really does
make a difference as far as
how this audio sounds.
I've also tried experimenting with
the volume marker just to see
what sounded good, what sounded bad.
Sometimes I could turn it up
and it would sound really, really
distorted.
I'd leave it in a mid
-45 range and then give myself
enough speaking distance so that my
voice had a chance to travel,
and dissipate a little bit because
if it's right up next to
me, it sounds really distorted. It's
just not pleasant.
Next, we've got the wired headset.
3.5mm, totally plain, simple.
I use it for listening to
music and having phone calls, and
they have served me well.
I feel like I get the
best audio from this, so we
can plug this one in.
Now, you should be hearing me
out of the headset stereo.
I apologize if there was some
audio in there before.
There is an internal microphone. I
can show you that here right
now.
Speaker warning, you're going to want
to turn the speakers down for
just a moment.
And now you can hear all
the wonderful fan noise of what's
going on in the computer.
That is the built-in microphone
to the computer. I usually leave
that muted so that you can't
hear it.
Now, if I change this back
to the headset, you should be
hearing me out of this thing.
And it shouldn't sound that bad,
except when it makes those connections
with my necklace.
That is also not pleasant. It's
kind of one of the reasons
why I either don't wear this
when I'm using this, or pretty
much that.
I'm also going to splice in
some audio from my phone, because
I think it's important to understand
all the devices that I have
to my avail,
and what those sound like as
well, because I wanted to put
all of this stuff in there
back to back to back.
Now, there are two apps in
my phone that I'm actually going
to demonstrate in the recordings that
I'm going to splice into the
video here.
One of them is the built
-in application that came with the
phone, and the other is called
X Camera.
I found this on the App
Store, and they've actually been responsive
with me with regards to actually
providing improvements to the application,
because what really dazzled me was
this application actually pulled the
horsepower out of this 108 megapixel
camera that I have been dying
to take advantage of.
I felt like the default application
just did not do the camera
justice.
So, this is a recording of
what it looks like with me
speaking directly to the phone with
no added microphones.
As you can see, the sound
is fairly decent, and it also
depends on how far away from
my face the phone is as
far as the audio is concerned.
Now, in order for me to
change the stream, I do have
to stop the recording here on
the phone, in order for me
to be able to use any
of the 3.5 million years.
And so, now this is what
it sounds like with the wired
headset connected to my device as
well.
As you can see, I feel
like this is where the best
audio is going to be captured
as far as what I can
use within this device itself.
I can pause the video in
this clip here, and I can
show you what it sounds like
when I use the lavalier microphone.
So, this is what it sounds
like with the lavalier microphone.
This is with the added 3
.5 millimeter. I switched over to
this.
So, now you can hear the
bass and how the distance has
an effect on how the audio
sounds.
I don't have any microphone controls
within the phone itself, so whatever
it gives me is whatever it
gives me.
That's all you get. Android is
really bad at managing audio. I'm
pretty sure it just cut out
too.
So, we can add that to
the review as well for this
thing.