Oh, hey there, it's Markizano
and welcome. Let's talk about virtualization:
Docker edition.
First things first, docker is not
a virtual machine. Docker is not a
virtual machine!
Docker is not a virtual machine!!!
I cannot tell you how many times I
had to learn this
the hard way myself and then had
to reinstruct the team because whenever
Docker was first
coming out, everybody was like, "how
do I SSH into the container?" :facepalm:
Docker is not a virtual machine. Before
I go straight into docker, let's kind
of sort
of break down some components about
how Linux works under the hood. You've
got PID1, this
can be sysv-init, it can
be Upstart, it can be OpenRC, it
can be systemd. And that kicks
off your X environment, be it Xorg,
be it Wayland. Okay, then you've also
got your
Getty sessions, which is,
back in the old days when Linux
was connected to
a typewriter. This is what allowed
you to talk to the to the
computer itself. You've
also got your SSH daemon. PID1 can
also start your docker daemon. While
you have your X
environment running, it can start
other apps, these other apps like
your terminal environment
emulation, your Chrome browser, your
Firefox browser, your Discord client,
not server,
and xchat, which is like for IRC.
I know, I'm sorry, I just dated
myself with that one.
Have a nice day. Anyways, these apps,
they get started by your X environment.
These are
the graphical sessions that you can
look at interact with your display
manager, your desktop
manager, I'm kind of sort of taking
all those concepts and wrapping them
up into one block,
so to speak to oversimplify it because
to break it down that far would
be well over
too many people's heads too quick.
So trying to dip into this as
best I can. Docker basically
takes these things that are running
in your system and puts them inside
of their own space
so that they look like they came
from this, this PID1. Docker emulates
the entire Linux
environment and makes it consistent
so that everything that's happening
inside of Linux
looks like it came from that one
PID or PID1, which happens to be
the Docker daemon itself.
So what Docker can do is make
it so that your Java app, or, for
example, the thing that creates
the captions for my videos that I
use is actually a script written by
OpenAI. I imported it into
a Docker container and I basically
give that container access to the
rest of my system,
my videos, so that it can pass
through the interpreter that goes
through and converts
my audio stream into subtitles so
that you can see the captions below
on my videos. Python
scripts, any kind of application,
whatever it is you have going on,
Docker basically
makes it so that the environment itself
is a consistent landscape across the
board and
you don't have to worry about what
the user has installed. It comes prepackaged inside
of your own container so that you
have your one PID running inside of
its own environment,
thinking it's the only application
running inside of your Linux-able,
MacOS-able,
Windows-able environment. Just to
type those out so that you can
see what they mean, PID1
can be sysvinit, openrc, or systemd.
If I mispronounce that, I apologize.
I've heard it pronounced
sysvinit (or "five"), so if you know
authoritatively what it means, please
drop a comment below.
I don't know any better. I just
know I prefer it over systemd because
it works, it's less
buggy, and Pottering just didn't...
I don't know. We'll get there. And
so here's the magic
of how all this stuff works. You
can create this thing called a Dockerfile.
Use `docker build -t image:version`
to tag your image. (I'll type that
out here in a second). But your
Dockerfile basically
describes what you want your image
to look like. So you can source
it from some other
image that somebody else has created.
Typically you start from a Linux base,
a Macintosh base,
or a Windows base if you so
decide to containerize Windows. Good
luck with that. I wish you luck
in that endeavor. And then you can
add whatever files, scripts, whoever
you need, whatever
you want. You can run specific commands.
You can tell it to install your dependencies.
You can set your entry point to
whatever kind of interpreter you want
to use. If it's Bash,
if it's Python, if it's Perl, if
it's PHP, I don't care, doesn't matter...
Does it execute?
That's all we care about. And then
your command can be used to execute
whatever specific commands
you have going on. This is the
entry point that kicks off the application,
that starts
off everything. So if there's any
finishing configurations that need
to be put into place
because you're inside of a dynamic
environment, if there is anything
you need to do as far
as starting up services, kicking off
subprocesses, talking to remote servers, authenticating
to whatever, you can do that after
you've compiled your image and started
your application
up. And then it's really as simple
as build your image using docker build,
`-t` to
tag it as a specific name so
that you can reference that later.
And then you simply
use `docker run` to run your container
image. Now that is way oversimplified.
I am dropping
out a lot of details just to
get this point across so that you
can see how simple it is
to craft a custom application, compile
it up inside of an image, and
then run it inside
of a specific environment. You know,
just, just go, just, just build and
go. It's wonderful.
I love it. Want to know what
all that extra is? Well, I guess
we're over the TikTok limit,
so you're going to have to subscribe
and find out some more. My name
is Markizano Draconus,
and I'm here to teach you about
IT, DevOps, and CloudOps. I really
hope this is helpful,
and we'll see you on the next one =)