So let's talk about virtualization.
Now let's say you're in an environment,
be it Windows, be it Linux, be
it Mac.
You probably have heard of a virtual
machine at some point, but what is that?
Well whenever you first start up the
computer, it needs to boot into the system.
That's where you access the BIOS.
The BIOS talks to your hard drive,
and then your hard drive has the
operating system on it.
The operating system being that software
that talks to the disks inside of
a hard drive,
the sensors that detect the temperature
of the motherboard, that actually
speak to the
processor, that actually read and
write to the memory, that talk to
your monitor, access
your microphone, and other parts of
your computer.
Your operating system is what is responsible
for talking to the hardware.
Sometimes we want an environment where
all of that is predetermined, predestined, already
mocked up, and represents something
that is consistent, and something
we can actually
use.
That's where virtual machines come
into play.
Virtual machines are a virtualization
of your operating system.
They simulate the hardware that your
operating system talks to in order
to create something
like a virtual machine.
VMWare and VirtualBox are examples
of virtualization software that give
you an operating system-like
environment without needing to actually
boot into another operating system.
Now if you want to pay for
the licensing from Oracle, you can
use VMWare.
VMWare also allows you to deploy fleets
upon fleets of virtual machines.
So say you have one really huge
server that's got a lot of resources
like a terabyte of
hard drive space, 64 gigabytes of
RAM, and 16 cores of CPU power.
You can then create four different
machines inside of that physical hardware
to create
4 additional virtual machines.
Pretty cool stuff, isn't it?
KVM stands for Kernel Virtual Machine.
This is a lower level version of
a virtual machine that allows you
to access an environment
that is strictly based off of the kernel.
KVMs and virtual machines only work
whenever you're talking to physical hardware.
Now Docker is a new instantiation
of this virtualization software.
Docker surrounds just the process,
whereas virtual machines surround
the entire operating system.
One of the confounding things that
drove me nuts whenever I was first
learning about Docker
when it first came out, back whenever
it was still open community, we thought
that it was
a virtual machine.
Or we kind of sort of placated
it and used it as if it
was a virtual machine because we
were trying to SSH into it.
Well, you don't do that with Docker.
We have now learned a lot, and
Docker actually surrounds just the process.
Just that one process can believe
that it's inside of a RedHat
environment, a Debian
environment, a Windows environment.
And yes, Docker also supports Macintosh
virtual containers.
Now if you want to deploy fleets
of virtual machines, you can use Control
Panel, which
is open source software.
You can go download it and it
will manage the virtual machines for
you in a virtual
like environment.
If you want to deploy fleets of
Docker containers, you can use Docker
Compose, or you can also
use Kubernetes, which is automation
software for your containers.
Now to give you a visual representation
of what these levels of virtualization
looks like,
let's take a look right quick.
We've got hardware, which includes
your mouse, your keyboard, your CPU,
your GPU, your central
processing unit, your graphics card,
your memory, your disk.
All the hardware that you can physically
put your hands on, that is what
actually is supported
by your operating system.
A virtual machine takes a virtualization
of that hardware, and that's why I
call it soft
hardware, because it's software that
simulates what hardware is like.
And this is where you can contain
your operating system inside of a
virtualized environment
without actually having to create
a physical environment that represents
how you're going
to access your computer.
This is how you can have Windows
running on Linux, Linux running on
Windows, and Windows
on Linux running on a Mac, and
vice versa, and all the other different permutations.
And then finally, Docker is containerization
that goes down to a single process,
or maybe
process group, if that process is
like a, you know, like Syslog, for
example, is actually
a container, a supervisor, and then
the Syslog agent itself.
Some things are multi-process, and
that's getting a little low-level.
The idea is Docker creates a containerized
environment that allows your application to
think it's on Red Hat, or Debian,
or Windows, or Mac, or whichever.