Loneliness.
Many are scared of loneliness.
I wonder, I ponder...
Are they really scared of themselves?
To be afraid of being alone is
to be unsatisfied with one's own company.
Why fear one's own shadow?
Loneliness should not be feared, unless
you are a fearful person.
People fear loneliness, but do they
fear themselves?
Ask yourself: am I really that bad company?
You may be surprised at your answer.
You may find that you really didn't
like your own company.
If so, then why?
Why do you carry with you what
you make as part of yourself that
you don't like?
What can you change?
What can't you change?
What may be hidden from truth that
could be changed, if only you put
in the shadow work?
Do you want change?
It could be very difficult,
but the results could be so rewarding.
Loneliness doesn't mean being alone.
You could be in a crowd of
people and still feel it.
I say lean into it, embrace it.
Admit it entry into your heart so
that you may transmute it into the
brightest light
such that no one around you feels
lonely ever again.
Including yourself, but most of all:
for yourself...