Cannot stand the silence,
some might say,
or are you just upset
from not getting your way?
Interjections abound, the talk will
talk on, but have you ever really
sat in silence?
Silence can be your best friend...
If you let it...
always there; accompanying every pause
and break,
always there when you need a moment to reflect,
never wavering...
when you sit still long enough for it to reach you,
never abandoning you,
even if you disturb it just a little,
never leaving your side, even if you
told it to leave.
Silence will never abandon you.
Silence can be your best friend,
if you let it.
Ever present, ever loving,
Silence never stops giving what it does best.
Standing right there by your side,
never leaving, never abandoning,
Silence never judges you, you do,
Silence never interrupts you.
Silence never hurts you, you do.
Silence will sit and listen patiently
to all your diatribes and monologues.
Silence will let you judge yourself.
Silence will listen as you continue to evolve and grow.
Silence will not abandon you.
As you discover the answer to your ponderings,
Silence will be there.
As you develop your mind,
silence will be watching.
As you rewrite your musings,
silence will be listening.
As you reach a new stage of consciousness,
silence will be there.
Silence is not to be feared
or avoided.
Silence should be embraced.
Silence can give you yourself...
but only if you are patient enough.
If you are patient enough to list to yourself,
to evolve and grow, silence
can give you that, but only if
you are patient
enough to get to know yourself.
Can you stand the silence?