Greetings and welcome to
Kizano's FinTech channel,
where I take you from zero to
master in IT and DevOps.
In today's video, we're going to be
talking about the Git process.
In previous videos on other platforms,
we've talked about Git in a little
bit of detail,
such that I can give you the
terms and terminology,
how it works, going over the fundamentals
of Git,
but not really talking about the process
by which this can get completed.
This video is going to be a
deep dive,
where we actually step into some scenarios
so that this makes better sense,
and you get a better understanding
of how
software engineering works from a
process perspective.
By the end of this video,
you should be able to step through
your first commit,
being able to understand how to merge
your files into the branches.
You should be able to understand the
fundamentals of a pull request,
why that should happen,
when you should open those up,
what should happen within the discourse
of the pull request,
and how to merge your changes back in.
What is the meaning of a release
and how we're going to accomplish that,
and tagging your branches such that
you can come back to those specific versions,
as they are related to the releases
that are associated with the code
that you're pushing out.
Also, as a bonus,
we're going to cover a merge conflict.
This is a video you're not going
to want to miss.
Hi, my name is Markizano Draconus,
and welcome to Kizano's FinTech channel,
where I take you from zero to
master in IT and DevOps.
So we'll first kick things off with
the master branch or the main branch,
whatever you want to call it,
which is the main copy of the
development line
that represents the code that recently
went to production.
We're going to create a branch*
off the master branch,
and we're going to create the staging branch.
Now, a little more elaboration on
what's going on here.
The master branch, as I'm going to
call it for this video,
is going to be the main line
of development,
meaning this is the closest copy to
production that we have.
Production is going to be the live copy,
the live version of your website,
that is the thing that's out there
making you money.
The staging branch is going to be
the place
where you present a copy of production
that's not quite production,
that allows us to do some testing and
assert that any changes that we make
to the website are the changes that
we expect.
We get to see what the result
of those changes are,
and we also get to operate in
some test bed environment to better
understand and know,
are we going to break the site?
Is it going to take it down?
Is it going to enhance it just
the way we want it to,
or maybe we wanted to put that
picture two pixels to the right instead?
This is the place where you can
do that,
and this is the branch where the
majority of those changes go as we
stage things for a release.
Now, we're going to branch from the
staging branch down to the development branch.
Now, the development branch is the
place where most of
the development team is going to be
contributing their changes.
If you have a team of two
or three,
you can get away with contributing
to the development branch directly.
For teams that are much larger,
need to be more dispersed,
need to be more decentralized,
can elect to create additional branches
below the development branch
that can be the sources of truth
where they go to get their changes
prior to promoting those branches
to any particular higher region, so
to speak.
If you notice, this pattern of creating
a branch off of the changes
is going to be a recurring pattern,
a recurring shape that is designed
in this giant mosaic that represents
the Git process.
Stay with me now as we continue
to look another pane of glass deeper
into the Kaleidoscope.
Now, before embarking on a project,
let's say you've gone through the
initial steps,
you now have all the business logic
in front of you,
you just need to convert that into
computer code,
and we're about to begin on the
execution phase of our project.
While in the execution phase,
you're going to take out a branch
on the development branch.
Why?
Because at this point, we're about
to make some changes to the code
in our own environment, so to speak,
so that other people can do the
same thing.
If everyone pulls from the development branch
and makes their changes from the development
branch on their local branch,
they can make changes in an isolated
environment, more or less,
from a development perspective and
being able to write the files to disk
and distribute those changes among
the other teams
so that other people can see a
copy of what it is they wrote.
And also for auditing purposes, you
can CYA (cover your arse) with this for every commit.
There's a hash that represents the
time at which you made the change.
How many files were made in that change?
And you can even write your own
signature saying,
I made those changes.
And it's almost like, you know,
you writing your own transaction to
a blockchain of sorts,
(if you're in cryptocurrency).
Git allows you to branch from other changes,
make your changes to that branch,
and then later we can merge those
changes back in.
And it allows us to do this
in a decentralized way
so that we're not all making changes
to the same exact files,
to the same exact directory tree.
For me, it's kind of like the
undo button.
I commit every change and I annotate
just about everything I do.
It's typically one or two changes
per file,
maybe a collection of changes across
a couple of files.
And I attach a message associated
with those changes
describing the why and the rationale
behind the change that I was making.
So in the git commit, and it
asks you the message,
and it says, what's the message you
want to make?
I'll summarize in a sentence or two
describing what the changes were and
why I was making those changes.
In this way, when somebody goes back
and they look at the history,
they can see and understand the thought process
that was going on in my mind
as I was making the changes to
the code and the reason why.
I may also include the ticket ID.
I may also include any other kind
of reference information to say,
well, if I make this change to
the code,
this is the reason why I'm making
the change to the code.
And it better articulates that so
that you can share that with other people
and they can look upon that and
see it
and not have to interrogate you for it.
Or at least that's the idea.
Now, say the changes are complete
and you're ready to merge your changes
back up.
What's going to happen is we're going
to open a pull request at this point.
And we're going to say, hey, I
have changes that I've made in my
feature branch.
I am now ready to take those
changes and merge them back into the
code base.
And by opening a pull request, you're
inviting another developer
to come and observe the changes that
you've made.
Do they honor the coding standards
that we have put forth?
Do you have enough spaces?
Are the braces on the same line?
Do you match the same formatting?
Not only that, did you place the
files in the right location?
Are the files conformant to the designs
of the framework?
Do the changes honor and adhere what
it is
we're looking for?
But aside from the politics of the code,
there's also the functionality of
the code.
Did it make the actual intended changes?
Do you have the associated unit tests
along with the code
to assert that what you changed and
what you altered
is going to end up with the
results that you expected?
The tests can also be used as
a sign off and a check off
to say,
yes, I have asserted that this code
is doing what it's supposed to do.
But also could be used as an
example of how this code is supposed
to be used.
Once you've made all your changes
and you've submitted them for a pull request,
somebody else comes in and basically asserts
that those changes were made correctly.
And if not, they can offer some
feedback for you
to proceed with making changes to
honor them
before they get merged back into the
development branch.
Once the changes have been merged
into the development branch,
that's time for the next parts of
the phases to kick off.
So now that you've made your changes
in your feature branch,
you've successfully gone through your
pull request.
Your changes have been successfully
accepted by the team.
And now you're ready to take your changes
and merge them into the staging branch.
The team has already signed off on,
let's also assume,
(just kind of sort of going along
the happy path here.)
Let's assume that your changes were successful.
You went through testing, your testing
was successful.
And the team was also happy and
excited for your changes.
And we can't wait to get them
into production.
The next phase is to pass this
over to the customer
and say, hey, we are done with
the changes.
We've offered the feature.
We've inserted your widget.
Are you happy with those changes?
Would you like anything else?
Would you want anything more from this?
And so the development branch
now opens a pull request up to
the staging branch
as we pass the code along to
the customer
or not the code, but the results
of the code.
And we say, did we get this right?
Let's also assume the customer is
perfectly happy,
doesn't require any other changes,
doesn't ask for you to go ahead
and move it back to other pixels
because he changed his mind last minute.
And let's just assume that none of
those things
ever happened in a perfect world.
And you're able to take your changes
from the staging branch
and merge them up to the master branch
because we're ready to publish to production.
And so the next stage is to
take staging
and merge it into master.
And by doing so, we open another
pull request.
Once we've taken our changes
and merged them into the master branch,
that is in effect from a developer's perspective,
publishing the code to production.
Now what this accomplishes is all
of the changes
and all of the work has now
been moved
into a place where we now know
this is a copy
of what was last published to production.
As a result, what we do next,
we tag.
We now have release 1.0.
Congratulations.
This is the perfect happy path.
We go from master.
We break it down to staging.
We break it down to development.
And then we have a feature.
We make our changes to the feature.
We merge our feature back into the
development branch.
The development branch merges back
into the staging branch.
The staging branch merges back
into the master branch.
And we have our release as a result
of this entire process that has guided us
to where we stand today.
Now, that's the happy path.
That's assuming there's no problems.
That's what they teach you in classrooms.
That's what they want you to know
on the blogs.
What happens in reality?
You know, your code doesn't work out here.
You end up with bugs.
The customer never accepts your changes.
They always want last minute changes.
The development team is never happy
with your code.
They always want you to refine your work.
And when you get into production,
there's going to be bugs.
And they're going to want you to
fix it hot spot.
Hot on the spot.
And, well, darling, that's where the
overtime kicks in....
Let's begin.
We're going to break this down.
Let's say you've got another ticket.
Another feature has come in.
And we need to get this feature
in at the same time.
Or we allow the features to run asynchronously
and we'll deploy them to production
as they become available.
How do you manage yourself in a situation
where you've got other people involved
in the same project
and they all need to contribute changes
to the code as well?
This is where things get really specific.
If they're making changes outside
of the files and modules
that you're working on yourself, you're
just fine.
They can make their changes.
They can publish them out.
They can put them to their branches,
merge them accordingly.
And when you receive and pull down
the changes,
it'll be a clean pull because you're
just pulling files
in other directories, not your own.
Say you're working on a feature.
Feature two has come in.
You're part of this team's project.
Feature one ended up not taking that
much time.
It got completed.
You're inside of feature two.
You branched at about the same time
they did.
You have the same code.
But what ends up happening is you
make a couple of changes.
Their feature got done.
Now it's time to take on their
changes and their code.
You first enact this operation by
doing a git pull
and you see the develop branch got updated.
So then you do a git merge
from origin develop
to pull those changes into your branch
to make sure that you stay up
to date with the latest changes
so that by the time it comes
for you to push your changes
into the other branches, you won't
have a bunch of conflicts.
The idea as a developer is to
resolve those conflicts over time.
A lot of people as developers, I
want to say get lazy,
but I think they also suffer from attrition,
is constantly staying up to date with changes,
especially if they completely disrupt
your entire workspace,
can get challenging.
I understand these.
And I'm here to teach you how
to navigate that.
This is how you can maneuver this
to get through it
because that's the operations that
need to happen in the brain.
So those changes come in.
You've been making your own changes.
Now you need to merge.
What happens?
Well, if they make changes to other
files, like I said,
you get a clean merge.
They just merge right in, done, cool,
up to date.
I don't need to do anything else.
I may push back to the remote
to make sure that, you know,
everybody else is aware I pulled my
changes in.
But what happens after that?
What happens if someone does make
a change to a file you're working on?
You now encounter what's called a
merge conflict.
But the idea of resolving a merge
conflict is to think,
what was the code intended to do
as a result of the changes that
were made?
If somebody's incoming changes were
intended to just rename a variable
or if it was a little bit
of white space, those changes are
fairly easy to overcome.
But if there are cases where an
entire function contract has changed
or the body of a function has changed,
and it's in the same code that
you're writing,
you will then need to consider how
those changes will impact
and what the end result was that
was the attempt at what needs to
be done.
And make sure that you resolve all
of the changes inside of all the files.
Do a diff afterwards to make sure
that there's no trailing
stuff that needs to be cleaned up
as a result of the conflict.
Because the conflicts themselves will
be written to the files.
And one of the things that gets
really annoying with me and editors
is they try to be too helpful.
And there's all these colors.
And it's so distracting.
So the idea is if you come
into a merge conflict,
the idea is to come to a
resolution of it.
And the resolution to the merge conflict
is what do you want the outcome
to be?
I stay focused on what the code
is supposed to do.
And I don't think too much about,
well, what did this, you know,
what was this incoming change?
What was this incoming change?
What was this perspective?
It's helpful to understand those perspectives.
But at the end of the day,
the code is going to do what
the code needs to do.
So if changes need to be overwritten,
that's fine.
And sometimes bugs are a result of
merge conflicts.
It's a side effect of what happens.
And as developers, that's what we're
here to do.
That's what we're here for.
That's part of your job as a
developer and why you make the six bugs.
So once we merge our conflicts, then
we can continue our changes.
Same principles apply.
Once you've made your changes to your
feature branch,
open a pull request to ask for
those changes to be merged in.
Oh, and speaking of bugs, I got
a little tidbit for you.
If a bug is detected in the
develop branch before it gets promoted up,
it can be easily corrected here in
the develop branch.
And the only thing it affects is
the other feature branches.
If a bug is detected in the
staging branch, what ends up happening?
The staging branch must now propagate
its changes back down.
That's not good.
It's good that we found the bug
in staging before it made it to production.
And that's staging's purpose.
But you want to try and reduce
and minimize how much of non-merging
commits get made to
the staging branch, because you don't
want too many hotfixes.
To be made to staging, that makes
it difficult for development,
because now they have incoming changes
that are not part of the development team.
These changes are coming in from another
source that shouldn't be from the
proper process,
and where the business analyst should
be talking with the customer saying,
hey, that's a feature, not a bug.
Sorry, it's going to cost you a
little bit more.
If your bug is detected in production,
that's really bad,
because that means that bug now needs
to be propagated back down.
That bug fix needs to be propagated
back down to staging,
back down to development, and into
all your feature branches.
That's also not good, because then
you also have to cut a new release
and re-tag your code saying, we
made a change to production, and it
happened to be a quick fix.
Now, as far as your release versioning
is concerned,
something else that doesn't get talked
about enough.
You have your major number, your minor
number, your fixed number, and your
build number.
Build number is optional.
Some people chop that off.
The major number, if this increments,
to me, that tells me you did
a complete rewrite of your code.
Whatever is going on in this version
is completely incompatible with anything
in the prior version.
The minor version update says, this
is a minimal update.
It's a good update.
It's a sustainable update, or has
some substance in its update.
But for the most part, is incompatible
with previous versions.
But there may be some parts of
it that are still functional with
this version.
The fix and the build are just
small, minor security patch updates.
You definitely should update to the
latest of these.
But as far as the data is
concerned, they should be completely compatible
with previous versions of the site.
So this is the Git process.
For the most part, anytime you want
to make a change to the repository,
branch off of your main source of
truth, make your changes to that branch,
and send a pull request to merge
those changes back into that branch,
or into your target development branch,
wherever it needs to be reviewed before
being merged back into master.
The idea behind this is to make
sure that you have an opportunity
to make your changes
without the incoming changes outside
of your control.
You have the control to be able
to say,
I want to pull those changes in
at my time, at my pace,
when I'm ready to accept those changes.
And I've made enough changes to my
code that it's complete enough
that I could accept those changes
and deal with those resolutions.
And I have the freedom and space
in my brain to do that.
Because when you're operating and
working on your feature,
oftentimes you have a tree of code
in your head
that can't fit the rest of this
process in
along with it while you're trying
to work the code.
And so it's better to distinguish
when you're going to be putting your
development hat on
to write your code,
focus on that tree of knowledge that
you have in your mind to write
your code,
versus when you're done with your
feature, you can put that off to
the side.
Your functions aren't full, expanded,
all the lines of code in your head.
You can now just refer to the
header and know what it was supposed
to do.
And you can come back to the
process aspect of this
that will allow you to focus on
how you get these changes in
or how you accept other changes into
your code.
This is the process by which software
gets complete.
And I'm not saying it is the
one end all be all.
Neither am I saying is this process
going to be the same for all
of eternity.
What I am saying is that this
is an industry standard,
well-identified, step-by-step how
stuff gets complete
that's applicable to both the corporate world
and the open source world.
My goal and objective with this is
to make you as efficient as possible
in whatever arena you decide to play,
whether it be in the corporate environment
or it could be in the open source.
So that is the Git process from
start to finish,
where I step you through some more details
and you get a better understanding
of how things are done.
I really hope this was helpful.
I hope it was informative and educational
for you.
And I look forward to seeing you
on the next video.