Greetings, and welcome to Kizano's
FinTech channel, where I take you
from zero to master
in IT and DevOps. In today's video,
we're going to be talking about the
Git process.
In previous videos on other platforms,
we've talked about Git in a little
bit of detail,
such that I can give you the
terms and terminology, how it works,
kind of sort of going over
the fundamentals of Git, but not really
talking about the process by which
this can get completed.
This video is going to be a
deep dive where we actually step into
some scenarios so that this
makes better sense and you get a
better understanding of how software engineering
works from a process perspective.
This is a video you're not going
to want to miss.
Hi, my name is Markizano Draconus,
and welcome to Kizano's FinTech channel,
where I take you from zero to
master in IT and DevOps.
So we'll first kick things off with
the master branch or the main branch,
whatever you want to
call it, which is the main copy
of the development line that represents
the code that recently went
to production. We're going to fork
off the master branch and we're going
to create the staging
branch. The master branch, as I'm
going to call it for this video,
is going to be the main line
of development. Production is going
to be the live copy, the live
version of your website.
The staging branch is going to be
the place where you present a copy
of production that's
not quite production that allows us
to do some testing and assert that
any changes that we make
to the website are the changes that
we expect, and this is the branch
where the majority of those
changes go as we stage things for
a release. Now, we're going to branch
from the staging branch
down to the development branch. If
you notice, this pattern of creating
a branch off of the
changes is going to be a recurring
pattern, a recurring shape that is
designed in this giant
mosaic that represents the Git process.
Stay with me now as we continue
to look another
pane of glass deeper into the Kaleidoscope.
Now, before embarking on a project,
let's say you've
gone through the initial steps, you
now have all the business logic in
front of you, you just need
to convert that into computer code,
and we're about to begin on the
execution phase of our project.
While in the execution phase, you're
going to take out a branch on
the development branch.
Why? Because at this point, we're
about to make some changes to the
code in our own environment,
so to speak, so that other people
can do the same thing. If everyone
pulls from the development
branch and makes their changes from
the development branch on their local branch,
they can make changes in an isolated
environment, more or less. Now, each
time you want to make a
change, you make a commit. For me,
it's kind of like the undo button.
I commit every change and
I annotate just about everything I
do. It's typically one or two changes
per file, maybe
a collection of changes across a couple
of files, and I attach a message
associated with those
describing the why and the rationale
behind the change that I was making.
So, in the git commit,
and it asks you the message, and
it says, what's the message you want
to make? I'll summarize
in a sentence or two describing what
the changes were and why I was
making those changes.
In this way, when somebody goes back
and they look at the history, they
can see and understand
the thought process that was going
on in my mind as I was
making the changes to the code and the
why. I may also include the ticket
ID. I may also include any other
kind of reference information.
Now, say the changes are complete
and you're ready to merge your changes
back up. What's going to
happen is we're going to open a
pull request at this point, and we're
going to say, hey, I have
changes that I've made in my feature
branch. I am now ready to take
those changes and merge them
back into the code base. And by
opening a pull request, you're asking
another, you're inviting
another developer to come and observe
the changes that you've made. Once
the changes have been
merged into the development branch,
that's time for the next parts of
the phases to kick off.
So, now that you've made your changes
in your feature branch, you've successfully
gone through
your pull request, your changes have
been successfully accepted by the
team, and now
you're ready to take your changes
and merge them into the staging branch.
The team has already
signed off on, let's also assume,
just kind of sort of going along
the happy path here.
Let's assume that your changes were
successful. You went through testing,
your testing was
successful, and the team was also
happy and excited for your changes,
and we can't wait to
get them into production. The next
phase is to pass this over to
the customer and say, hey, we
are done with the changes. We've offered
the feature. We've inserted your widget.
Are you happy
with those changes? Would you like
anything else? Would you want anything
more from this?
And so, the development branch now
opens a pull request up to the
staging branch as we pass the
code along to the customer, or not
the code, but the results of the
code, and we say, did we get
this right? Let's also assume the
customer is perfectly happy, doesn't
require any other
changes, doesn't ask for you to go
ahead and move it back two other
pixels because he changed his
mind last minute, and let's just assume
that none of those things ever happened
in a perfect world,
and you're able to take your changes
from the staging branch and merge
them up to the master
branch because we're ready to publish
to production, and so the next stage
is to take staging
and merge it into master, and by
doing so, we open another pull request.
Once we've taken our
changes and merged them into the master
branch, that is, in effect, from a
developer's perspective,
publishing the code to production.
Now, what this accomplishes is all
of the changes and all of the
work has now been moved into a
place where we now know this is
a copy of what was last published
to production. As a result, what we
do next, we tag. We now have
release 1.0. Congratulations.
Say you're working on a feature. Feature
2 has come in. You're part of
this team's project.
Feature 1 ended up not taking that
much time. It got completed. You're
inside of Feature 2.
You branched at about the same time
they did. You have the same code,
but what ends up happening is
you make a couple of changes. Their
feature got done. Now, it's time to
take on their changes
and their code. You first enact this
operation by doing a git pull, and
you see the develop branch
got updated, so then you do a
git merge from origin develop to pull
those changes into your branch
to make sure that you stay up
to date with the latest changes so
that by the time it comes for
you to push your changes into the
other branches, you won't have a bunch
of conflicts. The idea as
a developer is to resolve those conflicts
over time. Oh, and speaking of bugs,
I got a little
tidbit for you. If a bug is
detected in the develop branch before
it gets promoted up,
it can be easily corrected here in
the develop branch, and the only thing
it affects is the other
feature branches. So, this is the
git process. For the most part, anytime
you want to make a change
to the repository, branch off of your
main source of truth, make your changes
to that branch,
and send a pull request to merge
those changes back into that branch
or into your target
development branch, wherever it needs
to be reviewed before being merged
back into master.
The idea behind this is to make
sure that you have an opportunity
to make your changes
without the incoming changes outside
of your control. You have the control
to be able to say,
I want to pull those changes in
at my time, at my pace, when
I'm ready to accept those changes,
and I've made enough changes to my
code that it's complete enough that
I could accept those changes
and deal with those resolutions. And
I have the freedom and space in
my brain to do that,
because when you're operating and
working on your feature, oftentimes
you have a tree of code in
your head that can't fit the rest
of this process in along with it
while you're trying to work the
code. And so, it's better to distinguish
when you're going to be putting your
development hat
on to write your code, focus on
that tree of knowledge that you have
in your mind to write
your code, versus when you're done
with your feature, you can put that
off to the side,
your functions aren't, you know, full,
expanded, all the lines of code in
your head,
you can now just refer to the
header and know what it was supposed
to do. And you can come back
to the process aspect of this that
will allow you to focus on how
you get these changes in,
or how you accept other changes into
your code. This is the process by
which software gets
complete. And I'm not saying is the
one end all be all, neither am
I saying is this process going
to be the same for all of
eternity. What I am saying is that
this is an industry standard,
well identified, step by step, how
stuff gets complete that's applicable
to both the corporate
world and the open source world. My
goal and objective with this is to
make you as efficient
as possible in whatever arena you
decide to play, whether it be in
the corporate environment
or it could be in the open
source environment. So that is the
Git process from start to finish,
where I step you through some more
details and you get a better understanding
of how things are
done. I really hope this was helpful.
I hope it was informative and educational
for you.
And I look forward to seeing you
on the next video.