So let's talk about Git, the stupid
content tracker.
Now, if you don't know anything about
what I'm talking about,
I have other videos to get you
caught up
on what's going on.
In the meantime, I'm going to assume
that you've watched those other videos
and you know just about what Git is.
So here's the thing, you've been editing
this code,
you know how to commit,
you know how to push your changes
to the remote,
you know how to pull someone else's
changes down,
you understand the fundamental concept
of a branch
and how it is a line of
thinking or a line of commits
that you're making to a particular
set of changes.
So here's the flow, here's the juicy stuff,
here's the boss battle.
We're gonna understand this whole
control flow
as far as how a software development lifecycle
will complete itself in a project team.
This is the stuff they don't teach
you in college
and companies want you to know this
so that you can be efficient in
getting your work done.
And again, of course, I didn't really
learn much from college
anyways, because it was just high
school all over again,
but anyways, that's a side of the point.
Here's the thing, you're going to
have a set of branches,
a series of branches that are going
to represent
a set of changes.
The master branch, typically for production releases.
This is supposed to mimic what is
in production,
what is in that environment that is
making you money.
What is the source of truth for
whatever will be
the final result of the code that
is currently operating
and doing stuff in the environment.
Staging, sometimes called UAT or user
acceptance testing.
This is where we present changes,
we stage them to make them in production,
we pass them off to the customer
to say,
hey, are the changes that you asked
us to make
in this particular project complete
to your satisfaction
and do you approve of these changes
before we publish them into production
to make the money off of the software
that we are developing for you.
The develop branch is where most of
the engineering
is taking place.
This is where we've taken requirements
from the customer,
brought them into the engineering team,
identified what code changes need
to be made
and then publishing them on the develop branch
so that other engineers will be able
to test
and operate on them within this full
SDLC process
that we're gonna go over in a
future video.
I also like to set up the
premise of ticket branches
or feature branches because these
are short-lived branches
that will serve only a couple of commits
before making your changes and merging them
into the higher branches.
Because TikTok is so focused
on your short little attention span,
that's all you're gonna get for now.
You wanna learn more?
I've got another platform you can
go to check me out.
In the meantime, you're just gonna
have to watch
another video if you're gonna wanna see
how this process plays out.