So let's talk about Git, the stupid
content tracker.
Oh, and this isn't me making this up.
It's in the documentation itself.
That's what it's called.
And also a slight little correction
to myself
before I was calling it the stupid
file tracker.
It's actually called the stupid content tracker.
Apologies for that.
Recognize this from my last video?
If you don't, go check them out.
See, here's the thing.
The challenge that I face with most engineers
is they think Git is hard.
It's difficult to understand.
Yes, I understand there's a lot of
curves and turns,
but it's not that difficult
once you set yourself in a process,
get yourself in a routine,
and execute on some patterns
so that those wires that grow together
in your mind
will continue to build stronger and
get better
as far as how you control how
your code is edited.
So we'll start off with a basic premise
of we've got a new feature that's
coming in
or a new ticket that's come in,
and we need to make some changes
to that particular ticket
before they can be pushed back into
the develop branch
to get promoted to the upper environments.
So the idea is you branch from
the develop branch
into your ticket branch,
make your changes in that ticket branch,
and then merge them back into the
develop branch.
Now, if you're a cowboy, you can
just use git merge
because you're the only guy that's
working on the project,
so what do you need to do
the whole process for?
Now, if you're part of a development team,
what's going to need to happen,
at least for an efficient setup
that's going to lead you to the
best product possible,
is you open a pull request from
your ticket branch
into the develop branch.
What does the pull request do?
Well, it basically opens a conversation up
between you and the other engineers
for all of you to come together,
or however many of you needs to
come together
to review those changes
to ensure that they honor your coding standards
and also to ensure that the structure
of the code
matches what you need,
the business requirements have been met,
and everything that needs to be done
in this ticket
and whatever changes need to be implemented
have been done to satisfaction
by the local engineering team.
You merge that into the develop branch,
and we proceed on to the next
step in the SDLC process.
Similarly, for feature branches
that may include more than just a
couple of changes
or may involve just a few more discussions
than just a simple little quick ticket change,
sometimes you might be coming out
with a full-blown feature,
and this feature might need to be
broken down
into smaller components
so that those smaller pieces can be
executed on,
those changes can be made to the code,
they can be tested
and run through their own little mini process,
and then get merged back into the
develop branch
for the next parts that are gonna
come in the SDLC process.
SDLC is Software Development Lifecycle.
Thanks to TikTok's short-term attention span,
that's all you're gonna get for now.
Wanna know some more about how this
works in QA?
You're gonna have to subscribe
and go check out my other videos.