So let's talk about Git, the stupid
file tracker.
So if you don't know what Git is,
any of this or that and the other,
what's going on, I've never seen this before,
I have other videos, you should go
check those out.
I'm going to assume you've watched those
before you come to this one.
If not, save it for later, go
watch those,
come back, see this one.
Pause for now.
All right, great, thanks, we'll continue on.
So we're gonna talk about some basic
slash advanced concepts here.
When you make a change to your code,
you've been making your edits,
you've been making your updates,
you wanna share this with somebody else,
and so now you have your code
sitting in this repository.
You've committed your changes, you've
pushed, you've pulled,
you get the basic concepts of the Git
and how version control software works, VCS.
What now?
Well, this branching strategy.
You're gonna hear about this in development
because it is closely and heavily
tied to the SDLC,
or the software development lifecycle.
So in this video, we're gonna talk
about branching,
and specifically, what does that mean?
Because a branch is in your head.
A branch, like a tag, is an
annotation, a name of sorts,
that represents a line of changes
that we are making upon a particular
code base.
You have master, you have staging.
You may also have development,
and may also be a third branch.
I'm gonna cover that in a future video.
So as you are making changes to
your files,
and you run the command git commit,
you're basically creating little checkpoints
in time
where your code exists in that state,
at that time that you made that commit.
An entire full version copy of the code,
as it exists in this moment, exists
in that commit.
And you can make those commits
along these lines of changes.
Now, if you come into a situation
where you have two people
that want to contribute to a project,
and say they're making changes to
different sets of files,
and you want to keep them in sync,
but they may not be working on something
that is directly related to the same changes,
then what you can do is you
can create a separate branch
that you can use to stage your changes.
So you would then make your changes
to the staging branch.
Both of you would contribute and commit
to that branch.
And when you're ready to make a release,
you would take that and you would
merge it
into the master branch.
In this way, you will be able
to make changes
in a non-intrusive way that allows you
to make the changes on some other branch,
some other place where somebody else
isn't actively watching you making
those changes.
You can do that on a separate branch
and merge them on up into the
master branch.
So yep, I'm gonna cap it right there.
This is gonna be about merging.
Simply taking changes from a different line
of changes in a branch and you
merge that
into another branch.
Keep in touch, subscribe,
because I got more videos coming out.
I'm gonna play these in short form
so that you can get some really
quick content,
and then we'll just keep talking about
these subjects
until you're an expert.