So let's talk about Git, the stupid
content tracker.
Recognize this from my last video?
If you don't, go check him out,
you need to go see him.
If you do, you might notice some
stuff's missing here.
It's kinda cool.
So you've done the commit, you've
done the clone,
you've done the push, you've done
the pull,
you've done all these things in Git,
and now you understand just a little bit
about how the SDLC process works.
SDLC being the software development lifecycle.
Next steps is what happens in QA?
What happens when the engineers
have done all their coding things,
and what happens after that?
Well, one of the reasons why this
branching strategy
works so well is because no matter
how many ticket branches you have,
no matter how many features you have,
engineers and developers can constantly
pull from the develop branch to pull
those changes
into the ticket or feature that you're
working on,
and can push those changes back up
into the development stream,
where the other QA members can come
and snatch a version of that develop branch,
deploy it into an environment,
and either run automated testing about it,
around it, like Selenium,
or run manual testing around it,
where they actually load up the web browser,
or load up the environment,
click the buttons and do the things
in the code
to make sure that whatever business requirements
have been met effectively.
So as we are progressing along,
we've got all these tickets coming out,
making these changes,
and circling them back into the development environment,
what ends up happening is you build yourself
a really great cadence on how engineers
will be able to contribute changes
into the develop branch.
QA members can take those changes out,
create a snapshot out of it to say,
okay, out of this business case,
these things were tested,
I verified this works,
I verified this doesn't,
here's another ticket if I need to say
there's a bug in this particular setup,
here's how you can go to correct it,
this is what I did to reproduce it,
and that's another video I need to make,
but anyways.
And so now that the engineers have
had a chance
to go through and make the changes,
the QA team has had a chance
to go through
and do their testing,
the next step is to promote to
the staging branch,
sometimes also called UAT for user
acceptance testing.
This is where we take everything
that's been happening in the development line,
and promote it up to an environment
where we present it to the customer,
and we say, hey,
you gave us these business requirements,
you said you wanted these changes done
to your product, your site, your whatever,
did we get it right?
Did we manage the requirements?
Did we handle everything?
Can you go through your use cases?
And did you get what you asked for?
Customer then has an opportunity
to approve of the changes,
and at that point from staging,
changes get promoted to the master branch,
it releases cuts,
we're gonna cover that in our next video,
and if the customer declines and says,
no, you got this wrong,
you need to fix this,
can you move this over two pixels,
whatever, the customer can always
kick back,
and we just basically go through
this entire process all over again
to make sure that we complete the product
to the customer specification as per
their desires.
So yeah, thanks to TikTok's short
attention span,
that's all you're gonna get.
Wanna learn more?
Gonna have to subscribe.
Wanna see the next video and watch
us cut a release?
Gonna have to see the next video.