So let's talk about Git, the stupid
content tracker.
Recognize this from previous videos?
If you don't, you need to go
check them out, they're live.
So now that we've done the commit,
the push, the pull,
the merging, the develop branch, the
staging branch,
it's time to cut a release.
So the other thing that we need
to take into consideration
is we've taken our changes, our entire
SDLC process,
up until now, we've presented it to
the customer
and all the changes are now sitting
in staging.
We've done our pull requests,
we've had our conversations with the
engineering team,
they honor our coding standards,
they meet our business requirements,
the QA team has passed off on it.
QA, by the means, quality assurance.
We've done all these things.
Now, what we need to do is
we need to cut a release.
One of the things that I think
would be interesting
or important to understand is the
versioning process.
I see a lot of companies and
a lot of people
screwing around with this,
and this is one of those, please
don't reinvent the wheel.
Can we just agree on a standard
as far as versioning is concerned
and stick to that?
Chrome, Firefox, I'm looking at you.
Every time you do a major upgrade
of your versioning software,
I feel like you've completely rewritten
the entire code.
So let's break this down.
You have a major, you have a
minor, and you have a patch.
The major represents a significant change.
That means that whatever version of
this software
we are using is completely incompatible
with this other version of this software.
The major revision means that there
was a major rewrite,
an entire rewrite of the entire architecture
of all the code ever,
meaning you can take a 1.0
of a piece of software
and try to use it with a
version 2.0 of the data
or reverse, vice versa, whatever.
The result will be software
that completely cannot work with itself.
You'll have errors, you'll have all
kinds of problems.
Stop increasing the major
when the versions of the software
are in fact compatible with each other.
The minor revision is for whenever
you make changes
that are significant enough to bump
the version up.
It's more than a patch, less than
a complete rewrite.
It's a new feature, new ad, we've
got cool new things,
we've done some bug fixes or whatever,
but it's a significant amount of changes
that represents an increment of the
minor version
that is not a complete rewrite of
the major version.
And then finally, we have the patch version,
which is representative of some minor
bug fixes,
some little changes here and there,
some small little security updates maybe,
some, you know, for the most part,
software is compatible with itself
if the patch and the minor
are the only things that are incrementing.
If the major version of the software
is incrementing,
then to me, that just says
you completely rewrote the entire software.
And if you're incrementing this number
regardless of that,
then I have less respect for the
version number.
That's a lot of words to say
that whenever we cut a release,
we're basically taking a version and
tagging it in Git,
using git tag as the actual command
for that,
that will basically annotate the commit
that we've made
just before we publish to production
or as we're publishing to production,
however your setup goes.
So now that the customer has approved
of it,
you take your changes from your staging branch,
you merge them into the master branch,
and then you tag the results so
you know,
hey, this was the version of the software
that last went to production
whenever we decided that the customer
agreed on it,
we agreed on it, everybody's happy,
we're good to go.
All right, push it out, let's go.
And so now that I've made it
to the end of this,
and if you've made it this far,
thank you so much.
And congratulations, you're now an
expert in Git
from the client side perspective anyways.
And I wanna get some feedback from you.
Team movie or team episode?
Here on TikTok, I do team episode
where I do two or three minute blurbs,
we talk about one simple thing,
and I try to condense it down
into a small little segment.
Did that short term attention span
thing work for you?
Or would you rather another platform
where you can learn from me in
more elongated content?
Let's just say 10 or 15 minutes
might be a reasonable time
to explain something like this
so that you can understand the basic concepts.
What are your thoughts?
Let me know, comment below, curious.