So let's talk about hacking and security.
Now before we get started, I want
to make
sure you understand that Kizanos Fintech
does not condone the use of hacking to
steal some company's information,
to deal damages to another person,
to perform
damage to IP or to some other
company. Please hack ethically outside
of the
context of a contractual agreement
between you and the entity where you
have their express permission to perform
the operations discussed in this video.
Don't do anything illegal. Don't be
dumb. Don't do anything you're not
supposed to.
This is for edutainment purposes only.
But first, black tourmaline has properties
of the earth, is attuned to the
root chakra, can purify your space,
and also
dons purification of the energies
around you. It's a great traveling
companion and
one of my favorite stones. Fascinating,
isn't it? So how does a website get
hacked, you might be wondering. Well,
you know this login screen accepts
user input.
And if someone's not careful and doesn't
validate their input and escape their
output before they take these text
boxes and go and query the database, oftentimes
people find SQL injections inside
of these text boxes. Because a lot
of the
times people don't take the time to
make sure that their output that's being
that's coming from untrusted sources
is sanitized and actually represents the
data that they expect it to be.
A lot of times hackers will go
and find these
inputs and have scripts that automatically
go and attempt to inject
them with input that the application
wasn't expecting. So if as a software
engineer you are not vigilant as far
as making sure that untrusted information
is sanitized and cleansed before sending
it off to another source, you could be
opening yourself up for exploit. And
we all know and are probably quite annoyed
with that captcha box that checks
to make sure that you're actually human.
Well, that's there to make sure that
robots aren't able to continuously poke
at the login page to see if
they can try and authenticate. Because
bots can't tell
what those pictures are. And so this
is a mechanism that is used to
ensure that
someone can't brute force your login.
Because if you don't put some kind of
barrier in place to make it difficult
or rather to increase the cost of attack
of trying to guess at someone's password,
they can sit there and poke at
your site
all day long and you'll be none
the wiser and eventually find a way
to get in.
And we all know about these arduous
forms that tediously require us to
enter this information in over and
over again. Boy, I can't wait till
we get one
touch off where you just say bink
and you know information is shared
with who
you specifically authorize, when you
specifically authorize them, and for how
long they get that access. But until
that day comes around, we still got
these text
boxes to fill in. Did you know
that these text boxes are also a
treasure trove for hackers? They love
to find these inputs. Why? Because
it allows
them to poke at the site and
see what more can they do. Because
if I can get
your database to dump the contents
of the user database table right here on
the page, that's a treasure trove
of information right there. If I can get
your site to spit out a stack
trace and show me where the files
are on the file
system, that's more information I
can use in my reconnaissance to better
understand the lay of the land within
your current setup. If I can take these
inputs and make your server do something
that it wasn't intended to do, especially
if I could take text from these
boxes and put it into some kind
of execution
space. Because people sometimes love
to take input from users and run
it inside
of an eval function or evaluate, which
basically says take any string and
execute it as code. That's extremely
dangerous for unsanitized and unverified
input from the end user. Why? Because
I can get your server to go
and download a
malicious package and infect your
site. I can convince your server to
go out and do
things on your behalf and it will
look as if it's coming from your
website. Now
you're blacklisted. Now Google thinks
you're a hacked website. Now you get the
red banner at the top of the
site or completely blocked altogether because
you're not on the safe browsing list.
So let's say a hacker got access
to your
server. They've got a compromise now.
They found a way to get into your
application and get it to execute
some code that it wasn't expecting.
Let's say
there's a server out there that it
already has access to. They've already
compromised this server. What happens
next? They can say, hey server, my new
minion, I want you to go and
download some infected software that
I've got
control of. And this software is going
to give me more access to your
systems. So if
you have a fleet of servers that
are sitting inside of your network
and one
of them gets compromised and now they've
got control over it, they can go
and get
control to the rest of those servers
as well. From this point they can
do a
network scan to see what that server
can see as far as its internal
network is
concerned. So even though you may
be behind a VPC, even though this particular
server may be segmented off from the
rest of the network, the servers that are
inside of that local network are still
possible to be compromised. This software
that they've downloaded can now start
a crypto miner and use and abuse the
resources available to your system.
It can deface your website such that any
time somebody comes to visit it, they
also get infected with malware. Be
it on
mobile, desktop, any kind of client
that comes and accesses the server could
become infected because it touched
the infected server. Now what does that
infected part mean? It means code
executed outside of the context that it
was designated to execute. So even
though the program was running inside
of the
application on a server, somewhere
in that program it evaluated a string
and it
broke execution context. And so now
the application, that string that
the hacker
fed into the application told it,
gave it the instructions it needed
to go and do
something it wasn't supposed to. So
this is why things like protection against
cross-site scripting or cross-site
request forgery are important tactics to
make sure that you use to protect
yourself against exploit on the
website's side. This is why the networking
team is critical to ensure security
against exploits because firewalls
and other network partitions can prevent
stuff like this from happening. Even
though port 80 and 443 are open, you
should also have an application firewall
or even an outbound firewall to prevent
your application, if it is compromised,
from compromising things even further.
And this is why in my networks
I always run a two-way firewall.
It's not just
input, but also output. And so if
I see something from within my network
reaching out to some place like China,
Russia, another country, a known hacked
server, something's wrong. Something's
wrong. And I've seen my internal firewalls
block outbound traffic, preventing
me from getting infected further.
So it's
important to keep that in mind as
well. Network partitioning and segregating off
your servers such that only your application
servers would be impacted.
Can you imagine if the database sat
in the same location and that server got
compromised as well? If they got access
to the database and not talking about
just talking to the database as a
client, like a MySQL client or a
MongoDB client,
I'm talking about SSH or getting root
access to the server behind the database.
That's a very dangerous situation
as well. We want to avoid that
by making
sure that we validate our input, sanitize
and escape our output, make sure
firewalls are in place to protect
our systems so that people can't just
willy-nilly connect to services that
may be running on our servers. An application
firewall that understands the input
that's being received, so that if
it were
to perceive an injection attack or
some kind of cross-request forgery
attack, the
application firewall itself would
be intelligent enough to be able to figure
that out and would better be able
to protect your application from exploits.
Hi, my name is Marc-Isano Draconis
and I run Kizano's fintech channel
where I
take you from zero to master in
IT and DevOps. But did you also
know I'm a
licensed massage therapist in Dallas,
Texas? If you're looking for a holistic
alternative to health and well-being,
you can go to massage.marcisano.net
where you can schedule a massage with
me today. If you use the coupon code
RELAX2023 before the end of this month,
I'll give you $10 off your next massage.
I look forward to seeing you on
the table.