If you're trying to get into information
security, let's talk about XSS
(Cross-Site Scripting).
Cross-site scripting is whenever perfectly
benign, otherwise trusted websites
that seem
perfectly fine to visit end up sending
infections to your own workstation.
This can allow your website, even
if it is perfectly legit, even though
it is perfectly
fine, even though it is trusted, can
end up becoming detrusted or untrusted
because you
end up serving malicious code.
That's a big no-no.
Remember that page we did on URLs?
Well, just imagine that URL has instructions
to tell your computer to give the
hacker your
IP address, the internals of your
network, it might even poke at a
couple of systems
within your local setup that you have
going on there and send a nice
little payload of
that information right off to the
hacker server so he knows exactly
how to attack you next.
You know those WYSIWYG text boxes?
Well, anyways, we call them WYSIWYG
because "what you see is what you get".
And that text box that's got all
that pre-formatted stuff inside of
it, well... let's just say
I had a little fun with the
University of Phoenix before they
knew that this was a thing.
Or, they knew.
It was part of the classes.
They had to know.
I told them.
And I managed to get the text
box to store script data, so whenever
this rendered back
on the screen, it would alert with
your cookies and your login data.
And I could optionally have it send
that information to my server if I
wanted to get
access to one of the teacher's consoles.
That was a scary prospect, and I
tried telling them about this.
And it wasn't until I told somebody
who knew somebody who knew somebody
who was in on the
developments that it actually got fixed.
That's a scary, scary prospect there.
I mean, can you imagine visiting your
favorite website and then it suddenly
just start
acting all kind of funky?
Yeah, I'd be kind of creeped out too.
So that's why you want to protect
against cross-site scripting.
And the way you do this is
to validate your input, escape your output.
Any information that comes in from
the user, assume it is tainted.
Assume that it can't be trusted.
Assume that it already has those scripts
inside of it.
How do you disarm them?
Well, first, if you're expecting a
phone number, validate against a phone
number regular
expression.
If you're expecting an email, validate
against an email regular expression.
Same thing with IP address.
Same thing with names.
Same thing with phone book addresses.
There's postal validation systems
out there that you can take the
postal address, send
it off to USPS, FedEx, UPS, they
all got APIs, and you can verify
that that postal address
exists, is valid, and can be delivered.
And then, now that you've validated
the information, you're going to escape
the output before you
print to any other stream, meaning,
if you write to the database, you
use reserve placeholders
to indicate this is data, or properly
using the escape functions that will
take any characters
that represent special characters
and automatically escape them out.
MySQL, I'm looking at you.
This is why I love MongoDB.
I don't have to worry about escaping
data because it's stored as the data
structure itself.
If you're going to print to HTML,
make sure you use HTML entities to
escape output so
that it appears as entities, not as
the raw characters themselves.
We don't want those script tags showing
up in the output.
We do, but we want to see
the script tags, not have them hidden
and the scripts execute
in the background.
If you have output that's being spit
out to CSS, the same rules apply.
Escape for CSS because there's stuff
that can happen in just decorating
a page.
Can you imagine the remote exploits
that are available for trying to request
an image?
That was a little fast.
Let's run through that one more time.
User input, bad.
We take it, we validate it.
You can sanitize it, that's optional.
Then you escape it before it goes
anywhere else.
So we take our data, we make
sure it's what we expect it's going
to be, and then before
we print to any stream outside of
that, we want to make sure that
we escape it, meaning
the backslash, the quotes, whatever
that is.
It's different per something you're
talking to, be it the browser as
HTML, be it the database
as SQL, as NoSQL, as whatever solution
you're using.
The whatever third-party API, if you're
sending things off to them, you want
to make sure
you URL encode, JSON encode, YAML
encode, however you want to do it.
Curious, what techniques have you
used to protect against cross-site scripting?