Alright, I thought this was funny,
had to share!
But to give a fuck is not
the same as having a fuck.
But to fuck is follar.
But if you fuck, then you joder.
Pero si tu jodas, then you're fucking
with me.
Si estas follandome, then it's a good time.
Pero no me jodas is not to
fuck with me.
Pero no me follas means no.
Pasando el rato follando is a good afternoon.
But if you're haciendo joder, then
you gotta be kidding me.
Joder macho is like fucking man, but
it still doesn't translate right...
Cojer can be to choose or to fuck.
Pero cojer a cojer is to choose
to fuck, right?
But no, that would be elegir a
follar, si/no?
Fuck can be used in all eight
forms of speech in English.
Is it the same in other languages?
What is that one word of your
language that has all parts of speech available?