So, let's talk about the etymology
behind my name, because I see a
lot of people
messing this up, and I'm like, it's
not that difficult, is it? Two letters
at a time, right? I don't know. We'll see.
We'll find out.
Yeah, that's my government name.
It's boring. One syllable: Mark.
I mean, sure, it makes it easy to
remember, but
I'm always a little bit more. Now,
an extension to that could be Markiz or
Marcus. There's two different spellings.
I didn't really like Marcus. I like
Markiz because of the Z. It's kind
of fun drawing it out, too. Get
that little line
down the middle. Sometimes it might
be there, might not be there. I
also didn't
like Marcus because it was, likewise,
too common. If it was, you know,
tried to be
used as a username, it wouldn't work.
So, I tried Markiz because
it's an uncommon spelling and possibly
could be unique to me, right? So,
I added
the last part and made it Markizano.
And, typically, how languages work, the
accent typically falls on the second
to last syllable. So, Markizano. You
can also
put an accent over the "A" as
well to say there's an emphasis on
the Mark part
because it is an extension of my
first name. Draconus. I don't know
where people
are getting the "I" from. It's not
Draconius. I'm sorry. I don't see it, where do you?
Draconis is an extension of Draco,
which represents dragon. That is my Chinese
zodiac and I definitely align with
this, with all the personality traits.
I'm quick with the tongue, incredibly
intelligent, incredibly powerful.
I have,
you know, this kind of complex in
my head. But, I'm also compassionate
and willing
to learn and always try to adapt
to new things and with psychic abilities. So,
that's a quick little etymology or
history of my name in two minutes.
Markizano Draconus.