Did you know, storage and memory,
they're not the same thing.
As far as the insides of your
computer is concerned, storage is
where long-term information
is stored.
This is where you get to download
your files and your memories reside
in your mind from
last winter and COVID and all these things.
Did you know that memory is where
information must be loaded from disk
before it can do
anything inside of a computer?
Yeah, and they used to call it
RAM, which stands for Random Access Memory.
If you're looking for hardware chips,
that's what you'll be looking for
at least anyways.
Yes, information is loaded from disk
to memory, and this can be a
really expensive operation.
I mean, this can cost a lot
of time in a computer program.
And then we wonder why we get
that loading screen all the time.
Once things finally do make it into
memory, they get processed by the
processor, the CPU,
the central processing unit.
Some say this is the brain of
the computer, but I like to think
of it as the active tubules
that go off.
The brain of the computer, in my
head, is at least in the kernel
where the decisioning
is being made in the software.
The CPU is kind of sort of
like the hardware rails that represents
what the capacity of
the computer could do, similarly to
a person.
If I put a program in there
that only uses a couple of seconds
of CPU cycles, well, it
doesn't matter how powerful that CPU
is, that program is only going to
consume that much.
So I must create a program that
must consume the full capacity of
that processor if I'm
going to take advantage of the hardware
that has been given to me.
And then of course there's the GPU,
the graphics card.
This is typically responsible for
rendering what happens inside of your
screen as far
as your graphics is concerned, however,
we're starting to find a lot more
uses for these
things since they have an incredibly
dense computing capacity.
I think mining AI and gaming are
just the tip of the iceberg as
far as what this kind
of computing power could bring to us.
Yeah, memory and storage are not the
same thing, so if you're wondering
why you're being
corrected, now you know.