So, let's talk about how the inside
of your computer works.
See, a lot of people kind of
sort of have this misconception.
They seem to think that storage and
memory is all the same thing, when
in reality, it
isn't.
Let's get into that.
Storage is what is stored on disk,
and if I were to equate this
to how a human was to
behave, I would say it's your long
-term storage.
This is what you remember from your
past, from last winter, COVID, those
kinds of things.
Anytime you're needing to recall that
information in order to recite some
kind of speech you
may have recorded, or these words
that I'm speaking right now, as I
try to present this
information to you, that's information
that's stored in those frontal lobes,
where you
keep that information local, quick
and easy to access, and it doesn't
require much thought
for you to be able to come
off the top of the head for
these kinds of things.
That's what's called your memory,
or your RAM, random access memory.
Information that's stored long time
when the computer is turned off is
stored on the disk.
Information that is stored within
the memory disappears when the computer
gets turned off.
That information is not preserved.
Why?
It's because it's stored based on
electricity circuits that are being
kind of sort of cached
or held within a low latency diode
inside of the chip itself.
These actually store bits that can
be, you know, magnetically retrieved
later, and the
way this...
Alright, I'm getting too technical.