So, let's talk about how your computer works.
This is really fascinating because
computers act and behave, or actually,
computers were
made in man's image a lot more
similarly than you'd think.
Let's imagine you have your computer here.
And a lot of people get this wrong.
They, you know, think storage and
memory, it's all the same stuff, right?
No, it's not.
Storage, what's on disk, is completely
different than what is in memory.
You may have noticed from older sessions
that it is called RAM, which stands
for Random
Access Memory.
And that's because it's a mess up
here trying to figure out what's going
on inside of this
thing.
You can think of it this way,
storage, this is what is stored for
long term.
This is those memories that you have
from, you know, winter of last year,
or COVID, or
the last presidential election, or,
you know, some things that it seems
like a lot of people
seem to be missing is, you know,
the ability to store information and
save it for later.
And be able to recall that information
into your memory banks.
And this is where you're maybe working
in some finance, you may be working
with some
numbers, you may be in some Excel
workbook, and you've got a view of
all these tables
and columns and stuff, a visual representation
of that in your head, in your
memory, in your
RAM, your random access location,
where all that information is stored
in immediate recall,
that frontal part of your brain that
says, okay, I got it, right?
Right there.
Right?
Let's say you switch context.
Let's say you changed apps on your
phone, that app, the state of its
being the fact
that it's been, you know, read off
the disk, all the configuration has
been read off the
disk, the binary information is now
inside of the memory.
To write all that information back
to the disk would be extremely expensive.
You see, there's a cost factor here.
RAM is really, really, really, really,
really fast.
Like nanosecond, one, two, three nanoseconds
it takes to read and write information off
of RAM.
The disk, however, can take anywhere
between two, three hundred milliseconds
and more.
So it's really expensive to take information
from RAM and transfer it back and
forth from
the disk.
So what do we do?
We open up files on the file
system, or have different places,
different chips, different
spaces where you can cache that information.
So after the information has been
read from the disk, processed by the
processor, stored
within the memory, information can
also be stored in cache, and that's
what that is.
Post-compiled information that's been
read from other places that can be
stored on disk
because it's not considered the authoritative
source of truth.
I just need a copy of this
data stored in some place where I
can get access to it later without
consuming a whole bunch of other resources
and processes trying to write that
data back
to disk.
This is why you can have a
device that's got 16 gigabytes of
memory and a terabyte's worth
of storage.
This is also why IT people might
be getting upset with you over the
fact that you don't
clarify the difference between storage
and memory.
It's not the same.