Here is your Linux command of
the day.
`cmatrix`
That's pretty cool, isn't it?
Ha ha ha.
Did you know you can pipe
the output
of any other command into lolcat?
and you get this amazing glorified
rainbow unicorn output?
Isn't that just amazing?
Ha ha ha.
Hey, wait a minute....
Wait a minute, wait a minute,
wait a minute....
It's Fruity Pebbles matrix.
Hey, wait, there's this other command
called fortune.
It tells you your fortune.
But there's this other command called
cowsay.
Where you can have a cow,
pretty much prints ASCII text
that says any word.
Hey, wait a minute.
Ha ha ha ha ha ha.
Oh my.
All right, here's for the finale.
This one, this one's gonna blow
your socks off.
Wait, no, I need to get
the audio set right.
This is crazy.
So here's my number.
So call me maybe.
Now that's, ha ha ha ha
Ah, that's absolutely crazy
right there.