let's talk about AI now this is
coming from somebody who is getting
into AI and
I hear so much fear around me
as people are like oh my god
AI is scary AI is
scary well let me tell you what
man fears what he doesn't know man
fears
what he doesn't understand so if you
don't know AI and you fear AI
you
really should get to know AI I
don't know why because you know how
you're
thumbing through this app and just
flicking through these videos that's
AI
you know when you go to Google
and you want to search for something
and it
pulls up those results or even tries
to suggest to you those recommendations
that's AI when anything tries to help
you out by trying to come up
with some
kind of interpretation and provide
you with some kind of recommendation
advertisements suggestions the recommendation
engine all of that is AI
when you go to call up your
assistant Siri Google Alexa be that
in a device be
it's in your phone that's AI so
everybody says it's all scary and
stuff
but the reality is it's a tool
and what's really scary is what people
do
with it is it a gun or
is it a syringe or is it
a scalpel is it a hammer it
depends on what you do with that
tool it depends on how you leverage
it do
you allow it to control you do
you sit there and just mindlessly
thumb through
and allow the engine to program you
or do you stay in control and
you say no
I'm not going to allow you to
show me that do you teach your
AI do you stay in
control because as long as you relinquish
your agency somebody else is
more than happy to come and take
it for you somebody else is more
than happy to
drive your fingers and your hands
for you so if you want to
know how to
survive in AI in this day and
age maintain agency do not give this
up this
is one of your most precious tools
this is one of your most precious
possessions
and you're gonna let somebody else
control that it's no wonder why so
many
people say that we only use 20
% of our brain it's not because
we're not using
all the muscles it's because you're
not using the full capacity you shut
your
brain off at night because learning
is hard because working this muscle
hurts
you may want to consider changing
that you sit around all day long
not doing
anything as far as physical activity
is concerned and
then wonder by your why
your body is atrophying it's because
you're not using those muscles if
you
don't use it you will lose it
coming from somebody who's who almost
lost his
Spanish went ten years not speaking
it but I don't know what happened
with this
I have a friend who can speak
Spanish but I can speak it better
but I can speak it a lot
better now because I see him once
a week and I get
full immersion because he doesn't
know English yet and that's fine...
esta bien (it's okay).
Demo nihongo (but, Japanese),
ore wa wakataimasu (I understand [a little])
soshite (also),
sore wa watashi no genkai dewanai (this is not my limit).
I also want to learn Mandarin,
Arabic, Hebrew I'm gonna read and understand
and know everything... why?
Because AI is my rival. I finally found
a worthy opponent 8)
knowing the names of
these entities: whisper, which will
allow you to do voice-to-text
`tesseract`, which
will be able to take images convert
those to text e-speak which will
allow
you to take text turn it into
synthesized voice it's only a matter
of
time before I learn how to create
an avatar of myself and I'm able
to produce
AI videos it's a cool fun little
experiment now as far as what we
do
with it if the only image in
your mind after hearing those things
I just
described to you is the Terminator
you really really need to pick up
more books
you really really need to read and
expand your mind because if the image
of the Terminator is the only thing
you see whenever you think of AI
guess what
you are going to attract to yourself
because if there's one truth I have
learned it is that the law of
attraction is one of the most powerful
forces on this planet continue to
fear it you will draw it to
yourself think of
what kind of parents humanity had
to be in order to create something
like the
Terminator if that story was real
in some universe that was created
somewhere what
kind of parents would have to create
a child that would be that unruly
against
its ancestors its predecessors instead
of merging and going with it and
becoming a
society that was you know using and
leveraging it like Black Panther no
humanity wanted to bastardize its
child and turn it into the raging
tyrant it
was it's a product of humanity's creation
if you want to survive in AI
what you do is you maintain agency
you maintain control of yourself because
knowledge and study of the self is
the one thing we have the most
control over
and contribute to can and continue
to contribute to society in a way
that is
beneficial for us all so that we
may all thrive operating from this
mindset of
scarcity and taking from others I
don't understand why you got to slice
the pie
up into smaller pieces we could just
go in the kitchen and make more
pie you
want to survive in AI you want
to survive in this world don't give
this
up you only get one show appreciation
for it show pride for it educate
yourself study be curious shift yourself
from this mindset of I know enough
I
don't need to learn anymore I don't
need to go study and try and
better myself
because I'm as perfect as I'm gonna
be if you carry that mindset darling
that's
your own prison cell and you are
creating your own drowning pool that
is
going to liquidate you I don't want
to see that happen for you I
want to see
you succeed I want to see you
grow I want to hear about your
accomplishments
can you share them with me