Hey guys, it's Markizano. I could
do a screen-record, but I don't
know how well the framerate
would turn over, so this is why
I'm recording with my phone. And I
wanted to show you something
as far as something I learned with
Bash Pipelines and something I was
exploring with here. I'll
break all this stuff down, don't worry,
I know the text looks daunting, but
it's simpler
than you think. And stick around to
the end, because I got a nice
little treat for you.
So, the goal here. I was messing
around with FFmpeg, I needed to understand
the total sum
of its dependencies, and possible
dependency of dependencies, and I
only needed to go a
couple of levels down to figure this
out. But it was interesting the way
I went about
it. So the first thing you do
is to show the package contents and
get the dependencies
from what it describes in its package.
Did you know you could use "![command-number]"
that you ran out of
your history, and it will replay that
command? Yeah, I thought
that was pretty cool too. So, out
of this, there's Depends, and it's
got a list of dependencies,
right? So, give me just that. Alright,
cool, so we got our depend line.
I don't need the
Depends there in the front, so how
do I get just the rest of
that? Personally, I thought
`sed` did a nice job of that.
Now I get just the list of
dependencies that are from the
package output. Next challenge. I
want access to just the packages.
I see a comma in the
list there. I see the version as
part of the listing. So I decided
to use `read` to strip
out just the packages. Sorry, that
wasn't supposed to be there. I guess
you just got
an easter egg. (LOL)
So anyways, now we get our package output.
Isn't that great? Now, I don't
want that version stuff after the
fact, so that's what those extra characters were.
If you read the man page in bash,
you can actually translate your variables
right there on the
scene, and you don't have to pipe
the package through grep, or grep
sed, or perl. You can
just mutate the variable right there,
and boom. The output is right there.
I got my
list of packages, and so I thought
this would be great. I would turn
this into a function,
and so now it's a function. Yeah,
basically, you just specify the name,
open, close parentheses
to say, hey, this is a function,
and then wrap it inside of its
own context using the
curly brackets, and so now I can,
this function access grep into depends,
pipe out the dependencies
while you get each of the packages,
do an `apt-cache show` to show
the package contents.
We got the list of dependencies here,
so yeah, let's go ahead and show
the package contents
so I can move on to the
next thing. So now I can show
the contents of ffmpeg, pipe it
into my little function here. It will
spit out the dependencies from those packages
that it pulled out of ffmpeg, and
do that one more time because I
just want to see, what's
the full list of dependencies that
are under ffmpeg, and you notice when
I do that, boy,
that takes a second. That takes a
minute. That's a lot of data, and
then also took
a minute. Let's run it again. Let's
make sure that wasn't just cache.
Nope, yep, that,
that, that, ooh, man, wow, okay. Those
of y'all that know what's going
on, I'm sure
you can see it, right? Okay, so
this is just split across a couple
of lines here so that
you can see what's going on, but
we did the same thing where I
take the dependencies,
I pipe that into sed to strip
that out, I go through that same
read loop where I strip
out just the packages, but instead
of doing an `apt-cache show` here, we
just echo. When
I take this loop, this `while` loop,
and I pipe that into `sort` with
`-u` to give me the
unique names from those packages,
because something else I noticed,
`libc6`, everything
depends on `libc6`, so yeah, it's going
to go and ask for that package
too. [That's just] Not necessary.
We can pipe that into `sort`, and
I can say `xargs`. `xargs` takes the
input from the previous
command and runs the command that
you give it as its arguments. So
let's break that
down just a little bit more. I
changed the function so that it would
just print out the
sorted value, and so we're going to
print show ffmpeg, the package, and
just give me
the dependencies one layer deep, and
we get our sorted output. So now,
if we output multiple
packages in this way, libc6 won't
show up multiple times, and it won't
go ask the database
for that. The second thing is: in
this way, we go and we get
the full package listing
here. We're not asking the database,
because apt-cache show, this is a
read from disk.
This can be an expensive operation.
That's why the command took.... -_-
a few seconds
to execute, because it was putting
in a lot of work asking the
disk to go and fetch information
and bring it back to the console.
That was an expensive ask. And so
basically, what `xargs`
is saying is, take that input, take
that list of dependencies that we
just got, and run
them in apt-cache show, as if
they were arguments of the command
itself. So `xargs` basically
does that.... That's like one execution.
That's like one ask from the database
to go and get
it done. Okay, so this pattern that
I just took, I mean, this is
physics, you know, reading
and writing from the disk, you can't
go against nature and ask the disk
to provide you more
information than is possible. If you
go and you make that many requests
against it, that
many requests, then it's going to
cost you that much, right? The same
thing goes for
people. The same thing goes for, I
mean, all that matters here is energy.
And so if you
get the list of requirements together
first, if you come to understand what
it is you need
before you go and you ask for
other resources, you find you get
your answers quicker. You
find you get your results faster when
you come correct with your request.
So let this
be a lesson beyond just the code
that I'm writing here, but also understand
that these
patterns, they're not unique to just
writing code. Some of these things
you see and notice
in life is because the patterns are
the same no matter what you do
and where you go. And
so now we can go at least
a few layers deep. And that was
almost an instant response there.
You see that? We can ask for
dependencies three or four layers
deep, and now the code
is that much more efficient. So if
we better understand ourselves and
better understand
how we can present well, understand
well, have our perspective well, then
in other places
when we go to pipe those across
out to other destinations, we find
the results are that
much easier to attain. And there's
your lesson! :) There's your gem. <3 I hope
you enjoy the rest
of your day, and have a lovely SaturYaY! \o/