Artificial intelligence is killing
software engineering and coding jobs?
And I agree with him
Oh, yeah, by the way, happy Sunday
Funday y'all and tattoo got finished. =)
I'm really proud of that
They got colored in lovely. So yeah,
nobody's complaining about missing
their horse and buggy
Nobody's complaining about missing
their rotary phone. Nobody wishes
that we had our you know, the
Cart with the horse attached to it
like just like the automobile completely
changed that industry
Just like the internet completely
revolutionized our ability to communicate
and connect with each other in ways.
We have never seen before
So also has social media introduced
problems with emotional intelligence
So too has AI introduced security
exploits where I can trick it to
send me the raw information for Sam
Bankman Freid's
actual information
Sorry SBF was crypto and that was
so last year. :rolling_eyes: I'm sorry Sam Altman
But yeah, I mean there's just all
this, you know fear-mongering talk
about "oh my god
AI is going to replace the jobs"...
What jobs?
But the ones that don't serve? What
jobs but the ones we don't want
to repeat and do the same thing
over and over again...
There are jobs that I have automated
people out of with just the code
that I've written as a software engineer
as a System
Administrator. There is this guy that
would go and download a report
Look at the report for some certain
details and then upload what he got
from the report and send it up
to somewhere else...
I mean, it was the dumbest thing
in the world
He was like fresh out of college
and you know
He was good for that job for
like the six months
It took me to write the code
to automate him out of the position
and then he eventually got you know
Moved on to other things but the
idea, you know people talking about
AI is gonna you know, trash all
these jobs
Guess what code has been doing that
the Internet has been doing that everything
else has been changing the job landscape
for years...
decades... (10 years) centuries (100 years).
It's change. It's happening and
There's nothing you can do about it
any of us it's going to happen
It's just a matter of how do
you incorporate that into your life?
What matters is what are you doing
specifically to accomplish your goals?
For example, I
thought this picture was beautiful.
I managed to get Stable Diffusion
installed on my local workstation
And oh my god, that is just gorgeous
now imagine me being able to write
the story about Markizano Draconus and
helping you better understand what's
going on behind the scenes and why
I go by this name
because it's something like a middle
-earth sci-fi tech like it's a
story that meshes all these things together
Now with AI I don't have to
hire somebody to go in and do
all this expensive stuff
because I know I'm not easy to
work with and
I know that it's gonna take a
lot of time for me to refine
the thoughts that are going on inside
in my head because
It's my story not theirs
I also get to publish the story myself
and don't have to deal with copyright
writers and other people in my business
talking about we need to
get the sales. We need to get
the sales. You need to write the
story this way. It's like, no
I want to write the story that's
entertaining. I want to write the
story that comes from the mind.
I want to write the story that
comes from /my/ mind and the videos
that you see me post on TikTok
where it says it's been
Auto-captioned by whisper that was
me downloading AI to my local workstation
So I don't have to use CapCut
or pay for somebody else to subtitle
my stuff!
So, yeah
It's going to replace jobs and it's
going to enable people who are capable
who are
Willing to dip into AI and use
it as a tool rather than fear
it like... I don't know
Just fear... Why I don't understand why
fear is so prominent. I get it.
It's unknown
But guess what: you get to walk
right up to it. You get to
read the manuals. The stuff is open source
It's accessible for anybody to access.
There's nothing stopping you from
getting into this stuff
using this rather than fearing it.
So don't fall for the hype. Don't
fall for the bullshit
Go read the docs! RTFM! You'd
be surprised -- you'd be shocked
just how easy it is to understand
the stuff if you just took the
time to do it. A
majority of the time and the majority
of the people that I come across
in life who talk about I'm not
a technology person
I can't understand that stuff. Oh
my god, that's way over my head.
I know nothing about that bullshit
Sit down and read it for about
20 minutes...
Stick with it for 20 hours... I
promise you just being exposed to
it. Just watching my videos. My friends
have become enlightened on IT and how other
stuff works and it's not like they
have to be some kind of expert
in it.
I mean just having the visibility
into how things work
It does amazing wonders for the mind
So don't allow you yourself nor
your mind to be ruled by that
which is evil and that is the
negativity and the fear the things
that keep you from accomplishing your
goals, child for you are capable! You
are worthy. You have value
and
I believe in you
That's what that means. 8)