In the last couple of days,
I've been able to become more
efficient with Whisper and
the AI tools that are available
at my disposal, far more efficiently
than I could ever possibly
hope to achieve with CapCut.
If you notice, my video output
production has dramatically increased.
The quality of the videos has
also improved as well.
This is because I'm getting more
efficient with my tools using FFmpeg
and creating an
app that will automatically translate
a JSON description of what I
want to do with the
video into instructions that FFmpeg
will go and execute on.
And then I have a voice-to-text
command that will go
and take my video, automatically caption
it into an SRT file, and
then inscribe that SRT file directly
into the video.
This allows me to create videos
with automatic captions, and I'm starting
to put disclaimers
at the top of the video
saying, hey, this video has been
automatically captioned by
Whisper.
CapCut, this is a challenge to
you.
If you can make your interface
so delicious that I can't avoid
using it, that it's so
good that I can't help but
use it, if you can improve
your caption editor, because I'm
one of the few people that
actually do go through and edit
my captions, if you can make
that process simple, then I might
be more apt to using your
application more often.
If you can provide additional support
for Linux and make it such
that the web browser
doesn't freeze and seize up such
that I can't even edit a
simple 30-second video, then I
might be more apt to use
your application.
One of the reasons why I
love FFmpeg so much is because
the application does not crash.
There's no chance of the application
just seizing up because it failed
to render some
sprites in order to put them
on the screen and display them
accordingly.
I've been able to become more
efficient with plain text documents
and plain text descriptions
on what I want the video
to do.
The only benefit CapCut gives me
is the visual timeline editor, but
that's okay.
Being a text guy, I keep
that kind of stuff in my
head.
So the next challenge for you,
CapCut, is to see what you
can do to make your application
that much more juicy, that much
more delicious, that I can't help
but use your product.
In the meantime, my process is
amazing.
I record my video, I upload
them to my laptop, I inscribe
a couple of instructions to clip
out the pieces I need, put
the animations in place, I can
animate things almost as good
as CapCut now, and the captions
get automatically encoded in the video
as well.
Hardly any work on my part.
This is absolutely amazing.
And for those of you that
are catching on and picking up
on some of the stuff that
I'm putting down,
just know, as time
goes on, it's going to get
better.
Thank you so much for following,
and I look forward to teaching
you a helluva of a lot more!