So let's talk about technical acronyms.
Let's see if you can name how
many of
these acronyms mean what they mean.
USB: Think you know this one?
Universal Serial Bus.
Seems like Apple just recently picked up on the "universal" aspect of that...
TCP and UDP:
Think you know what these ones mean?
Drop a comment below if you do.
Transport* Control Protocol
and User Datagram Protocol.
I bet you hear that all the time and you're like...
"What does that mean???"
How about HTTP?
I know you know this one, right?
It stands for Hypertext Transfer Protocol.
This is the rules by which we
transmit information over HTTP.
Oh yeah, and the "S" means secure.
What about HTML and CSS?
I mean...
those things like make a web page,
but like
what do they mean?
HTML is just plain text that has been
hypertext markup language.
Which is basically,
text that's kind of sort of been dressed up
with a few tags here and there
that make it a little bit more structured.
They give it
something it can stand on.
Cascading Style Sheets are the descriptions
that you can associate with HTML
in order to represent
how you want it to look.
Make it look pretty.
Hmm, this one should be an easy one, right?
HDD?
You know it was hard disk drive, right?
Okay, so we hear about IP addresses all the time,
but like... what are they?
Did you know they were Internet Protocol addresses?
Teeing off of HDD,
can you guess what SSD is?
That's your solid state drive.
They're typically faster than your hard disk drives,
because, well...
the storage mechanisms are different.
Continuing down that line,
you've got to know what NVMe stands for, right?
If you did, you're better than me.
I had to look this one up.
It stands for Non-Volatile Memory Express,
and this is why your hard drives are ridiculously fast.
I mean, like close to
gigabyte read and write speeds.
It's awesome, if you have gotten one.
If you enjoyed that, I got a lot more.