Now, as an expansion to my last
video about this, I wanted to give
you some things that
you could actually use in your day
-to-day exercises.
If you're sitting here at your keyboard
and you're just waiting for a build
to complete
or you've got a couple of minutes
here, what I'll typically do is I'll
take this and I'll
stretch it out to the sides.
And what you want to do with
that is you want to feel the
muscles in your back connect.
You're going to feel that stuff in
the back of your head feel tight
because you've been
sitting here.
These muscles in the back of the
neck, like splenus capitis and splenus
cervicis; they
insert back here in the back of
the spine -- I'm sorry, they *originate*
in the back
of the spine, they insert in the
back of the head.
They are responsible for keeping your
head upright whenever you sit up straight.
And with them being under a lot
of strain and your head leaning forward,
those muscles
are tight because they've been sitting
here trying to hold your head up.
So give them a break, lean back
a little bit and allow the rest
of your body to take on
the stress of your weight.
Whenever I grab one of these things,
they vary in strength.
For example, this is the easiest one.
I mean, it's like a simple rubber band.
This one takes a little bit more
strength and is a little bit tighter.
Use whatever resistance works for you.
Just enough resistance is enough to
get you started.
You don't have to stress yourself.
And whenever you feel comfortable
and ready for it, you can definitely
always add more
later.
So when you start off first, just
connect with the body, just connect
with what you
feel.
All right.
So whenever I use the elastic bands,
especially when it comes to exercises
that involve using
my feet, what I'll do is I
don't like the band like this, because
if you try and step
on this, you can hit one and
the other and it just turns into a mess.
So I do one loop, one crossing,
so that way I can step on
the X to keep myself from
tripping on the elastic band.
And when I do the bicep curls,
I'm lifting up and I'm trying to
connect with my arms.
This is going to be great because
it connects you not only with your
biceps, but also the
extensors in your forearms as well.
You can curl your hands up and
start to feel some of that tension
from racketing on that
keyboard all the time.
You can also invert your hands, lift
up as well, and you can start
to feel some of those
forearms starting to burn as well
from using that mouse, I'm sure.
I can also hit the long head
of the biceps by hitting it outside.
I can also do the short head
of the biceps by hitting it on
the inside.
You can go online and look for
the overlays of what the muscles of
the body are, but these
are typically used to make sure that
I can continue typing effectively.
Another really great one is to hang
it across an overhead anchor and be
able to pull down
and work on the triceps as well.
I kind of came up with this
on the spot, but I suppose you
could do this as well.
This will make sure the backs of
your arms are straight as well.
Anytime I execute on one side of
the muscle, you also need to hit
the other side as well.
If I do front side of the
body, I do back side of the body.
If I do biceps, I also do triceps.
If I do quads, I also do hamstrings.
You don't want to have one side
of your body also left and right
as well.
You don't want to have one side
of your body, front, back, left, right,
it doesn't matter.
You don't want to have one side
of your body stronger, tighter, or
any more than the other.
I try to do this to maintain
consistency such that I can keep doing
my job because I want
to keep getting paid.
I don't want to be stuck in
a hospital bed all day long doing stuff.
When it comes to the exercise ball,
this one is a little bit different.
I have probably a mid-sized one.
I think this was a 50 to
55 inch one.
Basically, I anchor my feet into the
wall, I lay down on the exercise ball.
You'll feel this as soon as you
lay down, how the stretch and the
connection to the
back of the body is.
This will do you wonders.
This is all I do, probably about
5 to 10 of these a day,
where I just lay on the ball
and I connect myself.
I say, how do you feel?
Now, if you do this and this
is as far as you can get,
don't worry about it.
It's okay, honey.
You'll, you'll, it'll take some time.
Your body is waking up.
You've never used it before, just
like the Matrix.
Why does his eyes hurt so bad?
Because he never used them before.
It's okay.
Once you connect and work with your
body, it will work with you.
And eventually you'll be able to reach
all the way up and get that
full extension in
the back.
Same thing with the front side as well.
Now, I will anchor my feet into
the wall, lean on the ball.
This will allow me to lay back.
You can feel the stretch in the
spine and you can use that to
raise yourself up.
And basically all I'm doing is connecting
with the body.
Now, I also want to caveat here,
I am not turning this into a
workout channel.
This is an absolutely critical part
of your day.
This is something you need to incorporate
into your lifestyle.
This is a change in the ways
in which you get stuff done.
Because if you can't take care of
the body, if you don't take care
of the self, it will
fail on you and it will hurt
and it will be miserable and you're
not going to like it.
So if you incorporate these changes
into your day to day, as part
of your job, as part of
your world, in IT, because sitting
in that chair all day long is
a death sentence.
I can guarantee you this.
Don't sit in the chair all day long.
You have other aspects of life that
you can and should incorporate.