Now, when it comes to working from
home or working in the office, I
try to make sure
that I take care of my body.
Because if I don't take care of
me, how can I take care of the company?
(or anything else for that matter)?
So one of the few things that
I do in order to make sure
that I can continue chugging
away here at the keyboard is, for
1: make sure that your posture is right.
You want to make sure that your
back is straight and that you're comfortable
in your chair.
You don't want to be leaning back
in it too much because that'll lead
you to bad posture.
I have learned through my trials with
massage therapy that (also through
physically holding
my stance correctly), sitting in your
chair upright definitely does you
a justice as far
as making sure that you are upright,
your breath is just right.
I make sure to be conscious of
my breathing while I'm working and
try not to get too lost
into what it is I'm doing because
oftentimes I fall too far into this.
So if that happens, there are some
things you can do not only to
maintain better posture,
but also you can go get yourself
some elastic bands.
Typically what I'll do with these
things is if I'm running a command,
I make a build,
I'm waiting on code to compile, I'm
waiting on a server to finish kicking off.
I'll take one of these bands and
just stretch.
And when I go to work out,
when I do a proper workout, it's
not this pump, pump.
I got to get all alpha male.
"Give me my big muscles" business...
No, no, no, no, no honey,
no, no, no, darling... *tsk tsk*
It's more of a meditation thing for me.
It's more of a connect your mind
to your body.
And I just want to say triceps:
Good morning.
"How are you doing today?"
"Trapezius, how are you doing?"
Rhomboids, teres minor...
I want to connect to the muscles
in the back, identify them, and
feel my brain clinch on them for
just a minute.
Feel the tension.
If you do this and it feels
tight or it doesn't feel right,
don't go grabbing the pills.
I'm sorry, Ibuprofen, Tylenol, Advil.
No, honey, we don't need you up
in here.
We got exercise.
The pain in your body that you're
experiencing is a signal that you
need to
get off your donkey and do something
different for a minute.
The hurt that you're feeling is because
you're sitting here stale for
hours in a day.
That's not good.
That's not healthy.
I also have myself an exercise ball.
I use that at times for core workouts.
I prop myself against the wall, lean
on the ball, and
reach up to the sky to feel
the muscles in the back.
And then I may also lay on
my back so that I can do
more than just crunches.
I want to feel the entire torso, and
I want to connect to everything that
I have here.
Why?
Because a healthy body is a healthy environment.
And if you are better connected to
your body, and if you feel good
in your own
skin, I promise you, your work day
is gonna be so much better.
And then for cardio, I go jogging.
Now, it also took me 5 years
to get to where I am.
It took me 5 years to get
to a point where 3 miles is comfortable.
That 1st mile is a warm up....
The 2nd mile feels like I'm really working.
The third mile is about where I
start to taper down and kind of
sort of wind it up
so I can bring it back home.
When I first started at 28, I
said, whatever habits I carry with
me into my 30s, I will
carry them past my 30s.
So we need to make a change
right now.
And I was probably just like you,
sitting doing this all day, all day,
16 hours a day,
(as much as I could).
And then at some point I said,
"No, I need to take care of myself."
And what's easiest for me is first
thing in the morning before my brain
has a chance
to convince me I should not do this.
I get my shoes on, I get
my gear together and I go for
a jog.
And when I go for the jog,
it's, you know, I used to just
run until I felt tired and
then just stop for a second.
Also when I first started, I started
with 300 ft, maybe... barely making
it out the
parking lot, barely making it 5-7 mins, if that...
But I didn't want to nix myself.
Far too many people I saw trying
to start off like an Olympian.
And that just don't work.
I mean, I'm sorry.
What you do is you start off
with very baseline basic minimums
and you start with just what
you can handle and push yourself just
enough to say, well, I just want
to focus on consistency.
I don't care how far I go.
I don't care how strong I get.
I just want to consistently pay my body.
It's minimum wage it needs in order
to survive.
I don't care about being an Olympian.
I don't care about being the next
Arnold Schwarzenegger.
I care about taking care of "The
Self". The biggest driving motivating
factor that gets
me off my fanny is that hospital
bed, them stack of pills.
I do not want to be 50
years old, taking 9,000 pills, sitting
in a hospital bed, unable to
do anything or to contribute to society.
I need to be able to take
care of self so that I can
take care of and provide for others.
That's the motivation behind what
gets me going, what gets me moving.
And if this helps you to change
your perspective about what healthy
exercise and what it looks
like to take care of The Self,
it's a whole lot different than, Oh,
you know, I gotta
get all beefy and blah, blah, blah,
no, honey... ;)
that's some
alpha stuff.
You need to put that muffin off
to the side.
We ain't going to be dealing with that.
This is some meditation stuff.
This is gonna make you feel good.
I hope this helps. Drop a like
if you think it did. =)