Here is your Linux command of
the day: xclip. This gives you
command-line access
to your clipboard. It's really cool.
Oh yeah, did you know Linux
has multiple
clipboards? I remember when Android
had like 10 of them, or
at least LG did. But
yeah, there's primary, there's secondary,
and there's clipboard. Oh yeah, did
you
know it supported multiple formats
with the `-t` option too?
So you mean to tell
me I can take text on
the screen and select it in
the terminal to put it on
the clipboard, and I can run
a command that gives me the
output, and I can just
grep out the stuff that I
want and slice and dice? Well
gee, if you wonder why I
find things faster than you, this
might be it. Oh yeah, remember
that QR encode
video that we did before? Well,
let me just take a screenshot
of this.
So if we try to take
a look at the contents of
the clipboard, we get gobbledygook.
Well, I guess you're gonna have
to take a screenshot of that
QR code and tell me
what you found. Because if I
take the contents of the clipboard
and put it
inside of a file, and then
we take a look at that
file, we get that QR code
back.
Hmm, I wonder what it says.
So yeah, it's fun accessing our
clipboard from the command line!