So let's talk about cloud operations,
a history. When I first started off
in software engineering
and started learning about the different
languages, that was about the time
I learned
that software engineering and programming
languages and software solutions themselves
can be full-blown religions. It surprises
me how many people follow a language and,
you know, praise to it as if
it was a deity, or at least
it sounds like it sometimes,
and this is a thing in software.
The C/C++ developers are very snobbish,
the Java developers have their
own personality, the JavaScript developers
are all attuned to a specific frequency,
and the PHP developers, well, you
know, PHP is just brain fog, so
unless you actually absolutely
love the language, you try to do
everything you can not to interact
or do anything with PHP anymore
these days. But that's not me talking,
that's, you know, things I've heard
about how people treat
things. It's kind of sad. I like
to think of language as a tool,
you know, there's a reason
I know so many, and it's because
it just happened to be the right
tool for the job for whatever it
was I was doing, and I tend
to think of things from that perspective.
Now, as I evolved from
going into software, I go from software,
I went into systems, the connotation
was, well, I'm a
software guy, I just want to write
my software, I just want to write
code all day long, I don't
want to have anything to do with
the server, starting and stopping
services, managing any of
that stuff, so I just took it
upon myself and just started managing
them. Well, in the midst of
managing it, you know, back in the
day, you used to SSH into the
box, we used to call it,
or the server, so that you could
start, stop the services, add users,
create accounts,
make sure that the programs were not
running as root, setting up environments
so the developers
could log in and they could perform
some testing of sorts in a collaborative
environment that kind
of sort of represents what production
is, and I just kind of started
doing that, like everybody
was just working off of their local
workstation, packaging the code up,
and you had to publish that
whole website, you know, out to some
environment for some nebulous QA team
to do some testing.
Well, being able to step in between
the different arenas allowed me the
freedoms to be able to see
what that world looked like, and having
played that developer background,
I was able to bring
that with me into the systems part,
and that's where I just started automating
stuff. I mean,
if it was software that needed to
get deployed out there, or packages
that needed to be compiled,
because, you know, that was another
thing that really blew my mind, software
making software,
by taking the algebraic English that
we write and converting that into
the bytecode that the
computer uses in order to manipulate
those statements that you create,
which is why you
sometimes see that weird code stuff,
yeah, it basically gets converted
into things that the
computer can use. So, now that you've
got your software, you've packaged
it up, and you've put
it into some environment, and next
is being able to test it. Now,
there's different ways that you
can go about testing it. There's unit
testing, which is being able to write
code that writes
code, and it's important you do that,
because it's a great way to CYA,
and being able to describe
what you tested, how you tested it,
and why you tested it that way,
through documentation,
examples, and actually using the code.
It also allows other developers to
see how your API
interfaces, whatever code you write,
would be consumed by them if you
were working on different
modules. Now, if you don't want to
go that far low, because, you know,
trying to test one plus
one equals two is pretty redundant,
you want to do some functional testing,
where you'd mock your
environment up with like a stock setup
that says, well, you know, we have
an e-commerce website,
I want to have a shopping cart
set up, and, you know, let's set
up a test case where the shopping
cart is empty, product gets added,
and we want to verify that the
product is actually added to the
shopping cart, so whenever you go
to the checkout page, the total will
show up, and all that fun
stuff, and how it works. Well, you
can set that up inside of an
automated testing environment,
and, you know, it's part of my
job to help set that stage up
as well, so the QA team can now
click buttons and go through the actual
website itself to make sure that it
did what it was
supposed to do. Well, that got tedious,
and so now people came up with
a solution called Selenium.
Selenium is where it loads up a
virtual browser, or it loads up a
virtual machine with a browser
environment already installed in it,
or you can have it installed as
a browser extension to your
existing browser. Either way, whatever
it is, we mock up some kind
of browser environment,
and then it allows you to programmatically
describe what you want the page to
look like,
to say, if I click on the
login screen, does the login page
actually show? Is this element
actually rendered? What if I type
this text into this field? How will
it respond to that? What will
the HTML look like after the form
has been submitted back to the server?
What's the response
look like coming back from the server?
Can I inject that into the next
page so that the fields
populate with the, you know, the address,
and the from, and the to, and
whatever you're doing at
the time for logins, and registrations,
and such, and being able to manage
and track your sessions
over time, so if I, you know,
would allow the browser to sit idle
for 15 minutes or so,
would my cookies and stuff be deleted
off the server? You can automate all
of this stuff,
and it's just amazing how many tools
and utilities are out there. The number
of tools growing is just
mind-boggling, and it's impossible
to keep up with unless you're just
immersed in it all day,
every single day, and the problem
with that is anytime you pick a
tool or utility of sorts,
it's got to come with its own
packaging, its own product, its own
service, its own pipeline,
its own process, and if you're not
careful, you can end up in a
vendor lock-in situation
where you can't change solutions later
on down the line if you find
out what you got doesn't
fit your needs, because all your data
is with them, and they don't provide
a way to export
your information. Thank you GDPR for
making that possible, so now if somebody
wants to go to another
solution, they can, because that ended
up becoming national law somewhere,
and so if you want to be
internationally supported, you have
to support all the laws, so it
just kind of sort of becomes
this rat race of going down these
rabbit holes, trying to figure out
what works, and if it does,
great, if it doesn't, crap, you just,
did you waste all that time? I
don't know, I learned a lot of
stuff, but nobody else on the team
gets to benefit from it. Great, so
we've automated all this setup,
and we've set these tools up, you
know, Senor Jenkins and Travis are
some of our
most fond tools, because they allow
us to create a visual diagram of
what we want our systems,
and our setup, and our processes to
do, what we want them to look
like, and they allow you to just
fill out a bunch of forms that
describe what you want your your build
to look like, what you want
your deployment to look like, how
does your software actually get out
into the environments and such,
so great, now you've got an environment
for the developers, an environment
for the QA team,
an environment for testing with the
customer before you actually go to
production, because
the customer's always got to have
something to say about what's going
to happen to the software,
and it doesn't matter if you have
end user customers, or if you have
internal customers,
which happen to be the users of
the software within the company itself,
because sometimes
the IT team is sitting up here
writing the web forms and stuff for,
you know, KFC, or Taco Bell,
or somebody like that, like, you know,
they're not, it depends on who's doing
what, but sometimes
people are actually writing software
for themselves, and you're writing
either the customer,
the end user, or the stakeholders,
and the other associates within the
company itself, it's not
always a company writing software
for somebody else, you know, another
end user, end customer,
it's, there's all kinds of stuff out
there, there's all kinds of models,
and different kinds
of setups, and then once you make
it to production, you've got a slew
of things, like
being audited, so that you're PCI
compliant, which is the pricing, what
is it, the, I think it's the
pricing, PCI compliance, I should
know this, because, you know, we had
to be PCI compliant
for being able to accept credit card
information, you have to be HIPAA
compliant if you're going to
be dealing with medical information,
or anything that deals with patients,
you're going to need to
undergo certain audits, so that third
parties will be able to say, yes,
yes, yes, check a box, they are
secure against X, Y, and Z, and
keep up to date, and they got
all their stuff, you know, audited,
SOC2 compliance is a big deal,
you have to make sure that you're
properly regulated,
you've got to have HA, so that
your environments are, always have
two, and do blue-green deployments,
because taking production down for
the sake of an outage is just
unacceptable in any customer's eyes,
they want it to be up and
running all the time, so, yeah, and
now you've also got, out of all of
that, you've got solutions where people
can have already, like, prepackaged
stuff, like docker is a
prepackaged something, but then that
can expand into docker compose, that
can expand into terraform,
kubernetes, you know, there's these
other ready-made solutions that enable
you to basically
describe things through some kind
of description file, and then use
that to publish it into the
environment, or you got that one developer
guy who's on the team who knows
all the stuff, how
it works and everything, and he's
just writing the code himself from
scratch, and just basically
building the internal product, which
is just kind of sort of rewriting
Ansible, Puppet Chef,
docker, and all them, just using,
leveraging those tools and their APIs
to be able to access
the internals to get them to do
what they need to do, I mean,
just like cloud ops is huge,
like there's a lot to cloud ops,
and you think you can just be
like, yeah,
I'll just hire this guy off the
internet that can do this job.