So my thoughts on Althea L1, it
looks like it's trying to be a
cryptocurrency based
Infrastructure kind of sort of like
helium was if you don't know about
helium, you've never heard of that before
I just created a video you should
go check that out first
Because it'll give you some insights
and some context around this because
I don't like talking about stuff
But I've never talked about before
so I gave you a spiel on
helium and my take on Althea
It looks like the promising aspect
of what I was looking for what
I was looking for in helium by providing
internet access to rural areas where
it's difficult because
Centralized providers just don't draw
lines out that far
And so the idea is if you
have multiple Wi-Fi devices that can
connect to each other in a decentralized fashion
Then ideally you'd still be able to
connect to the internet
Albeit it may be a little bit slower
But you'd still have a minimal amount
of access to the internet because
it would be completely decentralized
They're not completely but at least
partially decentralized
Just like helium it looks really promising
it looks really great on the surface
I'm curious to know what it looks
like on the inside because
There are some really great projects
out there and some of them have
really done some good things
I
Caution with this because it's crypto
based. That's why I'm like, I don't know
Because if you own it and you're
distributing it who's to say somebody
can't exploit it
Who's to say somebody can't take this
and centralize it again?
Who's to say somebody can't influence
the developers and their decisions
on what to do?
there was all this talk in crypto
about how because it's decentralized
it because it's this because
Because it's decentralized because
you know, the community has to agree
to this
It doesn't take much for somebody
to come through and pay the developers
to go do what they need to do
So keeping that in mind
It looks like a promising prospect
you are right to sit and wait
you are right to sit there and watch
Because that's what I would do if
it stands the test of time and
it lasts four years
Then I might be interested in investing.
I might be interested in purchasing.
I might be interested in looking into it
But at this point after being burnt
from crypto and losing about $40,000
in various projects in 2021
I'm a lot more conservative now when
it comes to prospects because I don't
know what you're going to do after
you get my money
with that said
This is not financial advice. This
is not a
Poo-poo on something. It's just a
projection of my experiences and
My experience says it's okay to pause
and wait. It's okay to watch
Research learn more interview other
people that you might know who are
in this. What's their experience with
it? What are their gripes?
Try and see if
You know, this looks like something
that's relatively new. So how much
history does this happen? Actually,
no, it says since 2018
Okay, so they've been through at least
they've been through at least a cycle
or two. So that's good
actually that gives a little bit more
confidence to what they might be trying
to provide and
being that decentralized
Entity or being some kind of decentralized
entity that allows you to be able
to connect
I mean it'd be great if I
could open my Wi-Fi up and
allow other people access
but do that in a secure way
so that they can't see my communications
as well to be able to grant
somebody access to the
Internet and not have them see the
rest of the internals of my network.
That'd be kind of cool because then
You have a combination of being a
provider and a consumer and to those
that consume it
Yeah, if you can track it and
you know exactly what they're consuming.
It'd be easy to go ahead and
build them exactly what they're using
So if they can pull it off
if if they do it great if
they do a good job
if the developers are on point and
if they're able to accomplish their
goals then
By all means I want one too
and
I'll tag citizen fortress in this
as well. Perhaps he can help you
out in researching this as well because he's
I'm not sure but I think he
might be trying to explore alternative
internet solutions. So we'll see what happens