So let's talk about Helium mining.
What is Helium mining?
Well, it's when you
mine over the Wi-Fi's. It was
a really fascinating concept when
I first got
into it and during the 2017 -- (oops)
2020-2021 bull run I was getting into
cryptocurrencies and Helium mining
and piqued my interest because it
was a way
for you to do crypto mining using
radio wave technology compared to conventional
crypto mining where it relies on powerful
gear like ASICs (which are
Application Specific Integrated Circuits)
or GPUs (which are Graphical Processing
Units; aka your video card). Traditional
crypto mining might use those but
as a
result this was a lot less power
intensive and also something that allowed
Internet of Things (IOT) devices to be able
to chat and talk with each other.
The idea
behind Helium mining was decentralized
access to the network. You'd plug
it into
the wall you plug it into your
internet and off to the races you
went. What
happens is you know those dog collers
that tell you where your dog is
even if
it isn't connected to Wi-Fi or
those way old-fashioned GPS's that
are dedicated
to just knowing your geolocation and
whatever? It wasn't limited to just
geolocation there were packets of
other information like statistics
about what
this particular device was doing,
Apple watches, smart watches, other
Internet of
Things devices that needed to connect
to the Internet but didn't need to
transmit that much information also
did not require a Wi-Fi network.
Well Helium
mining could be a solution that would
solve that problem and it was a great
solution for low latency low bandwidth
because it required little power
probably $5 of electricity cost per
month and the trackers would come
packed with their own HNT tokens that
would be used to transmit packets of
information and then the miner itself
would be able to communicate and relay
that on the network so that the
rest of the system would be able
to keep track
and keep check on what's going on.
Because we're using radio signals we'd
be able to tell very clearly specifically
where your device is as far
as elevation placement and all that
other fun stuff is concerned and how far
away it was from other Helium miners.
The more packed in a specific area you
were with other Helium miners the
more those rewards were being distributed and
being split. So if you were the
only person inside of a hex grid
that covered
the whole that you know they basically
gridded the whole planet and if you were
the only miner you were collecting
all the rewards. If you were sharing
it with
other miners you were splitting the
rewards with them. Anytime a device
needed to connect and talk to any
one of the antennas it would be
sending HNT
tokens. The miner that received the
communication would receive the HNT
tokens as a reward of the communication
with the device. If you were a
witness to
the communication then you would get
witness tokens. Once that information was
sent back to the servers they'd be
recorded to the blockchain where the
validators would be able to take that
information and verify everything
matched up correctly. The validator
role was oftentimes placed in different
was randomly selected by one of the
miners. So in a way you were
playing the
lottery every time you interacted
with one of these devices because
you may be
elected to be one of the validators.
I follow VoskCoin on the other platform
and he was talking about how he
made like $5,000 in HNT tokens
from being one
of the validators that validated the
transactions. Well that sense has been
changed. The validators are now a
specific server setup that Helium, the
developers, control and you have to
be part of the whitelist in order
for them
to be able to permit you to
be one of the servers that do
the validation. So I
don't like how the reward structure
has changed as a result because it
felt like
HNT was very token heavy and that
it was very rewards based. But putting
that to
the side, you used to be able
to build your own miner. You would
be able to take
the antennas, hook them up to your
own computer, build the software and then
you're off to the races. You're now
part of the Helium network transmitting data
and you can control it yourself. This
proved to be pretty difficult for
a lot
of people so, not sponsored, but Bobcat,
Nebra and MNTD ("Minted") took up the
helm of providing these pre-built
boxes that came with the software
pre-installed
and with the radio antennas already
connected to them. The ability to
be able
to create the miners yourself kind
of sort of fell away and it
seemed like it
was impossible for me to be able
to just buy a RaspberryPi and
an antenna and
have a nice day. And after it's
all said and done, I paid about
$450 per miner.
Bobcat took about 10 months to deliver
the miner that I had put an
order for
them with. I also tried a few
times to get another miner from MNTD.
It took
them about three weeks to deliver
the Helium miner that I got from
them. So now
I've got two Helium miners. One sitting
in the living room. I figured I'd take
the other one over to a friend's
house that's been sitting over there
for some
time. And I am probably sitting on
maybe $30 of HNT tokens. I probably
have $8
in IOT tokens. They also migrated
from their own blockchain over to
Solana. So
they're no longer managing their own
thing. They're now taking it over
to a
new blockchain where now you've got
the IOT token, the mobile token and
a few
other things that I guess they were
not able to put into their own blockchain
so quickly. They also started offering
a 5G alternative that you could put
inside of your house as well. You
connect this to your connected to
the wall for
power, connect it to the internet
so it had access to it. And
the 5G device would
be able to provide 5G internet to
all your devices that were in that
area. And
the same rules applied as far as
being able to communicate. Just a
little bit
different because 5G has a lot more
bandwidth than the low-frequency
LoRaWAN. I can't remember exactly
what that was. But it was the
low-frequency, low-latency antennas
that talked to the other devices.
My take on
this was that Helium was a great
concept because decentralizing the
internet was
just... why? We all have Wi-Fi
routers. Why do we need to talk
to a central
authority to communicate with the
internet when I could just bounce
off of
Wi-Fi routers to get to the
internet and we decentralize it rather
than keep it
centralized? It sounded like a great
concept. I didn't like how it was
on just
those IOT devices and it was great
that they were trying to support 5G.
What I
would have loved to have seen was
more Wi-Fi general-purpose use with the
internet. Seeing as that didn't take
place, things have been shifted around.
The reward structure has been moved
so that you don't get that, you
know, you
don't get any of those lottery winnings
that came from being a validator on the
network. You now have to pay for
incredible hardware and also software
and possibly even a membership fee.
I don't know but possibly even a
membership fee to be a validator on
the Helium network. I don't like the fact
that now the the workers are not
getting, are hardly getting any of the
rewards because, you know, it's just
sad that I paid $450 for this
piece of hardware that was supposed
to make its returns within a month
or two
which was completely unbelievable
and unrealistic. But hey, you know, if
you got in early you got in
great but if not now the miners
are selling for about
$100 on the second-hand market and
$200 if you can find it
fresh. But even then it's difficult
to buy it off the second-hand market
because there are certain keys and
tokens that are embedded in the device
itself that need to be given to
you so you have to trust the
seller. They are
also going to give you the keys
to that, the software keys to that
miner so that
you can receive the rewards not mining
for them. Boy, that was fun.
So yeah, my
take on Helium mining was that it
was a great idea but a terrible implementation
not to mention Nebra, MNTD, and
Bobcat did not do a good job
at the
manufacturing. Bobcat was the best
for the longest but I waited the
longest for
my miner from them. Also this is
a requisite video to a comment reply that
I'm gonna be making on Althera which
is, looks like, the promising prospect of
what I wished Helium could be.
So that's next.