And this is not so far
off from the reality that we
create amongst ourselves whenever
we venture off into a video
game or decide we want to
abuse some substance to aberrate
ourselves from this thing that we
call our reality.
And given the considerable amount
of difficulty people experience these
days with making connections
with other human beings, why wouldn't
this become a thing?
And I agree with this, I
think most people would prefer another
human, but when you consider
the options that we have available
to us, some of us might
look around thinking, hmm,
that AI ain't looking too bad.
But I think you're also glossing
over this idea of child permanence
here.
Just because a state of being
is within this moment doesn't necessarily
mean that state
of being will always be there.
So even if AI does become
better at relationships than humans
do, do you really think it's
reasonable
to assume that everything is in
absolutes and that all humans will
prefer AI relationships?
No.
When has anything ever been absolute
in this world?
When has anybody ever chosen the
same exact thing, no matter what,
time after time, and
that is the thing.
We're describing these things as if
that's going to be the way,
when in reality, it's
just one way.
I beg to
differ with this point.
You see, in my relationships with
some folks, I have been coming
to the conclusion that
some people want that level of
understanding, all-knowing, and belief
that something will
always be there for you to
give you that sake of comfort.
Not so that you don't have
to change, but to give you
the comfort and the stability
that you need to stand upon
so that you can make the
greatest change of your life.
Case in point, here in my
life, in my time, I've been
trying to build a family, a
collection
of people who I know won't
bail on me at the first
sign of trouble.
People that I know who will
be there for me whenever there
are times of need.
Some people say those are just
friends.
My opinion of it is, no,
those are true friends.
A lot of people encounter superficial
people that don't exactly dip beyond
the surface.
But once I have that level
of stability and that unconditional
love, then I feel as if
I am able to flourish.
I think another aspect of
this that we seem to be
glossing over is the fact that
this could just be another tool
in order to help us obtain
that better knowledge when it
comes to emotional intelligence.
For example, like you said with
the example of being able to
understand vast swaths of
people.
That is to say that we
couldn't take that information and
use it as a learning mechanism
such that other people would be
able to learn from those experiences
rather than using them
as a replacement or a fill-in
to the actual relationship that
would ensue.
but does it have to be
real?
In order to have the experience
from the person who is experiencing,
does it really matter?
Yes.
And it's also something that can
be used as a tool.
True.
and that is something that some
kind of greater intelligence with
that unconditional love
could provide for us. So that
we could better understand our pain
and better also appreciate
the joy that comes from it
as well.
A disappointment.
It doesn't seem like something that
we as humans would do.
We crave that pain far too
much and far too many of
us are so fixated on creating
problems
so that we can work on
the solutions in order for us
to completely forgo any chance at
a future.
Because we crave that evolution and
growth.
We as humans are just the
experience of a spiritual element,
a soul that craves that
understanding, that growth, that hidden
meaning beyond what it is we
feel in these flesh bodies
these days.
And how is that any different
from the drugs and the addicts
that we have these days?
Because the argument could be made
the same from way back then.
When those drugs and those things
were new, well, didn't people think
that everybody would
be hyped up on drugs?
Now, if we look at ourselves
today, is everybody hyped up on
those drugs?
Or do we sometimes have people
who oftentimes elect not to live
in the state of constant bliss?
Who elect to live here in
this state of reality?
Who decide they want to continue
to pursue their life, their dreams,
their goals, their hopes, their wishes?
Well, that depends.
How much of your agency are
you willing to give up for
the sake of freedom?