So let's talk about hacking and security.
Now, before we get started, I want
to make
sure you understand that Kizano's Fintech
does not condone the use of hacking to
steal some company's information,
to deal damages to another person,
to perform
damage to IP or to some other
company. Please hack ethically outside
of the
context of a contractual agreement
between you and the entity where you
have their express permission to perform
the operations discussed in this video.
Don't do anything illegal. Don't be
dumb. Don't do anything you're not
supposed to.
This is for edutainment purposes only.
But first, black tourmaline has properties
of the earth, is attuned to the
root chakra, can purify your space,
and also
dons purification of the energies
around you. It's a great traveling
companion and
one of my favorite stones. Fascinating,
isn't it?
So how does a website get hacked, you
might be wondering. You know this
login screen accepts user input and if
someone's not careful and doesn't
validate their input and escape their
output before they take these textboxes
and go and query the database, oftentimes
people find SQL injections inside
of these text boxes. Because a lot
of the
times people don't take the time to
make sure that their output that's being
coming from untrusted sources is sanitized
and actually
represents the data that they expect
it to be. A lot of times
hackers will go and
find these inputs and have scripts
that automatically go and attempt
to inject
them with input that the application
wasn't expecting. So if, as a software
engineer, you are not vigilant as
far as making sure that untrusted information
is sanitized and cleansed before sending
it off to another source, you could be
opening yourself up for exploit. And
we all know and are probably quite annoyed
with that captcha box that checks
to make sure that you're actually human.
Well that's there to make sure that
robots aren't able to continuously poke
at the login page to see if
they can try and authenticate. Because
bots can't
tell what those pictures are. And
so this is a mechanism that is
used to ensure
that someone can't brute force your
login. Because if you don't put some kind
of barrier in place to make it
difficult, or rather to increase the
cost of attack
of trying to guess at someone's password,
they can sit there and poke at
your site all day long and you'll
be none the wiser. And eventually
find a way
to get in. And we all know
about these arduous forms that tediously
require us
to enter this information over and
over again. Boy I can't wait till
we get one
touch Auth where you just say *bink*
and information is shared
with who
you specifically authorize, when you
specifically authorize them, and for how
long they get that access. But until
that day comes around, we still got
these text
boxes to fill in. Did you know
that these text boxes are also a
treasure trove for hackers? They love
to find these inputs. Why? Because
it allows
them to poke at the site and
see what more can they do. Because
if I can get
your database to dump the contents
of the user database table right here on
the page, that's a treasure trove
of information right there. If I can get
your site to spit out a stacktrace
and show me where the files
are on the file
system, that's more information I
can use in my reconnaissance to better
understand the lay of the land within
your current setup. If I can take these
inputs and make your server do something
that it wasn't intended to do, especially
if I could take text from these
boxes and put it into some kind
of execution
space. Because people sometimes love
to take input from users and run
it inside
of an eval function or evaluate, which
basically says take any string and
execute it as code. That's extremely
dangerous for unsanitized and unverified
input from the end user. Why? Because
I can get your server to go
and download a
malicious package and infect your
site. I can convince your server to
go out and
do things on your behalf and it
will look as if it's coming from
your website.
Now you're blacklisted. Now Google
thinks you're a hacked website. Now
you get the
red banner at the top of the
site or completely blocked altogether because
you're not on the safe browsing list.
So let's say a hacker got access
to your
server. They've got it compromised now.
They found a way to get into your
application and get it to execute
some code that it wasn't expecting.
Let's say
there's a server out there that it
already has access to. They've already
compromised this server. What happens
next? They can say, hey server, my new
minion, I want you to go and
download some infected software that
I've got
control of. And this software is going
to give me more access to your systems.
So if you have a fleet of
servers that are sitting inside of
your network and
one of them gets compromised and now
they've got control over it, they
can go
and get control to the rest of
those servers as well. From this point
they can
do a network scan to see what
that server can see as far as
its internal
network is concerned. So even though
you may be behind a VPC, even
though this
particular server may be segmented
off from the rest of the network, the
servers that are inside of that local
network are still possible to be
compromised. This software that they've
downloaded can now start a crypto miner
and use and abuse the resources available
to your system. It can deface
your website such that anytime somebody
comes to visit it, they also get
infected with malware. Be it on mobile,
desktop, any kind of client that comes and
accesses the server could become infected
because it touched the infected server.
Now what does that infected part mean?
It means code executed outside of the
context that it was designated to
execute. So even though the program was
running inside of the application
on a server, somewhere in that program it
evaluated a string and it broke execution
context. And so now the
application, that string that the
hacker fed into the application told
it, gave
it the instructions it needed to go
and do something it wasn't supposed to.
So this is why things like protection
against cross-site scripting (XSS) or
cross-site request forgery (CSRF/XSRF) are important
tactics to make sure that you use to
protect yourself against exploit on
the website's side. This is why the networking
team is critical to ensure security
against exploits because firewalls and
other network partitions can prevent
stuff like this from happening. Even
though port 80 and 443 are open,
you should also have an application firewall
or even an outbound firewall to prevent
your application, if it is compromised,
from compromising things even further.
And this is why in my networks
I always
run a two-way firewall. It's not
just input but also output. And so
if I see
something from within my network reaching
out to some place like China,
Russia, another country, a known hacked
server, something's wrong. Something's wrong.
And I've seen my internal firewalls
block outbound traffic, preventing me
from getting infected further. So
it's important to keep that in mind
as well.
Network partitioning and segregating
off your servers such that only your
application servers would be impacted.
Can you imagine if the database sat in
the same location and that server
got compromised as well? If they got access
to the database, and not talking about
just talking to the database as a client
like a MySQL client or a MongoDB
client, I'm talking about SSH or getting root
access to the server behind the database.
That's a very dangerous situation as
well. We want to avoid that by
making sure that we validate our input, sanitize
and escape our output, make sure firewalls
are in place to protect our
systems, so that people can't just
willy-nilly connect to services that may
be running on our servers. An application
firewall that understands
the input that's being received, so
that if it were to perceive an injection
attack or some kind of cross-request
forgery attack, the application firewall
itself would be intelligent enough
to be able to figure that out,
and would
better be able to protect your application
from exploits.
Hi, my name is Markizano Draconus,
and I run Kizano's FinTech Channel,
where I take you from Zero to Master in IT and DevOps.
But did you also know
I'm a licensed massage therapist in Dallas, Texas?
If you're looking for a holistic alternative
to health and well-being,
you can go to massage.markizano.net
where you can schedule a massage with me today.
If you use the coupon code "RELAX2023"
before the end of this month (31-OCT-2023),
I'll give you $10 off your next massage.  =)
I look forward to seeing you on the table.