I'm going to give into the negativity
just this one time, just so you
can see the stark
contrast that I sometimes live with...
I can relate to where you come
from when it comes to the 6
years that I put into this
company that treated me just like
everybody else says on TikTok.
I mean, corporate America is new age
slavery America, and as long as we
can keep you there
working for that paycheck, it's fine,
we got you... because I put in
6 years worth of work, six and
a half years going on seven.
I was almost ready for my sabbatical.
I completely set up their entire infrastructure.
And I remember talking to one of
the leads who I was there when
the CTO hired her.
They had since nixed the CTO and
there was plenty of opportunity to
go ahead and step
up. Right. Well, I stepped up to
the plate, even though my title was
"SysAdmin", I did
things a director was supposed to
be doing.
I was doing things that a
C-level executive was supposed to be
doing as far as reviewing
financial documents, evaluating SOWs
and trying to understand the strategy
behind all
the technology and everything that
we were setting up.
And I remember sitting in the conversation
with her and she's like, "Mark," like, "What
can we do to truly show our
appreciation for people like you who've
been with us since
the start?" And I was like, you
could give me a title that actually
matches the job role
that I take. And well, I pretty
much got a non answer to that.
And after leaving the company, you
know, finding out that they basically
hired someone
else to take the manager's role that
I had busted my ass off for,
it basically told me
getting promotion, getting a promotion
was a fscking joke.
I don't know if I'm
too dark.
I don't know if I'm too gay.
I don't know what's
what's wrong with me.
What is wrong with me?
Why am I not good enough for
director level material who's able
to drive the decision
behind how stuff gets done?
On top of that, I spent four
years with my love and tried doing
all the things I could
and that didn't work out.
So I'm sitting here thinking to myself,
how worthless am I?
How useless am I?
Not good at my job, not good
at personal life.
What the fuck am I doing here?
And I sat in that for months
until I started putting these up to
remind myself I'm not...
Half of them are b/s.
You know, it's like Team-tasticness.
Oh, perfect attendance.
Good job.
But it's something.
The license.
Yeah, it'd be great because everybody's
like... (that's another lesson to learn.)
Don't listen to what other people
tell about you because everybody's
like, oh, you'd make
such a great massage therapist.
Guess what?
You would make an even better client.
I still have yet to get people
on the table like I really need.
And I've started to push myself out
there and say, come on, I need help.
I'm trying to get into a house.
I need people on the table.
Come on, let's go.
Where are we at?
Nobody crickets, nothing.
Nobody cares.
Nobody gives a shit.
So it'd be so easy for me
to just disappear off into the nothingness,
disappear off into
the ether and sign out. May 1st
of this year.
I almost did that.
I started moving money around and
when I did that, that scared the
living daylights out
of me.
I was like, holy crap, I cannot
believe I'm actually sitting this
close to the edge.
This brilliance, this mind that has
put so much effort after being told
time and time
again, you are useless, you are worthless,
stupid Mark, fscking Mark, faggot Mark!
So if you wonder why I'm such
a perfectionist, if you wonder why
everything must be so
polished, if you wonder why it's so
difficult to work with me and why
I'm always trying
to get things right and trying to
reach everything so that they do the
right things,
it's because of that.
It is a projection of the self.
It is a projection of, I have
never felt like I'm worthy enough.
I have never felt like I was enough.
I always had this voice in my
head constantly pinging at me.
"You should have changed this."
"You should have done that."
"You should have done it this way."
"You should have done it that way."
You know, no, no, no, no, no,
no, no, no.
Years I dealt with that and it
wasn't until the last two years or
so that I finally was
like, fsck all that.
No, we're, we're done.
Just... that's all negative.
That's all hate.
It's all self-deprecation.
Just put it off to the side.
What can we do to love the self?
And I have been going down this
path in so many ways, shapes and fashions.
I mean, as far as religion is
concerned, I want to read all the books.
As far as philosophy is concerned,
I want to evaluate all the things
that are out there.
As far as theocracy is concerned,
I want to take it as part
of my college courses.
I want to get my minors in
human psychology.
I've got, I mean, it's a matter
of picking a direction.
You've got -- I've got Osash: the Online
Services Auction, SuperHighway. Angie's list &
eBay basically had a baby.
And instead of it being just housing,
it's everything!
Amazon scale...
Osash is Amazon.
Amazon is products.
Osash is services.
That was an idea.
That was a business idea.
And I had thought through so many
components of it and how I could
string it together.
But fear of success is so real.
Fear of success is very real.
Okay, fine.
I've got the story of Markizano
Draconus who comes from a galaxy 25,000
light years away in
the Crux galaxy.
I have a story that I want
to tell about dreams I've had from
what seems like past lives.
I don't know... Who knows, but it's
a fun story.
And it's like super sci-fi, fantasy magic,
just space.
It's, it's a glorious story.
If I can sit down and write
it from start to finish.
I can't physically, I'm sitting here
thinking, what can I practically put
my hands on and
get done within a 5-7
period -- 5-7 year period.
And realistically, how can I convince
3 million people to give me $1
at a bare minimum?
That's my retirement.
If I can convince 3 million people
to give me $1, I can live
on the interest.
And I don't have to have crazy
billions or whatever.
And I see absolutely no reason why
we all can't have our 3 million
nest egg.
And we just live off the interest.
What can I practically put my hands on?
I can practically put my hands on
Kizano's Massage.
the Markizano Draconus story.
I can practically put my hands on
Kizano's Fintech, where you can come,
lab, learn,
grow, evolve.
And I can become a honeypot for
the companies that are trying to hire talent.
Talent can come in and they can
learn to do the things to get
better at whatever they're
doing as far as IT is concerned.
And I get in between that handshake
right there.
As a Libra, I can,
manage commerce.
That's a good place for me.
I know we don't get to choose
our own endings, but Warren Buffett
said it best.
Start with your obituary and work
your way backwards.
What do you want people to say
about you whenever you've already passed?
And you've already got a mind thinking
in that direction.
I think that's extremely admirable.
Because it suggests: what can I do
with all this energy that has been
given to me?
How can I use it the most efficiently?
Such that when my life is fully
consumed, my job here is also done.
Because I Refuse to be a corporate
slave for the rest of my life.
I Refuse to give in to this
idea that I should just make my
life beautiful, pretty, and comfortable
for me and screw everybody else who
ain't me.
I Refuse to accept that mentality
of "it's not enough that I should
win, but you should also lose."
I violently refuse these things.
Because it's just not me.
I'm the kind of person where once
I evolve, grow, do better, and am
able to provide...
That I don't do these things for
me, I do these things for you.
Because after I'm gone, you can't
take the money with you, honey.
I'm sorry; not sorry. But you can't
take it with you.
So, what are you going to do
while you're here?
And what are you going to do
that's going to be meaningful?
What are you going to do that
people are going to actually care about?
Because right now, I'm a nobody.
Nobody knows me.
Nobody gives a sh!t about me.
I could disappear the next day and
y'all just be like,
well, there goes that Markiz guy,
whoever that was, I don't know.
Think about it.
I probably have two or three people
that would really cry.
You know, they might actually shed
a tear.
But outside of that, nobody knows
who I am.
I'm a nobody.
Why should I care what you think?
It's because I do care.
And I care too much.
And if I get to choose my
end, I would like my death for
my 125th birthday.
#plxKThxBai.
Y'all are going to have to
figure it out.
I don't know what the deal is.
I know some of y'all love me.
I know you want me around forever.
But for 125, please, can I please
be done with this life, this plane,
this existence?
And while I'm here, let's turn this
nightmare around.
I'm tired of hearing all the pain
and the sorrow and the hurt.
And oh my God, I'm not enough.
I don't love me.
Come on, let's go.
If I'm stuck here and I'm stuck
with you, then we got to make
it something.
We have got to pick this up.
And 0xvmx, I applaud you.
I mean, you're doing the thing.
I know you feel like you don't
know what you're doing, but you're
doing something.
And I appreciate it.
Thank you.