So let's talk about networking:
IP address edition.
Okay, so first things first in
case you didn't already know: IP
stands for the
internet protocol in your IP address.
This is how we find out
where you are on the internet.
Kind of sort of like your
address, your direction. It basically
says,
you know, this is the street,
this is the number of the
house that's on the street,
that's the direction it is, and
that's the kind of street it
is. That's the unit number,
and you know, that's the city,
the state, and these five digit
numbers that represents the zip
code. I mean, there's all these
things that kind of sort of
point out what an address is,
right?
Let's look at an internet style.
Your internet protocol address is
basically a set of four
digits separated by a dot, which
is a number that ranges between
0 and 255. If you wonder
why that's significant,
go find the
"How-To Binary" video. Short of the
long of it is this number
between 0 and 255 in decimal
format can easily be represented between
zero and 0xFF in hexadecimal format.
Hexo what?
Well, imagine a numbering
system that isn't our base-10.
We have 10 fingers, 10 toes,
so we count as if there's
a base of 10 items. But
what if you have a numbering
system that is base
16? You see, binary is base
two. You only have zero and
one. I have a how-to
binary if you want to
not account there, but you count
in hexadecimal a little bit different
because once you get to nine,
you have more things to count.
We don't have numbers that represent
these, so we use letters,
A through F, and that represents
a placeholder for those values, greater
than 9, that still
represent something that you can count
to in a single digit. To
get to the next one, 10
is actually
16. So once you get to
nine, 10 in hexadecimal is A,
11 in hexadecimal is B, 12
in hexadecimal is C,
and then when you get up
to 16, that's actually 10. 17
is 11, and you go 12,
34,
all the way up to 19,
and then instead of counting 19
to 20, we go 1A, 1B,
1C, 1E, all the way down
to 1F.
Once you get to 1F, then
32 is actually in hexadecimal, is
20 in decimal.
Scratch that, reverse it.
Wait a minute, strike that, reverse it.
Thank you.
20 in hexadecimal is 32 in decimal.
So let's give an example to that.
If you've got an IP address of
4.4.4.4, now let's
say I take the
hexadecimal representation of this
IP address and convert it into
a hexadecimal number. That's 0x04040404.
Which, if you convert that to decimal...
What is that...?
That's just a really big number.
You take that
really big number and you can
store that in two bytes.
There's a lot of database guys that
I see
that are taking this as a
string and storing it as a
string and you make my head
hurt. You could just
use the htons() function that exists
out there to convert this string
representation of this IP address
into this numeric representation that
there is here and you can
store so much less data compared
to the what 12 to 14
characters it takes to store string.
Those characters, what is that? 24
bytes
versus the two bytes it takes
to store a really big number.
So whenever you want to take
your IP
address from its binary stored format,
which is just a really huge
number, you convert it back
into hexadecimal, break it up by
its multiple places, convert those
hexadecimal back to their
decimal representation and you got
your IP address back at you.
An IP address is just a
number that
shows the internet where you are
so we know how to find
you.