So let's talk about Local Admin Rights.
But first, this is Pyrite. Element of
fire and earth, tuned to the chakra
of the solar plexus. Oftentimes represents
manifestation and willpower and can
be used as a good luck charm. Fascinating.
I see a lot of security gurus
out there talking about how they deny
access to
developers when they want admin rights
to their local workstation. And I see
some attempts at trying to make some
explanations. Some of them make sense, but
also some of them from the developers
perspective probably still leave them
wondering or feeling, why can't I
have admin rights to my workstation?
Well it
comes from the principle of least
privilege. You see, as someone who comes
in and pretty much does line developer
work, there isn't that much access that
is really necessary for the engineer
on their local workstation when they have
access to a server environment that
has the complete suite of all the software
and everything they need running.
Not to mention the structure and the
setup that
is required for having that particular
application execute in whatever kind of
environment they're using for their
development. If you have done some
modicum of software engineering at
some point, you have run into the
concept of
dependencies. Your software oftentimes
needs to install additional dependencies
from other repositories. Somebody
else has written that code, so why
should you?
Totally get it. Perfectly understandable.
I'm a little late to this post because
this has been published for quite
some time, but it's important to understand.
Hackers have gone out and they've
actually infected these repositories. Now
I'm not saying every package has been
infected, and it's also not as simple as
we'll just avoid those packages, right?
Also, this is not a new concept either.
This actually has been around for
as long as code has existed. Hackers
will go
and they'll infect the packages and
they may use this concept called
typosquatting*, which is using those
funny characters that are part of
a Latin
alphabet that look like the same character
they represent. Like an "รก"
You cannot just brush
over the accent because you think
it's a
typo, right? No, it's called typosquatting,
and it's something to pay attention to.
If there's a package you're looking
to install, you copy and paste the
name of
the website and it happens to have
the name messed up or named very
similar, you
know, name the same package with a
"-dev" at the end of it
to indicate that it
might be a developer's package of
sorts. People do all kinds of things
to get you
to install malicious software. Well,
what happens when that software hits your
workstation? When your workstation
is connected to the company VPN and your
workstation can access the internal
guts and the internal network of
everything that the company needs
as far as how it gets its
work done? What if you
as the developer, the engineer, had
access to the production environment
where we make our money, where our
customer information is, where our
PII, personally identifiable information,
is stored? The risk of all of
that coming down because the developer
installed a bad package by accident, by
intention, by bad copy and paste,
by spoofing, who knows? In security,
it's a
matter of measuring the risk versus
the protection of the data. If the
risk is
greater than the information we're
trying to protect, then yeah, we're
going to increase the cost of attack.
And as far as I can tell,
as far as my
interpretation is concerned, security
isn't about being completely blanketing,
total, white glove;
everything perfectly clean. It's about
increasing the cost of attack to make
it more expensive to exploit the system and
to do something you're not supposed
to, than it would be to use
the application
like it was supposed to, as it
was intended. So in security, if I
can make
it really expensive to attack us,
but really cheap to just use us,
hey, that's a
win-win, right? So the reason why
you don't have admin rights on your local
workstation is because it's too much
of a risk to the company to
allow you to be
able to do that. Until, as an
engineer, as a developer, and you
get that senior rank
and you are able to prove that
you're diligent enough to protect yourself
against exploits -- Actually I think
it's just becoming a general practice more
as time goes on. Because we've had
far too many instances where employees get
exploited. Companies are not treating
their employees like they should be. So
it makes it really easy to compromise
the employees, get in their head,
and get
them to think that they can get
back at the company for something.
And it's just
not worth the risk. So with that
in mind, please have a little bit more
patience with your security. Have
a little bit more patience with those that
are trying to balance the scales between,
is it usable? Is it functional? Can
I get my job done?
Can I be effective?
Can I be fast and still affordable?
Versus, can I
be compliant? Can I be secure? Because
the most secure thing that you could
ever do
is just unplug the ethernet cable.
Simple as that. But then you can't get
anything done. So it's a toss-up.
It's a balance between functionality and security.
Hi, my name is Markizano
Draconus and I run Kizano's FinTech
channel where I take you from Zero
to master in IT and DevOps.
But did you also know
I'm a licensed massage therapist
in Dallas, Texas? If you're
looking for a holistic alternative
to health and well-being, you can
go to
massage.markizano.net where you can
schedule a massage with me today.
If you
use the coupon code "RELAX2023" before
the end of this month, I'll give you
$10 off your next massage. =) I look
forward to seeing you on the table.