So, let's talk about server automation,
SaltStack edition.
Hey y'all, it's Markizano.
In this video, we're going to talk
about Minions and I can't believe
it, but I'm actually building
quite a library here.
I also have six other videos to
go check out if you're curious and
want to learn more about
SaltStack.
So, the SaltMinions job is an agent
that's running on your *server (excuse me),
on your server.
It can install the services that you
need, like say you're creating a generic
web application
set up, which requires an Nginx server
or Apache to be running, to forward
the request
down to some PHP, Python, Perl, some
application (Java even)
you are running
that may be talking to some database,
be it MySQL, MariaDB, some NoSQL solution
like CouchDB
or MongoDB, does not matter, SaltStack
will be able to go and install
it, configure it,
service it, and execute against it.
What's really cool about SaltStack
is you can use configuration directives
to describe
specifically how you want your server
to be set up and even with
its custom execution pipeline,
you can also execute custom commands
to get information from your servers
as well.
This stuff is really cool.
So here's a use case for the
execution pipeline.
Say you have a SaltMaster who's connected
to a set of Minions and we
want to find out
what version of Nginx is actually
installed on each of the machines.
From the SaltMaster, you can issue
a command to the Minions themselves.
The Minions will go and execute the
command, get the console output, return
that back to
the SaltMaster, and you get to see
that from a central console point
of view.
This gives you a central commanding
control center where you have full
control over every
specific aspect of your systems, and
as long as you can get the
developers out of the boxes,
you will have full control over your
entire setup.
It's really awesome.
Oh, what's also really cool is the
Salt setup has its own CRON built in.
So if you don't have CRON installed,
which is really unusual in a Linux environment,
probably more common in Windows-like
environments where you need something
to be executed at
specific intervals or scheduled to
execute at specific times.
SaltStack has a built-in engine that
is kept track with the clock so
that you can execute
things and schedule them at your own needs.
Generally speaking, the Minions are
present to ensure that there's a communication channel
between the SaltMaster and the host
itself upon which the Minion is running.
And so what this allows you to
do is it allows you to always
have something available so
that you can go and query information
off of a specific environment without
having to
SSH into every single box, which can
be very tedious.
I really hope this series on SaltStack
was helpful.
I plan on doing something more formal,
more proper on my YouTube channel
because I don't
like that I currently just take my
TikTok videos and post them to YouTube.
I want to create content that is
specific for the other platform, that
is destined for
the other platform with, you know,
the proper frame ratio.
So looking forward to publishing that
soon once I get enough of this
stuff written out
and out of my head.
This was just a crude means for
me to try and get the explanation
out and get awareness
set up so that other people can
get more involved in open source software
because I truly believe
that decentralization and open source
is the way to go.
My name is Markizano Draconus, and
I'm here to help you learn about
IT and technology.
And I look forward to seeing you
on the next video.
Thank you so much!