So, let's talk about server automation,
SaltStack edition.
In this video, we're going to talk
about what and how modules work.
And for reference, if you want to
go check out my introduction, my grains,
my states
and pillar, other videos that I may
have done on SaltStack, you're more
than welcome to
go check those out on my profile
as well.
So, if you're wondering what a SaltStack
module is, it is Python code execution
context for
whatever *Infrastructure you happen to be writing.
So, you can think of it as
the data structures basically define
and describe using a data
structure on how to execute something
in the environment.
For example, the `file.managed` part,
the file is the module that is created.
The managed is the function that is
invoked with the arguments provided
to it as the data
structure that is described proceeding
that file module description.
I also put standalone action in here
because it's really easy to turn a
custom module into
something that just does too much.
And so, I also say it can
also be code entry point, execution
entry point for any software
that you happen to be writing.
So, for example, one of the questions
that we oftentimes asked ourself was
how can we
be able to test the code that
we create that performs some kind
of operation?
Well, one of the things I thought
about doing in custom modules was
taking the APIs and
the code that we would otherwise write
in that modules directory and place
it inside
of a separate module, a separate pip
that was installed that was part of
a custom library.
I can get into that later.
I realize that just like kind of
blew it out of the water, but
as you dip into modules,
you come to find out that there's
a lot of Pythonisms available and
a lot of Python goody
like just like you can import full
-blown programs into your modules
if you're creating custom
modules.
So, let's have a look at that
module example.
You've got file at the root of
the file structure at the root of
the data structure here.
This is a YAML example and manage
is just one of the keys here
that is described.
I'm going to pause here for a
moment and point out file managed
as described by that is the
same thing as if you had file
.managed and described everything
the same as we're about
to go over right here.
If you have source set to some
salt location, it's going to look
on the salt master wherever
it says under the file serve and
it's going to create a file by
this name.
You can also create there's another
parameter for make directories if
you want to have it
make the directory leading up to this
file for you and then it's also
going to set the
permissions accordingly.
We also found out if you set
the permissions like this using the
leading zero to indicate
that there's no sticky bit explicitly.
Oftentimes this can get translated
into an integer when being read from YAML.
So we decided to create this as
a string and that seemed to carry
the meaning over into
the definition for the file permissions.
Now this is an example of a
function from the file module.
This is also a built-in module
to salt stack itself.
You can write custom modules that
do custom things for you and those
are the pieces that
I was describing if you wanted to
go beyond just making sure that a
file was present.
For example, I actually created custom
modules that perform the deployments
for us and we
had a specific order in which the
applications needed to be started
and that had to be pre-configured
or predestined based on certain things.
I was able to craft custom modules
that executed on the deployment for
us and we were able
to do this in a way that
didn't matter what flavor of Linux
was being used because we
had a few different flavors between
Red Hat and Debian and we needed
to be able to perform
the same operations regardless of
the kind or type of environment that
we were in.
Salt stack was really good at solving
that problem for us because among
the other tools
that basically do configuration as
code are able to deploy these things
in a way that
is uniform across the board.
One of the things that I really
loved about salt stack was its ubiquitous
way of invoking
itself so you could use salt call,
the module name, and then the arguments
that proceeded
after that to basically describe what
you wanted to invoke and you can
invoke it as a module
not necessarily as a state as well.
I would go and create custom modules
that basically say, take my app in
the dev environment
and deploy a version that we crafted
from Jenkins in order to make it
possible for this
app to be able to get a
version of itself out there.
I also thought this was a really
great way to ensure that deployments
got done consistently
and also because often times the steps
in which something needed to happen
may change
and so we would be able to
team up with the engineering team
to make sure that as the
necessary requirements were coming
in for the deployment itself that
we could also put
that as part of the release.
So if the process itself changed,
it was automated and could go through
the same review process
as the engineering team and DevOps
CloudOps would be able to make sure
that all the operations
were automated in synchrony with the
engineering team.
I thought this was a really great
implementation of salt stack as a
tool for not just server
automation but also process automation
to some extent.
So now that you kind of sort
of get the gist of how a
module works, here's the juicy part.
Say you're in an environment, say
you're in any environment, and you
have stuff going
on inside of your environment, be
it deployments, be it changes in permissions,
be it logs that
need to be extracted, there's some
operation that you perform in your
environment on a
routine basis and you had to automate it.
What custom module would you write
and what would it do?