So, let's talk about server automation,
SaltStack edition.
SaltStack is server automation software
that uses YAML, which is YAML
Ain't Markup Language (Yet Another Markup Language).
Imagine using YAML or a configuration
format to describe what you want your
server environment
to look like, and then being able
to just deploy your entire infrastructure
using description
format.
So, you don't need to SSH into
a server environment to install Nginx
and make sure that the service
is running.
You can just describe that you want
that to be created using a simple
configuration format.
This stuff is absolutely incredible.
So, let's take a closer look at that.
You've got a top.sls file, which
is the entry point into which these
things occur.
This is where you can match against
specific server names.
You can match against different grains.
You can match against different pieces
of information that a server should
have, and
if that server has that piece of
information, for example, a host name
for a specific server
or a specific grain that you want
for a specific piece of data point
that you have, you can
make sure that it is included in
the states that describe what the
server environment
is like.
And then in that state, in the
base.sls, which is teed off of
the state that's included here,
you can describe what kinds of services,
packages, files, anything you could
ever possibly want
to describe in a server environment
can be set in place using SaltStack,
or any automation
software we just happen to be covering here.
Chef, Ansible, and Puppet, they all
do the same thing, but different ways
in which these
things are done.
I'll go over those in other videos.
So, let's look at that in a
little bit closer detail.
You've got a top.sls file that
points out your server and says
`net.nginx` needs to be
included.
-- (excuse me)
What you end up doing is you can
create a directory
in the root of your salt project,
this is under the states, and you
can create nginx.sls.
(blah) -- The dot means that you
can create files inside of directories,
so anytime you
specify something with a dot inside
of the top.sls file, and you're
specifying states,
you can specify states under a subdirectory.
Now, personally, what I like to do
is, actually I'll talk about directory
structures in a
little bit.
For now, we'll talk about this file
and its contents, and I'll get into
more about specifically
how this stuff works.
So you create a directory, you create
an sls file called nginx, and this
creates the service,
so the package makes sure that it
gets installed, the service makes
sure that it keeps running,
and then the file makes sure that
it continues to be present, and this
configuration file
is written to disk, with the name
pointing to specifically where you
want the file to
be stored.
So let's step into that file.managed
context just a little bit further:
We're still inside
of the net.nginx.sls file,
or the salt state file
that describes how
we want nginx to be installed.
You have a file.managed, which you
can allow it to specify a source
using the `salt://`
which gives you access to the salt
file system, where you can find the
configuration template
for the particular configuration you're
trying to install.
You can set the mode on the
file to make sure that it's readable,
that the user and the
group are set, if it's not going
to be root, or it will default
to the running user of
the salt engine, and typically salt
runs as root.
Context specifies variables that you
want to give the template that will
render it so
that these values show up in place
of the template placeholders.
The template engine is jinja, but
it also provides support for some
other template engines
as well.
Now, I'm using an oversimplified configuration
template here for illustrative purposes so
that you can understand the contents
of the configuration file that we
have defined here.
You have your server block inside
of your nginx configuration, and the
server name
is using the template variable that
we created in the salt state itself.
And this allows us to create dynamic
templates that can render based on
whatever information
we provided it in the states.
Now, here's a part that threw me
off whenever I first started getting
started with SaltStack
was the organization of the
files themselves.
SaltStack is dynamic in that you
can specify a state, and when you
do, the .SLS is automatically
appended and a dot represents where
you can traverse in the file system
as far as placing
your states.
Now, some people probably had a flat
directory with all the states right
there at the top
level, all the files right there at
the top level as well, and I
thought that would be
kind of messy.
So, I organized things based off of
a top-level category.
At a bare minimum, everything, unless
it is baseline and is involved in
all the servers
and every server should have this,
unless you meet that criteria, then
you don't go
in the root of the file system.
You go in at least a subdirectory
that tries to categorize something
that I'm trying to
do in the infrastructure.
And then anything under that could
be application-specific, context-specific,
middleware-specific.
I place things inside of that directory.
So net, for networking, if it has
anything to do with DHCP, DNS, Nginx,
Apache, web servers,
HAProxy, if anything dealt with networking
and trying to stitch stuff together, then
it would go inside of a network folder.
If it was something that was baseline
to the system, if it was specific
to Linux, then
it would go in a Linux folder.
If it was something that was, you
know, even more, let's say security,
that would have
its own folder.
There's no real prescription around this.
It's more directive and organized
to your needs.
So what happens then is I create
another directory for containing everything
related to Nginx
specifically.
Nginx would have its top-level state,
it would have its own file, and
then there'd be a files
directory that contained the templates
that were related to Nginx.
So in this way, if anyone came
to the states and they wanted to
understand how the server
architecture worked, the top.sls would
be the main starting point to direct
people where
to go.
And then all of the subdirectories
and everything contained underneath
it would be in an organized
fashion so that folks would be able
to drill their way down to something
more specific
to what they're related to.
It's just a matter of understanding
that level of organization and whatever
you choose to
do.
Saltstack is free and open enough
that you can elect whatever you like.
I just created some patterns, some
guardrails to better describe some
of the formatting
that was left for open interpretation,
especially whenever Saltstack was
in its infancy.
So we're going to cover a little
bit of terminology before cutting
this video off, and then we're
going to talk about some other topics
in next videos coming up soon.
So states basically defines a state
in which the server environment shall exist.
You describe this in YAML.
You basically say, I want this service here.
I want it installed.
I want it running.
I want these files there.
I want this kind of setup and
architecture going for this particular
server environment.
And then any data that you need
to populate that server with, anything
that might be specific
to color it, design it, you know,
make sure it represents this website,
make sure it covers
this host name, make sure it has
this specific information inside of
this configuration file.
Data that needs to populate the state
of the server is used using the
pillar, a pillar
of salt, kind of sort of playing
on the same words, but the idea
is the same.
And then grains or a grain of
salt is a unique piece of information
that is derived from the
server and can be used within the
states to say, I'm unique, I'm special,
such as what
operating system is it running on,
how much RAM and CPU and other
physical resources are
available to the system.
What is the host name of the
system itself and anything else that
we can use to specifically
describe the server.
Grains can be used.
A lot of them are provided and
you can also create custom grains
as necessary in the configuration
of SaltStack and by dynamically assigning
them to server environments themselves.
If you want to learn more about
pillars and grains, you're going to
have to hit that follow
button and see my other videos and
I'll catch you on the next one.