So let's talk about server automation,
SaltStack edition! Now I thought this
was really ingenious whenever I was
first learning about it and it's just
really cool exploring how some of
these software tools work. So in a previous
video we covered the states, which
is basically description YAML that
describes what your infrastructure
is supposed to look like. But if there's
custom data or a custom information
that you want in order to properly populate
a template or to properly name a
file if it's part of an application that
you're building. The pillar is the
data that is used to encompass what
you can
place inside of your states. To make
a programming reference you could
think of
the states as like the program, the
PHP, the Python that defines the structure of
the application. The description in
data in a data structure format that
describes what your infrastructure
looks like. Infrastructure as code, but
not only as code, as data, as
a description object. And then the
pillar is yet another data structure
that describes information that's
supposed to populate the structure
that you're building. So this could
be like
the scaffolding that describes that
you want Nginx installed, you want this
file here, you want the servers running,
you want to have a schedule set,
you want
to make sure syslog is present, you
want to make sure that has this template
file. And then the pillar is what
populates the information that says okay
Nginx inside of this environment I
want you to watch after this hosting
because this is the dev environment.
And because the dev environment is
configured this way they're going
to need minimal throttling, they only need
one environment, they don't need any
backup, they don't need HA, we don't need
to describe a full structure. I can
describe a partial structure of what the
development environment needs for
a full stack for development and deployments.
And then for production that actually
has all of the HA, all of
the backups in
place, everything turned on, and the
pillar can describe the differences
between those two environments and
you only have to describe your environment
once. And you can deploy it multiple
times using different T's of a data
structure inside of the pillar. So
this is what's cool about the file structure
that is possible in Saltstack. You
have your top.sls that describes the
environments and says what gets what
states. Then you can either use nginx.sls
and Salt will honor that inside of
the top level. Although what I did
was I set
a pattern and said no instead of
referencing something.sls reference
the directory/init.sls. This
will ensure that everything is contained
within a folder and later if you
want to come back add files other states
neighbors so to speak you have a
directory and you don't have to change
it you can just do it. So
then inside of that Nginx directory
I can create a
files directory that contains all
the template files related to this
particular state that I'm building.
And in this way I have the base
configuration for Nginx and I also
have a template file for describing
a site.
So if I want to take if
I want to describe configuration for
a specific
site that I'm watching after in the
configuration for Nginx I can do that
and describe it here in the states.
And then likewise I can have a separate
state that does not have to be
included and can make it something
optional that
I also look at whenever I'm looking
at top.sls. Now here's something the
documentation doesn't exactly tell
you that you can do to make
your life easier
whenever you're dealing with salt.
The directory structure that I used to
describe the pillar mirrors that of
the states. This makes it easy and intuitive
so if anybody goes into the pillar
or the states they know generally
where they
can find stuff because the structures
will generally be the same. So you have
your top.sls which in my use
case I had known reason not to
use the same
exact top.sls so I just same
linked the both of them together and
said just make
sure you're referencing the same top
level things. And the Nginx directory
contains the init.sls file that is
needed to describe the baseline
configuration for describing this
particular setup of Nginx. And then the
site.sls reference this particular
site that I'm watching after. And if
there's a customer specific environment
that needs configuration specific to
their particular setup then I can
do that and change the site as
needed on a
per customer basis. I thought that
was pretty cool. So the documentation the
reference novels that describe what
all of these functions are in the
salt stack
documentation will tell you that you
can use your top.sls and your
Nginx and
your other SLS files to describe your
states. They'll tell you that you can
describe your data structure using
the pillar and that you can use
the top.sls
to reference whatever particular states
in pillar objects you want included in
your site. What the documentation
doesn't talk about is ways in which
you can
implement this such that it makes
sense and it's a little bit more
intuitive. And
it's something that can that can be
used to create either a monolithic
setup so
for example if I wanted to create
a per customer environment I could
do that
within the pillar and then just dynamically
pull in the information I
need whenever I'm in the states describing
how the server setup goes.
This is where all the jinja happens
and this is where all the logicing happens
whenever I'm thinking about should
I include this file should I not include
this file should it have this directive
you know is it production environment
should it have should it contain this
configuration I do all the if-then here
and I just describe a flat data
structure whenever I'm inside of the
pillar. By doing that it made it
so much easier to work with salt
stack and that
much more intuitive when it came to
designing a system that others would be
able to hop on board and say
okay how does this stuff work all
right read the
docs what's going on. This was a
way of describing some kind of a
pattern and
creating some kind of cadence because
if the pillar and states were also
committed to a github repository now
I had an automated way in which
I could
make a change to our infrastructure
commit push the repository the
repository would kick off a hook to
go update the salt master the salt master
would see the changes within a few
seconds and now the changes were
implemented in the environment they
were alive I could then invoke it
using salt
`salt-call state.highstate` won't
put it here sorry that was the other
thing that tripped me up it was
how do you get all this implemented
on the
server itself you use `salt-call state.highstate`
you run this command on
the minion itself and everything that
you've described based off of the top.sls
gets implemented on the host
itself you can also schedule this to
execute at regular intervals so that
your systems are constantly kept up to
date with the states but keep in
mind challenges are in place with that
because with automated deployment
of infrastructure comes with the need to
monitor things and so we can cover
monitoring in another video but how the
states and everything get on the server
invoking this call as a command-line
function running as root or as the
salt user if the salt user happens
to be
running as root then you'd be able
to actually invoke the things that
you need
in your server automation I don't
know I seem to know the salt
stuff pretty well
because I've worked with it for so
many years if you think I should
get a
certification in it drop a comment
below and I'll work on getting that