So, let's talk about Server Automation,
SaltStack edition.
If you're curious about the pillars
and the states, I did a video
on that.
If you're curious about how it actually
gets implemented in the environment,
I did a video
on that.
You should go check those out.
(If you care, I don't know.
I mean, it's just a thing.)
So let's talk about grains.
Grains in SaltStack are a unique piece
of information that identifies a host
for a specific piece
of information that it contains.
For example, how many processors this
host may have?
How much memory is available to the system?
What is the host name of this
particular machine?
Is it a virtual machine, a container,
or is it hardware?
And what was useful for our use
case was what kind of environment
is it in?
And also, what's the promotion path?
So not only which customer does this
environment belong to, but also is
it QA, is it DEV,
is it PROD?
It's good to know.
Is it a database server?
Is it a web application?
Is it a middleware service processing
unit, or is it a batch operation
that occurs asynchronously?
Having these grains inside of your
configuration can help you better
allocate what servers
and what resources belong to what pieces.
And what's also great is SaltStack
works great for both on-prem and cloud.
So if you're on-premises and your
servers are local right there in your
data center,
or you go to a co-location
center down the street, doesn't matter,
SaltStack will be
able to identify your entire inventory
and tell you what all they have,
and you can create
your systems and your setups accordingly.
So if you have a particular server
size or virtual machine size, you
can assign that
to a specific environment, and the
grains will allow you to execute certain states
on certain either types of hosts,
sizes of hosts, or whoever may have
certain resources
available.
So going back to our previous example
where we were installing Nginx, we
wanted to make
sure the package was present and installed,
that the service was set to running
by default
when the host came back online, or
whenever highstate ran and
made sure to enforce
the state of the server, and that
this particular file was managed,
and that it had a particular
template file that it was pointing
to inside of the SaltStack engine.
So let's take a look at that
file itself inside of /net/nginx/files/config.tpl.
Here we actually have the configuration
for the Nginx setup.
So we've got our server block here
that describes some site that it's
listening to on port 80.
The server name itself could be something
dynamic, and therefore you can place
Jinja extrapolations
to be able to articulate that this
is going to render a grain, or
a piece of the pillar,
depending on where your context sits
whenever you're describing the configuration
to have
it installed.
Now SaltStack does offer multiple
template engines.
The most common one is Jinja, so
I'll be using that for the examples
in this one.
If you want to learn more about
the other template engines like Mako,
and there's like
a couple of others out there I
can't rattle off the top of my
head, you can definitely
look into those.
You can definitely include those in
your configuration, and you know,
whatever template engine suits
your fancy is whatever you can do
with it.
What's nice about template engines
is they handle some of the bulk
decision making as
far as how to render your configuration.
So if we're sitting inside of our
config.tpl, and let's say we want
to check to see if dev
is in the fully qualified domain name (FQDN)
for this particular configuration
that we're setting
up, you can put an if statement
around that, and this text will only
render inside of the
configuration for the nginx file that
you're creating if this particular
condition matches.
So some of that previous work that
we've done on understanding how programming
works is
useful in server automation as well,
because there's programming scriptability whenever
you are automating your setup.
I mean, it's a programming language
from creating a template.
It's almost like a web server environment
for your infrastructure.
It's really cool.
I mean, what's also cool is that
you can use this templating engine
to your benefit.
For example, you can set up a
dynamic check to see if it's in
the development environment,
and if you wanted to, you could
also check to see which environment
it's in, and which
region, which part of the promotion
path it's a part of.
So like, for example, this environment
is customer A, and this particular
promotion path is
development, not QA, not UAT, not Production.
And then you can also match against
that particular domain for your specific company.
I think this is really cool, and
I think it's really powerful, because
it allows you to
have really dynamic configuration.
One of the caveats, though, that they
won't tell you about in the documentation
is that
you need to be careful.
With every added bit of complexity,
it makes it that much more difficult
for other developers
and engineers to ramp up.
And so I try to keep this
in mind, because while this capacity
and capability is available
to customize to your needs, because
when is business ever consistent enough
for us to
make coherent requirements and have
consistent configuration across the
board that never
changes?
Well, that's part of our job in
making sure that we can maintain some
kind of consistency
in place.
Because if business comes to you and
says, we need you to make these
changes, and you
say, well, these changes would induce
these costs.
These changes would induce this work,
and these changes would have us to
consider this
stuff going on here, then you'll be
able to bring that to the table
and have actual documentation
in place, or at least code as
documentation to support your backing.
One last little piece, I know I
just loaded you with a lot.
If you can document all of this
stuff outside of just code as infrastructure,
you also have
a company and documentation that can
go along with this as well, I
promise it is going to
help your case so much more.
Architecture diagrams go a long way.