Hey, welcome back. Remember this stuff?
If not, you're gonna have to go
check it out.
For those of you that are just
showing up: Welcome! My name is Markizano.
We're talking about SaltStack and
this is a continuation video of a
previous one
I did about the Salt Master, the
Salt Minions, and we left off on
the Salt Syndic.
If you haven't seen any of this
stuff before, I highly recommend you
go check it out. To give you
a quick recap here,
we've got the Salt Master, which is
presiding over the Salt Minions, and
it controls the environments around
what you have set up going on here.
Sometimes you run into places where
you've got a few Salt Masters that
need to be controlled because
the Salt Master is a constraint and
can cause you to have an environment where
you just can't control everything.
You hit a ping out there, you
do something, and you don't include
a batch operation,
and then your Salt Master spends the
next 20 minutes responding to a simple
data collection request.
So what we did to solve that
problem was we took advantage of the
Salt Syndic.
What the Salt Syndic did, it was
like a master of masters.
It was a coordinator, an expediter
of sorts, that allowed us to be
able to continue the chain of command
in a hierarchical type of environment
such that
we'd have multiple Salt Masters commanding
their local environment and the Salt
Syndic would be able to synchronize
commands and other information between
the Salt Master and the person invoking
the command from the command center.
This is where the documentation teaches
you what you can do, but doesn't
exactly show you /how/ to do.
I'm going to go through that right now.
Now, I know the rabbit hole goes
deep with this one.
I know this can look really complicated
when if it's not done correctly, but
if you bear with me here,
this is just for example, this is
to help you better understand how
this stuff works.
Implement the solution or the tools
for your specifications and what works
best for you.
This is just an example of how
it can work.
So you've got a Salt Master, which
is like the master of the masters.
This contains all the core configuration
and everything that is needed to describe
everything you could possibly need.
The Salt Master of Masters talks to
the Salt Master Syncdics or the
Salt Syncdic.
The Salt Syncdic is strictly just there.
It's like a minion that listens for
commands from the Salt Master, but
it immediately passes them off to
other Salt Masters. And those Salt
Masters can control the minions of
their local environments.
And so if I were to set
this up again, if I were to
redo what I have done in the past,
it would be to set this up
separate so that you have a master
which basically commands Syncdics
and each of these are set up
per customer.
And I would have different configurations
per customer that would enable us
to have
whatever desperate setups we needed
in order to serve our customer environments
such that you didn't have a giant
massive configuration
that you know, if I make a
change to one customer it affects
another customer because we didn't
think through the possibility of
Oh crap, installing this dependency
here changes the dependencies that
are here and this application actually
needed this version of this
back-end library and oh, and you
know, oh crap, we upgraded that here now
You know it you can see how
it becomes dependency hell
so by
partitioning these things off
It allows us to set things up
in a way so that they're kind
of sort of isolated in their own place
And we still get to
control these things from a perspective
And each of the customers get their
own configurations for their own pillar
and states
So i'm going to stop this one
right here because syndic is a complicated
enough thought as it is
I'll let you go ahead and flick
on to your next video. I'll see
you on the next one
We're going to cover minions in the
next video and I'll see you in
the next one!
My name is Markizano Draconus, and
I hope you're enjoying learning about
DevOps, CloudOps and all these other
fun things
Thank you so much. Love you, and
we'll see you on the next one! ;)