So let's talk about Server Automation:
SaltStack Edition. =)
Hey guys, it's Markizano, and in this
video we're going to talk about the
SaltMaster and the SaltMinion.
And if you want, and you're curious
about this, you can learn more about
SaltStack, some grains, some pillar
and states,
and modules videos that I've done
in the past, just if you want
to check them out.
So, the SaltStack infrastructure is
based on a Master and Minion setup,
where the Master receives information
from the pillar, from the states that
you create,
and the grains from the SaltMaster
itself, and also from any of the
Minions, if it wants to consider them.
And use that to take that description
data structure that you created,
in the states, in the pillar, combine
all that into a set of instructions,
that go and implement those instructions
on each of the Minions.
So, in a Master-Minion setup like
this, you can have an Nginx server,
a PHP server, and a MySQL database,
just as an example.
Yes, I know, my art is just
glorious, that's a scale. ;)
So, in this setup, you can have
a SaltMaster sit here and contain
all this information that is a description here.
And then what's cool, is you can
have multiple web services that are
basically the load balancer,
that balances the application's activities,
as the request gets sent to the
application itself.
And then the application communicates
with the database, so that all that
information can communicate.
However, what's really nice, is all
of that infrastructure can be defined
and described just using a data structure.
That is what makes this so cool,
is you no longer have to go
SSH into the server,
app get install Nginx, configure Etsy
Nginx, blah, blah, blah.
Go and configure each of the sites,
set all that stuff up.
Maybe you have a template, maybe you don't.
The application itself could require
additional steps to get that application deployed.
It may have additional dependencies.
Your database server needs to be set up.
It's got to have sufficient disk space.
It needs to have sufficient configuration
in place.
And yes, I know there's Amazon RDS,
but still, you know, there's things
that you can do with Salt,
that allow you to be able to
set this stuff up in an automated fashion.
And using just a data structure.
It's really cool.
And then what I think is really
cool is that with the next step up,
what you will be doing is you'll
be creating a dev environment, a QA
environment, a UAT environment, and
a production environment.
And the Salt master will be able
to command and control the description
for all of these.
You simply write the states once to
describe how you want the environment
set up.
You use the pillar to populate it
with the data so that it knows
to watch DEV, QA, UAT, and PROD.
And then you can set the configuration
up and say, here is a release
of the infrastructure as it was,
as it were, the day that we
decided to perform the deployment.
And what's also really cool is with
the states in the pillar being flat
data structures,
what you can do is you can
take the states in the pillar, put
those inside of a Git repository.
Now you have history. Now you have
versioning. Now you have control.
Now you know who changed what.
Now you have a clear description of
your environment and your infrastructure
without having to wonder,
oh crap, did I SSH into that
server and make that change to that file?
Oh crap, what was that file name?
Because guess what?
These servers, they're transient.
They die.
Something can happen. The disk fails.
Suddenly Amazon revokes your access.
Somebody didn't pay the bill and now
the servers have been deleted and
taken offline.
Somebody else from another department
didn't know that you still needed
this environment
and ended up deleting those servers.
I don't care.
As long as the configuration is stored
within the Salt Master and stored
within Git,
just as a means by which I
can use to keep track of all
this infrastructure configuration,
it doesn't matter. Delete the environments.
I don't care. I can use the
salt master and craft a new one
in a cinch.
Now you've got your one master setup
and you've got your one environment setup.
This works really great for one customer.
Say you have multiple customers.
Say customer XYZ has got a few
changes that are different from customer ABC.
And say it's different enough that
it's not just data, it's structure.
They require a different app.
The different app's got to be set
up a different way.
It needs these dependencies instead.
It's got to be on a Red
Hat box rather than a Debian box.
I don't know.
People come up with all kinds of
requirements like crazy.
And so what's nice about SaltStack
is yes, it can handle this.
However, the way that I implemented
it in the past was this was
done using the same salt master.
If I were to go back and
redo it, I would say one salt
master per customer.
So one salt master per cluster of
setup that you've got going on.
One release that can be inside of
one Git repository.
And if there's another customer that
comes in that needs a desperately
different setup,
then I would set them up on
their own Git repository with their
own salt master.
Possibly copying states between as
needed in order to set the infrastructure up.
And then would have them on their
own release, their own cadence, so
that they had their own freedom
as far as how their infrastructure
made it out into the environments.
Also, generally speaking, we found
that it depends on what you're doing
with SaltStack
and what you're doing with the masters
and the minions
and as far as how much communication
is happening in this kind of a setup.
But there is a constraint on the
salt master itself.
In my experience, more than a thousand
minions will drag your salt master down.
Especially if you don't have the computing
power for the salt master
to be able to compile the configuration
that is needed for each of the minions
that are going to be asking for
the data from the salt master
so that they can populate their state
inside of each of the environments.
Enter the salt syndic.
And I guess that's all you're going
to get for this video.
If you want to keep in touch,
go ahead and hit that follow up button.
I've got some more videos coming out.
And looking forward to seeing the
rest of ya'll. Thank you so much.
My name is Markizano Draconus, and
I'm here to teach you about IT, DevOps,
and all these fun things.
Look forward to seeing you on the
next one. Thanks!