Hey guys, it's Markizano.
If you're using Linux and you're on
Devuan, you may have noticed they
had an upgrade recently.
I'm a little late to the post
here, but if you wanted to upgrade
in place without a
new install, here's how you would
do it.
Make sure to have a backup of
your systems before you begin.
Always have a backup.
Yeap.
Next, you're going to update your
package list here with `apt-get update`
and `apt-get upgrade`.
This is going to install the latest
packages and ensure you are up to
date with the latest
patches for the current version of
your operating system.
The last thing you want is for
your system to be trying to skip
an update and trip over
itself performing the update, and
then your server ends up in surgery.
Let's not have an apt-get surgery ;)
It's very painful!
Next, you're going to disable your
foreign packages and repositories
by commenting all
the files in /etc/apt/sources.list.d/*
This will ensure that no foreign software
interferes with the upgrade process.
Again, we're trying to avoid that
apt-get surgery, remember?
Once you have your repositories commented
out, let's edit the sources.list file,
the main
file and reduce it down to the
very main repository and change the
destination from
Chimaera to Daedalus.
Save the file and exit your text editor.
Now you're going to update your local
repository cache with `apt-get update`.
First, we need to install the latest
dpkg and version of aptitude, so
`apt-get install dpkg apt`
to install those.
This was a pattern introduced to ensure
that the latest updates from the upstream
are used
for the upgrade as opposed to the
current version, whereas before you
would just upgrade
from here.
Once this is done, you will have
the latest versions of the Debian-based
package managers.
You may see a prompt about news.
This is a lesspipe, so you
can navigate using the arrow keys,
you can use the space bar
for the next page, and Q for
leaving the message.
Take note of what they have to
say here, though.
Oftentimes, developers are making
updates and this is how you get
to see what changes
are coming in so you can take
action accordingly in your system.
As the system upgrades, it will ask
you about services that need to be
restarted and files
that may need to be replaced if
you change them or if you want
to just leave them be.
I forgot to include the options that
mandate the aptitude leave the system
as is, so know
that there are ways of suppressing
these messages and these actions,
and also know that without
those updates to your system, you
may require some additional tweaking
to get it working
with the latest software.
So be on the lookout for any
failed services that fail to restart
during this update.
When you finish with the upgrade,
you may get some additional helpful
information to
know about your system.
For example, I was relieved to find
out that you had to set a
kernel option now to enable
net.ifnames, as depicted here.
I was so upset when they decided
out of nowhere to change our network
interface names on us.
"#eth0" in the comments if you agree.
Now comes the part where it takes
some time to upgrade the system.
For this part, I like to ensure
that I'm running in a screen session
if I'm SSH'd
into a server, because I've been disconnected
mid-upgrade and let me tell you,
that is not sexy...
Now, this time we're going to use
`apt-get dist-upgrade`.
This will do a deep inspection of
your package listing and ensure that
all packages are upgraded
to the latest versions.
It will also remove old and unused
packages, whereas `apt-get upgrade`
may leave some things
out and kind of sort of do
a sloppy job.
Again, after downloading packages,
it'll print the news.
There's a few bullet points, though,
that I wanted to call out here:
1.) isc-dhcp-server:
They are stopping maintenance on their
client part, so I'll have to find
an alternative
to dhclient.
2.) nfs-utils is no longer using /etc/default/*
for its configuration.
Instead, use `/etc/nfs.conf.d/local.conf`
3.) There's a lot of updates coming in
for SSH, but basically, we're getting
better hashing
algorithms and more secure configurations.
4.) You'll no longer need to quote interglob
SCP results when targeting on the remote...
That is fantastic.
I cannot tell you how many times
I've tried to SCP a file and
get caught by that glob pattern.
5.) The OpenSSL upgrade breaks how OpenVPN
works, so it will need some configuration changes
for encryption ciphers to continue working.
6.) fgrep and egrep are no longer a
thing, so use the respective flags
when using grep.
Once you've consumed all the updates,
use "q" to exit from the lesspipe.
And we're off and running to the upgrade.
You may have to confirm your keyboard
character set and maybe answer a couple
of other questions
on the upgrade.
And after that, the upgrade will tarry
on quite nicely if all goes jolly.
This isn't actually how fast it goes,
but... you get the idea.
After the package upgrade is complete,
I like to peek around at the
new versions of the
software I have and make sure the
package managers are nice and tidy.
You can do this with
`apt-get autoremove` and `apt-get autoclean`.
Autoremove will remove old packages
that are obsolete, not in use, or
otherwise not
necessary on your system.
(No longer a dependency).
Autoclean will delete the debian
packages downloaded to your local
computer's cache.
You don't need those consuming your
precious disk space!
Once I see that no packages are
left needing upgrading or cleaning,
I will open up the
`sources.list` to replace the other
repositories for security updates
and such.
Since we updated `sources.list`, we'll
need to run `apt-get update` once
more to refresh
the package cache.
Now, we are going to run one
more `apt-get dist-upgrade` in order
to ensure security updates
and other updates are installed successfully
and to completion.
This may be a smaller list of
packages that need update and a little
more minimal than
what you just did with the full upgrade.
Finally, I will go into `sources.list.d`
and enable all of the foreign
package repositories
from before and edit them to ensure
they are on the compatible version
of software for
the version of Linux that I am running.
You know the drill by now.
We edited `sources.list`, so we need
to run one more `apt-get update`
to refresh
the package list and the package manager
knows where to find all the packages.
Then we can use `apt-get upgrade`
to ensure those packages are up to date.
But first, here's something tricky
about aptitude that gets a lot of
people since
it's a change in behavior.
The GPG keys are no longer in
a trusted.gpg keyring in the configuration.
Instead, each package can store their
keys in `/etc/apt/trusted.gpg.d`.
So you can run `gpg --no-default-keyring
--keyring /etc/apt/trusted.gpg
-a (for ascii armored export)
--export [KEY]`
and then, pipe it to a dedicated
file in the trusted.gpg.d directory
as depicted here.
I have three keys to copy out
of the keyring, so you'll see me
do that now for MongoDB,
NodeJS, and Docker.
Once the keys have been exported from
the keyring and into their own dedicated file,
the subsequent invocation of
`apt-get update` should yield no warnings about
the keys in
the keyring.
Now you can `apt-get upgrade` or
`apt-get install` the software as needed
to get to the latest versions.
With that, you're done, and all the
updates is set.
It's time to reboot into your newly
upgraded system.
I use `shutdown -F` to
force check the file system on the
next boot, and then
`shutdown -r now` to say reboot.
You can also say `shutdown -h now` for
halt/shutdown.
And that will check to make sure
everything is okay on the next boot.
Thank you so much.
Hope this was helpful.
Save it for later, follow for more,
and we'll see you on the next one.