Okay, so here's a diatribe of my
own to share:
So many people around me do stupid
stuff to get attention.
What is attention but the idea that
someone is looking at you?
And what kind of attention do you want?
Do you want the loving kind that
kisses you on the forehead at night.
A strong hug to
remind you that you are loved. A
kindred look of adoration and admiration?
Or do you want the kind of
attention where one is angry with
you because that's the only
kind of attention that you get. The
kind that zaps energy from others,
especially if you
love them. The kind of attention where
one looks at you with contempt and disdain?
All that matters is energy.
Do you want energy of abundance or
energy of scarcity?
It also boils down to how much
energy and what kind of energy do
you feed yourself?
What do you feed yourself with?
When my co-workers don't pay attention
to me, a younger me would fumble
around with
things like: "They don't care about
me!" ...and... "I'm going to get laid
off from work if I don't
work!" ...and... "I'm not worth anything if
I'm not doing something!"
The present me now says, if they
don't pay the same attention I give,
then I simply won't
pay them as much attention.
It's an equal exchange, you see.
By paying me attention, it's like
they are showing appreciation for
my time, my efforts,
and my attention.
Besides, I have plenty to pay my
attention towards that serves me in
place of those I'm
appealing for attention.
It also comes from a place of,
"I am sufficient, I am enough."
When my friends don't pay me attention,
I simply go about my day as
if they never existed.
In reality, in that moment, they don't.
In that moment, I have my desires,
my goals, my accomplishments to achieve
that one day
someone may write about them in my obituary.
And when my friends do pay me
attention, I return the favor.
I am present because they matter.
When you reach that place of believing
in yourself enough to love yourself, suddenly
the world changes.
Suddenly you are no longer the victim
of a lack of attention from others.
When you become your own source of
power, your own battery, and your
own plug, you notice
that people act differently around you.
You no longer have time for flakes
and fakes.
They seem to find another place to
leech upon.
When you are sufficient, suddenly
you think from an abundance mindset
rather than a scarce
one.
Patience is an interesting one as well.
Patience is simply doing something
else while you wait for whatever it
is you want to be
complete or available.
Patience goes a long way.
A pause can go a long way.
Allow time to pass such that the
universe can work its magic.
Because time is magical.
Time is precious.
How much of your time will be
spent in a scarce mindset and how
much of it will you live in
abundance?
There are two things in life that
are stolen the most:
That is your time and attention.
Choose wisely how you decide you will
spend them.