So I might make some friends and
enemies and frenemies with this one. ;)
Let's talk
about PID 1 on Linux. Way back
in the day we only had two
options, sysv-init
and upstart. Even before then
there were fewer options than that
as far as
what you could use to initialize the
system. How does the computer boot and
how does it know where the monitor
is, where the hard drive is, where
the PCI
bus is, how to find all those
things, talk to the memory circuits
and be able
to, store data in there.
How much processor power is available and
communicating with it and organizing
all this information, how to store
it on
the disk. There's a lot that's
involved with booting your computer up
and just getting it going so that
once it is connected to the graphics
card, the
monitor, the hard drive, and all the
peripherals, and the Bluetooth, and all
the devices, and the microphone, and
the headset, and everything that you
use to
talk to your computer. Yeah, process
one has got to kick off all
those things,
connect to all those pieces, and then
start allowing you to be able to
interface with those things. Process
one is what stands above the kernel which
is the actual decision maker, the
real brain behind the computer. Process
one is
what you can use to start in
Linux. Sysv-init, Upstart, they're both pretty
similar in their setups. Upstart requires
just a little bit different
configuration. It's like bash but
not really bash. Where is that OpenRC
That's open RC. Sysvnit is the
most common and most of the
distributions in Linux would use Sysvnit
as the main process one
option that you would use in Linux.
You also have the option for Upstart,
so if
you knew that, the way you would
start and stop your services was a
little bit
different. Let me see if I can
throw some examples up for you. And
so from a user's
perspective, you just had to know
what command, or style, or way of
being able to
start and stop service would enable
you to be able to manage the
system. Upstart
had its own way to do things.
OpenRC had its own way of doing
things. Systemd
had its own way of doing things
as far as starting and stopping services. And
from a package management perspective,
you know, from a developer's perspective, if
you're developing a piece of software
and you want to be able to
deploy that
piece of software in a Linux type
of environment, you had to package your
application so that it would work
with all of these different kinds
of systems.
Now, this is the part that's probably
gonna ruffle some feathers, but hey, it
needs to be said. Sysvnit, it worked.
Probably because it stood the test of
time. Probably because it had so much
contributions and it got to a point
where it was like, alright, we know
that these are the limitations of this
particular type of setup, but it works.
You basically had shell scripts that sat
inside of a directory, they were registered
with this service command, it
found those services that you had
inside of that directory, and basically
you had
start and stop switches that you could
tell the service to start and stop. It
was great. On a Linux box, you
can start, you can stop your service,
have a nice
day. Upstart said you had to run
it a little bit different. OpenRC
also had
its own way of starting and stopping
the services, but those scripts were
not the
same as what was supported by these
two systems. These scripts were
sort of bash, but not really. It
was its own OpenRC DSL, domain specific
language, that kind of sort of sat
on as a layer and you had
to use their shell
scripts or you could use your own
bash scripts or any type of executable, but
they offered it as an option and
it was something that also provided
a lot of
the same functionality that I saw
Systemd trying to handle as far as
trying to
create a consistent ecosystem and
a consistent environment in which the
developer doesn't have to worry about
any of the differences or deltas that
would exist as far as hardware is
concerned, because you shouldn't.
As a
developer, when I go to write my
code, I shouldn't have to care about
whether you
have an Intel or an AMD processor.
I shouldn't have to care if you
have, you
know, two cores or 32 cores. I
should be able to write my program
and it can
describe what its boundaries are and
the computer will automatically figure out
how much capacity it can allocate
to my program and I don't have
to do
calculations from within my scripts
and programs to be able to talk
to the
processor specifically, unless I want
to take advantage of those specific
adapters, drivers or capabilities
within that processor. Well, then
came along James
Pottering and he decided to release
Systemd and the challenges that I faced
with this was not only was the
implementation not a single focus
on a
single responsibility, it was a responsibility
that globbed into so much
of the Linux ecosystem that just polluted
this idea of do one thing and do
it well. That was one of the
things about Linux and one of the
reasons why it
worked was because its whole paradigm
is based on this idea of a
single principle
of responsibility and you assign that
to a single algorithm that describes what
that particular thing is supposed
to do and that way you can
build upon that
and it's a modular component that
can be reused through other components within
the system. And one of the reasons
why I feel like Systemd had such
a struggle
coming, I'm being really nice, why
Systemd was shit software for its
beginnings, it's it's it was because
if you saw some of the email threads
between Pottering and Torvalds, I
see what he was trying to do,
it's just
the way he went about it was
just, and it shows in its implementation
and its
bugginess and the way it has this
weird kind of, what are you really
doing? Because I
have a two-way firewall, my traffic
is not blocked just inbound, my traffic is
also blocked outbound as well, so
when I see things hit the inside
of my firewall
that normally should not be hitting
the inside of my firewall, I go
snooping and
trying to figure out where is it
coming from because I want to know,
I must know
and when I come to find that
my operating system was the source
of the network
traffic, we got issues. Systemd, why
the hell are you reaching out to
China and
Russia and Microsoft? Why are you
sending information up to them? Why
are you
talking to them by default? Where
was that coming from? When I found
out that
it was because of misconfigurations
and all kinds of personal stuff that they
had going on, I stepped away. I
said I have I want nothing to
do with that
project and none of my servers will
touch it and if I can help
it I'm gonna
keep on you know our job from
having to deal with that nonsense
until it has a
chance to mature because clearly this
project needs to stand the test of time
before I'm willing to put a leg
on it and when I saw systems
like Debian and
Ubuntu go and adopt Systemd, I didn't
agree with how they went about that
either. I didn't like how it was
this is now going to be the
default and no we
are not going to support anything
but Systemd going forward. Like whose
authoritarianship came through and
just swept in it freedom from everything? So
this is why I use Dev1 is
because we forked away from Debian
which is the
original predecessor to Ubuntu. Dev1
is a fork of Debian that maintains your
freedom. You may choose any of these
that you like. If you want Systemd
you can go
to Debian but if not we maintain
the option for you to be able
to select
process 1 in your system and so
for those of you that don't know
Debian is
the original operating system. Ubuntu
is a fork of that. Also Kubuntu, Shubuntu,
Mint, Ubuntu Mint, all the other Ubuntu
derivatives they're all forks of Ubuntu
and Ubuntu is a fork of Debian.
Debian is the original OG. Red Hat
is also the
original OG and they gave way to
CentOS which for some reason they
just dropped
support off of that and Fedora which
is another Red Hat based operating system
that you can use for desktop that's
based off of the K desktop environment.
Dev1 is a fork of Debian that
offers the option for you to be
able to select
process 1 in your operating system.