Oh, you're not gonna want to miss
this one. Let's talk about cross-site
request forgery.
This is a scary one. You're gonna
want to know about this one, I'm
telling you.
Say you're just cruising in the website,
cruising the web like normal. You
visit your bank,
you log in, you check your balance.
Okay, fine. Everything's good. You
close the tab.
You didn't log out. You get an
email. Your account's been locked
down. It looks like
it's from your bank or from Coinbase
or some site. I don't know. It
catches your attention
just enough to get you to click
on it impulsively. Oh, shit. I went
to the site. It got redirected
real quick and then blank page. I
don't know what happened. I guess
I'm okay.
I didn't, I didn't, you know, I
clicked on the link. The link didn't
do anything. I guess the
hacker's attempt failed, right? Nah.
Next day you go back to your
bank account. You find out
it's been drained. Why? Cross-site
request forgery means somebody else can
make your workstation do something
on your behalf. You visited the website.
They bounced
off your workstation. They bounced
the request off your workstation because
you visited it.
You clicked on it. You went to
the site. Your cookies are there.
All they gotta do is say,
hey, bank, can you send all these
dollars over to this account over
here? Bank's like, hey,
looks like you asked for it. You
just logged in. You didn't log out.
Sure, why not?
Cross-site request forgery is whenever
someone invokes access where they
shouldn't have it.
Where they shouldn't because they're
not authenticated because they aren't
you. But
guess what? They took advantage of
you and used you to send your
money elsewhere. That's a scary
prospect, isn't it? You'd want to
pay attention to that, wouldn't you?
For one, I'm going to tell
you right now that logout button is
there for a reason. You should use
it because it clears your
sessions and tells the server that
you are done with the website and
makes it so that whatever
authentication tokens you have or
had have since been revoked. Don't
rely on the site to log you
out over the next 15 minutes or
so. One way to mitigate against this
is as time goes on through
the user's visit through your application,
they may attempt to, when they first
visit your site,
they're going to get back a cookie
that gives them your session cookies
so you know who they are.
That's the whole notification button
at the bottom. GDPR says that you
now have to notify
people whenever this cookie shows
up or that you use this cookie
to keep track of them while
they're on the site. Then when the
user tries to log in, MFA or
multi-factor authentication is
then used to verify that the user's
login or the submitted token that
was sent during the login
is actually correct. An alternative
way to solve this and I would
even just add it on as additional
security is using a CSRF token or
an XSRF token, which basically is
a randomly generated piece of
data that you send to the browser.
When the user makes a login and
sends that information back,
it's sent back as a hidden field.
You give the user an invisible piece
of data that only you
know they have. They must send that
back to you in order to make
sure that they are the person
who's actually making the request
and that token expires within 5, 10,
15 minutes. Such that you end
up with a situation where this user
has been given a piece of information
that can only be used once
and can only be used during a
specific period of time. Once they've
attempted to log in,
that token may no longer be repeated.
That token may no longer be used again.
And that's another means by which
you can try to protect against CSRF
attacks. Another way is
CAPTCHA. Another way is the authentication
tokens. Another way is the YubiKeys.
In closing, this is why
it is absolutely critical that you
set up multi-factor authentication
so that whenever
anybody tries to perform anything
on your behalf, it's done with those
tokens that you have saved
to your multi-factor authentication
application, device, whatever you
happen to be using.
Please stay safe, change your passwords
on a regular basis, and I'll see
you on the next video.