If you want the text version of
this, you can go to my blog
at blog.markizano.net.
There I've got the instructions on
a post that I just recently made
on how to connect
to Wi-Fi in Linux using just
two commands, `wpa_supplicant` and `dhclient`.
If you're ever in a situation where
your network manager isn't behaving
or if you want to explore
more about how you connect to a
Wi-Fi network in Linux without using
a network manager,
you can use these commands to help
get a better understanding of what
happens under the hood
when it comes to connecting to a
wireless network.
You simply have to make sure that
some packages are installed.
It does include a couple more steps,
but I think it's worth it for
the control that I
get over being able to connect to
the network.
You can use `wpa_passphrase` to create
the Wi-Fi key that this client
will use to perform the
encryption.
Connecting to the wireless network
uses `wpa_supplicant`.
This handles the heavy lifting as
far as encryption and decryption and
talking to the router itself
so that whenever you're talking to
the wireless router, you don't have
to worry about using
any keys or doing any kind of encryption.
This does it for you.
And then finally, you'll get the IP
address using dhclient.
This will allow you to actually communicate
with other devices on the network.
It's interesting because the way Linux
works is you "Do one thing, and
you do it well."
You've got one thing that actually
talks to the Wi-Fi router itself,
and it breaks that
down separate from getting an IP address
and routing yourself within that network after
the encryption has already been decrypted.
If you have any questions or if
you have any issues, I included some
additional tips that
you should check out in case because,
well, I ran into these problems myself.
And also, I've got some scripts on
Gist GitHub where you can totally
customize this and
make it a service.
If you want to have some fun,
install it on your system, make sure
those programs are
there installed, and voila, service
start and stop Wi-Fi.
It'd be awesome.
Let me know what you think in
the comments.
Looking forward to seeing you.
Cheers!